<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="MIWschema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to <persName key="garlandM">Maria Garland</persName>
				</title>
				<author>
					<persName key="lili">Lili Ilse Elvenes</persName>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation completed on <date when="2017-11-26">26 November 2017</date>
					</resp>
					<persName ref="kj">Kristin Jacobsen</persName>
					<persName ref="mb">Maiken Boysen</persName>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoding updated on <date when="2018-11-05">05 November 2018</date>
					</resp>
					<persName ref="tnm">Tyler Monaghan</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p>Publication Information</p>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Information about the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<!-- tnm 10/19/2018: unsure as whom Herr Oberartz should be tagged. It seems contextually like warnekros but gebhard and doctorHead both appear in the schema as well, and it's not clear to me which to use -->
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>

			<div type="original">

				<div type="opener">
					<p>
						<add place="pageTopLeftCorner" type="insertion" rend="red-pencil">Mein Brief</add>
						<note type="editor" source="kj mb">Written in red ink in top left corner.</note>
					</p>
					<p>18 August 1931</p>
					<p>
						<placeName key="dresden">Dresden.</placeName>
					</p>
					<!-- the period after Dresden is not in the translated word doc but seems clearly there on the image to me -tnm -->
				</div><!-- end "opener(original)" div -->

				<div type="body">
					<p style="salutation">Kære Veninde.</p>
					<p>
						<persName key="warnekros">Professoren</persName> synes godt om Begyndelsen. Han har kun nogle rent lokale<note type="translator">The phrase "rent locale" is literally "purely local."</note> Indvendinger at gøre – og vil formulere dem for mig en af de første Dage.
					</p>
					<p>Samtidig vil han give mig sin <placeName>hemmelige Adresse</placeName>. Sagen<note type="translator">Sagen could also be translated as thing, but that would be a more modern usage.</note> er, han rejser i Slutningen af Ugen bort i Ferien – og her kender man saa ikke hans Adresse. Det er for at faa Fred.</p>
					<p>Dertil kan vi altsaa sende de følgende Kapitler Jeg kan godt forstaa paa ham, at han tror Bogen vil vække en uhyre Opsigt i <placeName key="germany">Tyskland</placeName> – saa snart nu Forholdene atter bliver rolige.</p>
					<p>Mit eget Helbred bringer mig til Fortvivlelse. Jeg synes slet ikke det gaar fremad – og mit skønneste Haab er Døden. Kun ved jeg, at det faar jeg ikke Lov til, fordi Professoren ikke vil – og han er saa stærk.</p>
					<p>Mit Ønske med Bogen er en lille Revision af <hi rend="underline">
						<persName key= "warnekros">Herr Oberartz</persName>
						</hi>. Sidste Aar kendte jeg ikke al hans Mildhed og Barmhjærtighed. Han har
						<pb />reddet mig fra alle de værste Rædsler – <hi rend="underline">og jeg vil altid skamme mig dybt</hi>, om der i min Bog stod et Ord, han kunde<note type="translator">This was the correct spelling before 1948. It is the same in From Man Into Woman.</note> blive ked af. Altid er han saa god og mild imod – og altid parat at <del type="strikethrough">stille</del>
						<note type="translator">Danish and German word for alleviate.</note> dæmpe mine Smærter. Og de<note type="translator">Should be the formal "De." Lili is most likely tired and recovering from surgery.</note> aner ikke hvor højt man kommer til at elske en saadan Mand. </p>
					<!--tnm:2018-10-14 after af. there is a blank space, should I use <gap> here? -->
					<!-- something seems wrong with the above line - not picking up closing tags for last translator note or p -->
					<p>Jeg haaber, De faar stor Glæde af Deres Begyn-delse paa <placeName key="theatreRoyal">det Kongelige</placeName> – og kommer jeg engang saa vidt, vilde det være herligt at se Dem spille der en Aften.</p>
					<!-- tnm:2018-10-4: line above, Begyn-delse (beginning) is hyphenated across lines (doesn't look like a hyphen to me, more of an underscore_)  -->
				</div> <!-- end body (original) div -->

				<div type="closer">
					<p style="valediction">De hjærteligste Hilsner til Dem og Deres Mand. Deres hengivne</p>
					<p>
						<persName key="lili">Lili Elvenes</persName>
						<note type="?">Flourish under signature.</note>
					</p>
				</div> <!-- end closer(original) div -->

				<div type="postscript">
					<p>Undskyld Brevenes<note type="translator">Should be brevets form if she is referring to this letter, but she also could be referring to all her recent letters.</note> Form!</p>
					<p>Jeg er altfor træt.</p>
				</div> <!-- end postscript (original) div -->
			</div> <!-- end original div -->

			<div type="translation">

				<div type="opener">
					<p>
						<add place="pageTopLeftCorner" type="insertion" rend="red-pencil">My Letter</add>
						<note type="editor" source="kj mb">Written in red ink in top left corner.</note>
					</p>
					<p>18 August 1931</p>
					<p>
						<placeName key="dresden">Dresden.</placeName>
					</p>
					<!-- the period after Dresden is not in the translated word doc but seems clearly there on the image to me -tnm -->
				</div>
				<!-- end "opener(translation)" div -->

				<div type="body">
					<p style="salutation">Kære Veninde.</p>
					<p>
						<persName key="warnekros">The professor</persName> thinks well of the beginning. He only has some objections here and there to make – and will formulate them for me in the next few days.
					</p>
					<p>At the same time he will give me his <placeName>secret address</placeName>. The case is, he travels at the end of the week on vacation – and here one doesn’t know his address. It is [for him] to be left in peace.</p>
					<!-- tnm:2018-10-14 again, not sure where to place the translator's note or handle the [] -->
					<p>So there we can send the following chapters. I can understand that he thinks the book will create an enormous sensation in <placeName key="germany">Germany</placeName> – as soon as the state of affairs becomes calm again.</p>
					<p>My own health brings me to despair. I do not think it will improve at all – and my most beautiful hope is death. Only I know that I am not allowed to because the professor doesn’t want it – and he is so strong.</p>
					<p>My wish for the book is a little revision of <hi rend="underline">
						<persName key="warnekros">the head doctor</persName>
						</hi>. Last year I did not know all his gentleness and mercy. He has
						<pb />saved me from all the worst horrors – <hi rend="underline">and I would be deeply ashamed</hi> if there was a word in my book that would make him sad. He is always so good and gentle – and always ready to <del type="strikethrough">alleviate</del><note type="translator">Danish and German word for alleviate.</note> alleviate my pains. And you<note type="translator">Should be the formal "De." Lili is most likely tired and recovering from surgery.</note> would not know how much one comes to love such a man. </p>
					<!-- tnm 2018-10-14: again, this translator's note doesn't make sense to me if placed in the English reading. -->
					<!--tnm:2018-10-14 the blank space in the image isn't rendered at all in the English -->
					<p>I hope you will enjoy your start at the <placeName key="theatreRoyal">Royal Theatre</placeName> – and if I manage to get that far, it would be a pleasure to get to see you play there one night.</p>
				</div> <!-- end body (translation) div -->

				<div type="closer">
					<p style="valediction">The heartiest greetings to you and your husband. Your devoted</p>
					<p>
						<persName key="lili">Lili Elvenes</persName>
						<note type="?">Flourish under signature.</note>
					</p>
				</div> <!-- end closer(original) div -->

				<div type="postscript">
					<p>Excuse the letter's form!</p>
					<p>I am too tired.</p>
				</div> <!-- end postscript (translation) div -->
			</div> <!-- end translation div -->
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>