<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="LEDA_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>  
                <div type="original">
                    <!--letter-->
                    
                    <author>
                        <persName>Carl Reissner</persName>
                    </author>
                    
                    <!-- Formatting dates in <respStmt> elements:            
            If given exact date(s): <date>Month(written out) day#-day#, Year(as YYYY)</date> <date>Month(written out) day#, Year(as YYYY)</date>
            If given month range: <date>Month(written out), Year(as YYYY) to Month, Year</date> <date>Month to Month, Same Year</date>
            If given month: <date>Month(written out), Year(as YYYY)</date>-->
                    
                    <!-- People in <respStmt> elements: 
            Each person on the project team has a special identifier (including you as an encoder).
            These IDs should be used in the blank ref attribute-values below. 
            IDs are created by taking the first and last initial of the person's name. 
            Some team members have asked to be identified with three initials. Please reference Dr. Caughie as plc and Rebecca Parker as rjp.-->
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>Photographed <date when="2017-08-16">August 16-17, 2017</date>
                            by</resp>
                        <persName ref="plc">Pamela L. Caughie</persName>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>Images prepared
                            <date><!--insert date; see formatting suggestions above--></date> by</resp>
                        <persName ref="mg">Matthew Gallagher</persName>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>Transcription completed
                            <date>April 4, 2019</date> by</resp>
                        <persName ref="twj">Tatjana Willms-Jones</persName>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>Translation completed
                            <date>March 12 to April 4, 2019</date> by</resp>
                        <persName ref="twj">Tatjana Willms-Jones</persName>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>Translation reviewed
                            <date><!--insert date; see formatting suggestions above--></date> by</resp>
                        <persName ref=""><!-- Name of Translation Reviewer --></persName>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>Encoding completed
                            <date>April 23, 2019 </date>by</resp>
                        <persName ref="bm">Joaquin Davalos</persName>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>Encoding assistance and/or XML proofing completed by</resp>
                        <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>XML transformed into HTML
                            <date><!-- exact transformation date yyyy-mm-dd --></date> by</resp>
                        <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>HTML proofing completed
                            <date><!-- insert date; see formatting suggestions above --></date> by</resp>
                        <persName ref=""><!-- Name of Proofer --></persName>
                        <persName ref=""><!-- Name of Proofer --></persName>
                        <!-- Remove any additional persName elements not used -->
                    </respStmt>
                    <sponsor>Loyola University Chicago</sponsor>
                    <sponsor>Loyola's Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities</sponsor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <authority>Lili Elbe Digital Archive</authority>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date>July 6th, 2019</date>
                        <availability>
                            <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName><!-- name of archive --></orgName> in
                                <placeName><!-- location of archive --></placeName>
                            </p>
                            <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                                4.0 International license.</licence>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <p><!-- describe anything worth noting about the physical text document from looking at the facsimile images;
               encoder's description must be in complete, logical sentences --></p>
                    </sourceDesc>
                    </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
                </div>
                <date when="1932-01-21">21. Januar 1932</date></seg>
                </p>
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
                    <salute>
                        <seg n="g02">Sehr geehrter Herr <persName>Schumann</persName> !,</seg>
                    </salute>
                    <p><seg n="g03">TIch bestätige den Eingang Ihres Schreibens vom 18.1.
                        nebst Vertrag mit Ihrer Unterschrift. Besten Dank.</seg>
                        <seg n="g04">Vorweg muss ich zu dem letzten Passus Ihres Schreibens Stellung nehmen.</seg>
                        <seg n="g05">. Mit Ihrer Auslegung der Frage der Vorauszahlung bin ich nicht einverstanden.</seg>
                        <seg n="g06">Sie steht im Widerspruch mit Ihrem Schre ben vom 28. Dezember, 
                            der Voraussetzung für unsern Abschluss war.</seg>
                        <seg n="g07">Sie wehrten sich darin gegen die mir zugetragene Behauptung,
                            kei-ne Vorauszahlung zu leisten.</seg>
                        <seg n="g08">Sie schreiben mir wörtlich am 28.12. "Ich gebe hiermit die Erklärung ab, dass ich noch niemals die deutschen Rechte eines fremdsprachigen Buches erworben habe, 
                            ohne bei Vertragsabschluss eine angemessene Vorauszahlung zu leisten."</seg>
                        <seg n="g09">Der Vertrag zwischen uns ist abgeschlossen.</seg>
                        <seg n="g10">Das Ihnen vorliegende Manuskript ist druckreif</seg>
                        <seg n="g11">Kürzungen, die vorgenommen werden sol-len, spielen dabei keine Rolle.</seg>
                        <seg n="g12">Auch ist ja überhaupt noch nicht von Ihnen meine Frage, ob Kürzungen überhaupt vorgenommen werden sollen, beantwortet worden, obgleich ich bereits zweimal danach gefragt habe.</seg>
                        <seg n="g13">.- Vertragsmässig, und ich muss unbedingt auf genau-este Einhaltung des Vertrages bestehen, ist die Vorauszahlung also seit 7.1.32. bereits überfällig. Ergänzungen, die ich für das Schlusskapitel 
                            liefern werde, spielen auch dabei nicht die min-deste Rolle.</seg>
                        <seg n="g14">Ich habe Ihnen gesagt, dass ich nur unter der Voraus-setzung abschliessen könnte, dass bei 
                            Vertragsabschluss die Vor=auszahlung sofort angewiesen würde.</seg>
                        <seg n="g15">Es spielt dabei auch keine grosse Rolle, ob das Buch nun 6 M. oder 8 M. kosten wird. </seg>
                        <seg n="g16">Weniger als 6 M. wird es nicht kosten können. </seg>
                        <seg n="g17">So wären also mindestens 900 Mark seit 7.1.fällig. </seg>
                        <seg n="g18">Ich bitte Sie, diesen Betrag also anzu-weisen.</seg>
                        <seg n="g19">Ich habe Ihr Wort mit Ihrem Schreiben vom 28.12.bekommen, dass diese Vorauszahlung Ihrerseits geschehen würde.</seg>
                        <seg n="g20">Nun warte ich auf die Erfüllung dieser klipp und klar getroffenen Ver=einbarung.</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <seg n="g21">Soll gestrichen werden, so müssen Sie mir jetzt erst einmal sagen w a s.</seg>
                        <seg n="g22">Wie ich Ihnen schrieb, scheint es mir ratsam, in den ersten zwei Kapiteln einiges zu streichen</seg>
                        <seg n="g23">- Mehr aber auch nicht,- Dies geschieht sofort nach Ihrer Vorauszahlung. Ich erwarte Ihre Nach-richt.</seg>
                        <seg n="g24">.- 
                            Dann werde ich auch im Epilog die dort bereits zusammengefassten Briefstellen ergänzen.</seg>
                        <seg n="g25">Ebenso werde ich dann die mir ausgeliefer-ten Briefe verarbeiten.</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <seg n="g26">Mehr Bilder kann ich nur liefern, wenn ich Fotos von hier befind-lichen Bildern nehmen lassen kann. </seg>
                        <seg n="g27">Dies wird pro Stück 5 Mark kosten.</seg>
                        <seg n="g28">Die Bildabteilung von "Berlingske Tidende" wird dieses dan- in die Wege leiten.</seg>
                        <seg n="g29">- Die Kosten für diese Fotos müssten Sie na-türlich tragen. </seg>
                        <seg n="g30">Ich bitte um Ihre Auftragserteilung.</seg>
                        <seg n="g31">Ist Ihnen der Preis Preis zu hoch, so will ich versuchen, hier herunterzuhandeln. </seg>
                        <seg n="g32">Dann bitte ich um Nennung eines Stückpreises.</seg>
                        <seg n="g33">Fotos von Gemälden müs-sen ja sehr sorgsam gemacht werden.</seg>
                        <seg n="g34">Sie selber sagen ja auch, dass die Bilder in trefflichster Wiedergabe ausgeführt sein müssen. </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p>   
                        <seg n="g35">Ich werde mich heute übrigens mit dem "Institut für 
                            Sexualwissenschaft"Berlin NW, In den Zelten 10, in Verbindung setzen. 
                        </seg>
                        <seg n="g37">Dort sollen sich auch einige Bilder von Einar Wegener befinden. </seg>
                        <seg n="g38">Ob sie 
                            sich für eine Wiedergabe eignen, weiss ich leider nicht.</seg>
                        <seg n="g39">Sie er-halten 
                            von mir sehr bald weiteren Bescheid. 
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <seg n="g40">Im übrigen teile ich Ihre Gründe begl. des Erscheinungstermins.</seg>
                        <seg n="g41">Sie sehen, ich gebe mir die grösste Mühe, Ihnen in allen Stücken 
                            behilflich zu sein.</seg>
                        <seg n="g42">Nun aber bitte ich Sie auch, vertragstreu mir die, wie 
                            gesagt, längst verfallene Anzahlung zu machen.</seg>
                        <seg n="g43">Die dänisch-sprachigen Anlagen werden frühzeitig für Ihre Zwecke 
                            übersetzt werden.</seg>
                        <seg n="g44">Hier finden sich an die 20 Gemälde, die für Ihre Zwecke in Fra=ge kommen.</seg>
                        <seg n="g45">Sind Sie also damit einverstanden, dass ich diese Ge=mälde auf Verlagskosten photographieren lasse?</seg> 
                        <seg n="g46">? Ich erwarte hier-zu Ihren Bescheid.</seg>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <salute><seg n="g47">Mit den besten Grüssen</seg>
                            <seg n="48">Jhr ergebenster</seg>
                            <signed><persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </div>
                <div type="translation">
                    <p><subst>
                        <del type="strikethrough">Attachment 5</del>
                        <add place="above" type="overwrite" rend="redCrayon">my Letter</add>
                    </subst></p>
                    <seg corresp="#g01">the <date when="1932-01-32">21st January 1932
                        1932</date>.</seg>
                        </p>
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
                    <salute>
                        <seg corresp="#g02">Dear Mr. Schumann,</seg>
                    </salute>
                    <p><seg corresp="#g03">I am confirming that I received your letter from the 1/18, along with the contract with your signature. Thank you very much. .</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g04">First off, I need to take a stance on the last passage of your letter.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g05">I do not agree with your interpretation of the question about the advance payment. .</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g06">It contradicts what you wrote on the 28th December, which was the requirement for our transaction.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g07">In the letter, you defended yourself against my accusations
                            that you had not completed the advance payment.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g08">On 12/28 you wrote to me verbatim: "I hereby declare, that I have never gained the German rights to a foreign book, 
                            without having given an advance payment when the contract was concluded.".</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g09">The contract between us has been concluded.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g10">The manuscript that you have is ready to be printed</seg>
                        <seg corresp="g11">Any cuts that still need to be made are not important.</seg> 
                        <seg corresp="g12">You haven't even answered my question about whether any cuts need to be made,
                            even though I have asked you twice already</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <seg corresp="#g13">According to the contract, and I have to insist on adhering to the contract exactly,
                            the advance payment has been past due since the 1/7/32 </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g14">Any additions, that I will have for the final chapter, do not matter here. I told you that I could only finalize everything if I received the 
                            advance payment when we concluded the contract..</seg>
                        
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <seg corresp="#g15">It does not matter if the book ends up costing 6 M. or 8 M.. It cannot cost less than 6M. </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g16">Therefore, at least 900 Mark would have been due since the 1/7 </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g17">I am asking you to transfer this amount. </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g18">I received your promise in your letter from the 12/28, 
                            that this advance payment would be coming from you.
                            <seg corresp="#g19">Now I am waiting for the completion of this agreement, which was very clear </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <seg corresp="#g20">If any cuts need to be made, 
                            then you need to tell me w h a t . </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g21">Like I've written to you before,
                            it seems advisable to me to only make cuts in the first two chapters. </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g22">But not more than this,-This will happen immediately after your advance payment. </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g23">I am awaiting your reply. </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g24">Then I will also complete the summary
                            of the letters that are in the epilogue. </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g25">I will also edit the letters that were sent to me. </seg> 
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <seg corresp="#g26">I can only send more pictures if I can have photographs taken of the paintings that I have here. </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g27">This will cost 5 Mark a piece</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g28">The photography section of "Berlingske Tidende" will 
                            be responsible for this.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g29">Naturally, you will have to cover the cost
                            of these photographs</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g30">I kindly ask for your order placement.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g31">If the price is too high for you, I can try to lower it.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g32">If this is the case, I would ask for you to suggest a price.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g33">Photographs of paintings have to be made very carefully. </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g34">You said yourself 
                            that the paintings have to be returned in perfect condition.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g35">I am going to contact the "Institute of Sexual Science" Berlin NW, in the tents 10. </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g36">More of Einar Wegener's paintings should be located there</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g37">I am not sure if they are fit for replication.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g38">You will receive more information from me very shortly.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g39">Furthermore, we share the same reasons regarding the publication date.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g40">As you can see, I am doing my best to be as helpful to you as I can.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g41">Now I ask that you follow the contract and make the past due advance payment.</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g42">The Danish documents will be translated for your use promptly.</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <seg corresp="#g43">There are about 20 paintings here that could be useful to you. </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g44">Do you give me permission to have the paintings photographed?</seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g45">I am awaiting your reply to this</seg>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <seg corresp="#g46"> Kind regards </seg>
                        <seg corresp="#g14">Yours sincerely.</seg>
                        <persName>Lilimoe</persName> and his brother.</seg>
                        <signed><persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
</TEI>

