<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="LEDA_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>
                    <date>June 30, 1932</date> Letter to <persName key="hoyerNiels">Mr.
                        Hoyer</persName>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="schumannH">H. Schumann</persName>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Photographed <date>August 16-17, 2017</date> by</resp>
                    <persName ref="plc">Pamela L. Caughie</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Images prepared <date> </date> by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mg">Matthew Gallagher</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed <date>March 12 to April 4, 2019</date> by</resp>
                    <persName ref="twj">Tatjana Willms-Jones</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation completed <date>March 12 to April 4, 2019</date> by</resp>
                    <persName ref="twj">Tatjana Willms-Jones</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation reviewed
                            <date><!--insert date; see formatting suggestions above--></date>
                        by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""><!-- Name of Translation Reviewer --></persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed
                            <date>April 10, 2019</date>
                        by</resp>
                    <persName ref="sr">Samantha Riker</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance and/or XML proofing completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
                    <persName ref=""><!-- Name of Encoder/Proofer --></persName>
                    <!-- Remove any additional persName elements not used -->
                    <persName ref=""><!-- Name of Encoder/Proofer --></persName>
                    <!-- Remove any additional persName elements not used -->
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>XML transformed into HTML
                            <date><!-- exact transformation date yyyy-mm-dd --></date> by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>HTML proofing completed
                            <date><!-- insert date; see formatting suggestions above --></date>
                        by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""><!-- Name of Proofer --></persName>
                    <persName ref=""><!-- Name of Proofer --></persName>
                    <!-- Remove any additional persName elements not used -->
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Loyola University Chicago</sponsor>
                <sponsor>Loyola's Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Lili Elbe Digital Archive</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>July 6th, 2019</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName>Ernst Harthern Archives</orgName> in
                            <placeName>Huddinge, Sweden</placeName>
                    </p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                        Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p><!-- describe anything worth noting about the physical text document from looking at the facsimile images;
               encoder's description must be in complete, logical sentences --></p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="original">
                <div rend="head">
                    <p>CARL REISSNER / VERLAG / DRESDEN</p>
                     <p>Dresden-N.6, den 30. Juni 1932. Königstraße</p>
                      <p>13 / Fernsprecher 54 008</p>
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
                    <salute>Verehrter lieber Herr Hoyer !</salute>
                    <p>Für Ihren soeben erhaltenen Brief danke ich Ihnen herzlich, der mir ein Zeichen und Beweis für unsere gute Verständigung ist. Doch möchte ich mich heute nur darauf beschränken, die von Ihnen berührten ver-legerischen Fragen so gründlich und präzise wie möglich zu beantworten.</p>
                    <p>Bevor ich dies jedoch tue, möchte ich ein kurzes Wort zu der Angelegen-heit des Herrn von Einsiedel sagen, obwohl sich dies eigentlich erübri-gen dürfte, da Sie ja selbst „Schwamm drüber“ gerufen haben. Mit Herrn von Einsiedel habe ich im März oder April eine eingehende, sehr angeregte Unter-haltung gehabt, und seine Persönlichkeit hat auf mich durchaus Eindruck gemacht, zumal ich seine Uebersetzertätigkeit schon von früher her kannte, ganz besonders von seinem Marseille-Buch. Dass seine Besprechung Ihres Buches von Einfluss sein wird, freut mich ebenso, wie ich das offenbar obwaltende Missverständnis mit meinem Verlag, von dem Sie in diesem Zusammenhang sprechen, lebhaft bedauere. Ich werde mich sogleich mit der Angelegenheit beschäftigen und mir jenen Brief vorlegen lassen, den Sie als merkwürdig empfinden. Aber das Sie ausdrücklich das Schlusswort in der Angelegenheit gesprochen haben, dürfte es sich erübrigen, auf die Angelegenheit noch einmal zurückzukommen.</p> 
                    <p>Nun zu den wichtigen verlegerischen Dingen:</p>
                    <p>Die ersten Korrekturen Ihres Buch haben Sie inzwischen ja er-halten, und da ich der Druckerei das Versprechen abgerungen habe, täglich drei Bogen zu leisten, so werden Sie in wenigen Tagen im Besitz der ge-samten Korrekturen sein, sodass der von Ihnen vorgesehene Zeitpunkt noch wesentlich abgekürzt zu werden vermag.</p>
                    <p>Dass Sie auf ein Nachwort verzichten, findet durchaus meinen Bei-fall, und was Sie über die Absicht Ihres Vorwortes aussprechen, ist alles so ausgezeichnet, dass ich Sie zu dieser glücklichen Lösung nur beglück-wünschen kann, die das lebhafteste Echo in mir ausgelöst hat. Nur erschei-nen mir Ihre allerwichtigsten Darlegungen über die “Confessio“ und das “Document humain“ so wichtig zu sein, dass mir die Bezeichnung “Vorwort“ oder “Einleitung“ als zu unbedeutsam erscheint. Ich schlage daher vor, diese Ihre wichtigen Darlegungen als“ersten Teil“zu bezeichnen, das übrige Buch dagegen als“zweiten Teil“. Obwohl ich die Verringerung des Umfangs natürlich lebhaft begrüsse, wenn auch freilich nur aus äusseren Gründen, so muss ich doch sagen, dass ich bei diesem ersten Teil mit einer Ausführ-lichkeit durchaus einverstanden wäre, ganz nach Ihrem Ermessen, denn alles, was Sie über den Inhalt dieser geplanten Einleitungsarbeit sagen, empfinde ich gardezu als faszinierend. Uebrigens ist es auch recht gut, dass Sie auf die Wirkung der dänischen Ausgabe ausführlich hinweisen wollen, was propagandistisch wichtig wäre.</p> 
                    <p>Einar Wegeners Buch “Le Livre des Vikings“ bitte ich mir auf alle Fälle zu senden; selbstverständlich erhalten Sie es unversehrt zurück.</p>
                    <p>Von Prof. Warnekros erhielt ich die beifolgenden 10 Bilder, die ich auf der Rückseite mit einem roten W versehen habe. Darf ich Sie bitten, auf der Rückseite jedem Bild die Bezeichnung zu geben?</p>
                    <p>Die beifolgende Einschaltung hat sich wohl inzwischen erübrigt?</p>
                    <p>Sodann stehe ich jetzt mit Herrn Dr. Magnus Hirschfeld in persön-lichen Beziehungen. Halten Sie es für unerlässlich, dass die Bilder dem Buch beigegeben werden, die von Lili Elbe in dem Berliner Institut für Sexualwisschenschaft enthalten sind?</p>
                    <p>Leider habe ich dagegen nicht die Dresdener Zeitung, die den Bericht der falschen Todesursache enthält.</p>
                    
                    <p>Blatt 2 zum Brief an Herrn Niels Hoyer, Kopenhagen, vom 30.6.32.</p>
                    
                    <p>Sie wollten so freundlich sein, mir die Uebersetzung des däni-schen Artikels für meine Propaganda zuzusenden; wann darf ich diese erwarten?</p>
                    <p>Was zum Schluss noch Ihren Wunsch einer Vertragänderung anbetrifft, so muss ich diese Angelegenheit mir zunächst noch überlegen, wodurch ich jedoch die Absendung dieses Briefes nicht verzögern will. Auf alle Fälle muss ich aber der Behauptung der Erben widersprechen, dass die jetzt bestehende Vereinbarung auch nur im geringsten unklar sei, wovon doch wirklich keine Rede sein kann. Die Angelegenheit einer Vertrags-änderung ist insofern ein wenig schwierig, als ich es bei der Mentalität des deutschen Publikums für eine Unmöglichkeit halte, Ihrem Wunsch ge-mäss auf einen Leinenband zu verzichten. Doch komme ich hierauf, wie ge-sagt, noch demnächst zurück.</p>
                    <p>Am Montag begleite ich meinen besten Freund auf einer kurzen Autofahrt, die mich jedoch diesmal nicht weniger als etwa 10 Tage von Dresden fern halten wird. Hierdurch wird natürlich nicht die mindeste Verzögerung eintreten.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <salute>In Erwiderung Ihrer freundlichen Grüsse und mit den herzlichsten Wünschen für ihren gute, sonnige, frohe Urlaubstage</salute>
                            <salute>Ihr ergebenster</salute>
                        <signed><persName key="schumannH">H. Schumann</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation">
                <div rend="head">
                    <p>CARL REISSNER / PUBLISHER / DRESDEN</p>
                    <p>Dresden-N.6, the 30th June 1932.</p>
                    <p>Königstraße 13 / Telephone 54 008</p>
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
                    <salute>Dear Mr. Hoyer !</salute>
                    <p>I would like to thank you for your letter that I just received, which is a sign and proof of our good communication. Today I would like to focus on answering your questions regarding the publication as thorough and precise as possible.</p> 
                    
                        <p>However, before I do this, I would like to say something about the situation with Mr. Einsiedel, although this might be unnecessary, since you yourself already dismissed it.</p>  
                        <p>I had a very in-depth and lively conversation with Mr. Einsiedel in March or April, and his personality made a great impression on me, especially since I already knew of his work as a translator, particularly his Marseille book.</p> 
                        <p>Just as much that I am happy that his critique of your book will have some influence, I regret the misunderstanding with my publishing company in this situation.</p>  
                        <p>I will immediately direct my attention towards this and find the letter that you found odd.</p> 
                        <p>But since you so explicitly stated that you wanted to dismiss this matter, it may be superfluous to keep addressing it.</p>  
                    
                    
                    <p>Now to the important things concerning the publication:</p> 
                    <p>You have received the first corrections of your book, and since I have promised the printers to finish three pages a day, this means that you will have all of the corrections in a couple of days, earlier than you anticipated.</p> 
                    
                    <p>I applaud the fact that you have decided to do without the epilogue, and what you plan to do with your foreword is so wonderful, that I can only congratulate you on this happy solution, which elicited the liveliest echo in me.</p> 
                    <p>Your statements about the “Confessio” and the “Document humain” seem so important to me now, that the terms “foreword” or “introduction” seem meaningless. I would suggest, that you name your important remarks “part one” and then the rest of the book “part two”.</p> 
                    <p>Although I would welcome any cutbacks in the book, even if purely for outside reasons, I do need to say that I would be alright with the first part being detailed, because I find everything that you have planned for this introduction quite fascinating.</p>
                    
                    <p>It is also good that you want to discuss the effect of the Danish version, since this would be important for advertising.</p> 
                    
                    <p>I would ask for you to send me Einar Wegener’s book “Le Livre des Vikings“, which I will return to you in perfect condition.</p> 
                    <p>I have attached the 10 pictures that I received from Prof. Warnekros, and marked them with a red W on the back. Could you please write a description on the back of each picture?</p> 
                    <p>I’m assuming the attached ??? is not of importance anymore?</p>
                    <p>I am in contact with Mr. Dr. Magnus Hirschfeld. Is it crucial that the pictures of Lili, that are in the Institute for Sexual Science Berlin, are included in the book?</p> 
                    
                      <p>Unfortunately I do not have the Dresden newspaper that contains the report with the false cause of death.</p> 
                    
                      <p>Page 2 of the letter to Mr. Niels Hoyer, Copenhagen, the 6/30/32</p>
                        
                      <p>You said you’d be so kind as to send me the translation of the Danish article for my advertisement; when can I expect this?</p> 
                   
                      <p>Concerning your request to make changes to the contract, I still need to think this matter over, but I do not want to delay sending this letter because of it.</p> 
                      <p>I do have to disagree with the heirs, in the fact that our agreement is even in the least bit unclear, since this is not at all the case.</p> 
                      <p>Regarding the changes in the contract, this will be a little difficult, since it is impossible for the German audience to do without a paperback version, like you wished.</p> 
                   
                  <p>But, like I said, I will revisit this issue soon.</p> 
                    
                     <p>On Monday, I will accompany my best friend on a short road trip, which will keep me away from Dresden less than 10 days. Of course, I will not let this delay my work.</p> 
                    
                    <closer>
                        <salute>In response to your kind regards I send you the warmest wishes for a good, sunny and happy vacation. </salute>
                        <salute>Yours sincerely,</salute>
                        <signed><persName key="schumannH">H. Schumann</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
