<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="LEDA_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Chapter about the Wegeners from Hélène Allatini's book Mosaïques</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="allatiniH">Hélène Allatini</persName>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding updated on <date when="2018-10-19">26 November 2018</date></resp>
                    <persName ref="ak">Abdur Khan</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation</resp>
                    <persName ref="ac">Anne M. Callahan</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>He and She</head>
                <p>It was near the end of the year 1916 that I met them. My <persName
                        key="allatiniE">fiancé</persName> was then fighting in the Italian army, on
                    the <placeName key="dolomites">Dolomites</placeName> front. During his rest
                    periods he was writing fairy tales for our future children. Since he appreciated
                    the talent of the Danish artist, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda
                        Wegener</persName>, whose drawings appeared in La Vie Parisienne that I sent
                    to him regularly, he asked me to approach her about doing the illustrations of
                    his tales. I knew that she had done a very pretty cover for a book by <persName
                        key="magreM">Maurice Magre</persName>, and so I asked my old friend to put
                    me in touch. That is how, several days later, we came to ring at the door of a
                    <placeName key="studioLille">studio on the rue de Lille.</placeName></p>
                <p> We entered a large tastefully arranged room: antique furniture, Spanish shawls,
                    vases of flowers and tiles from a Scandinavian household. Since her <persName
                        key="wegenerE">husband</persName> was also a painter, an accomplished
                    landscape artist, he excelled in perspective. <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName> and <persName key="wegenerE">Einar Wegener</persName>
                    offered us chairs and they sat down across from us on a large black sofa,
                    decorated with variously colored cushions. Thus, side by side, they reminded me
                    of characters in <persName>Andersen’s</persName> tales,
                    especially the ones in The Snow Queen: <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda
                        Wegener</persName>, so blonde, so fair, personified for me the other Gerda,
                    the one who went off, risking her life, in search of her beloved Kaj in the
                    enchanted palace, while <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> was an exact
                    replica of Kaj, with a mischievous smile that played on his well-drawn lips. The
                        <persName key="wegenerG">young artist</persName> wore her hair drawn back in
                    a chignon on her neck, and two rolls, similar to eighteenth-century hammers,
                    adorned her temples; a black velvet ribbon further brought out the whiteness of
                    her neck. In a nearby cage, two inseparable love birds—the one acid green and
                    the other green ash—playfully hit each other. They seemed to be a living
                    symbol of their owners, who one felt were tenderly united, inseparable as well.
                    A similar clarity lit the golden pupils of <persName key="wegenerE"
                        >Einar</persName>’s eyes and <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda’s</persName>
                    cerulean blue gaze. One had the feeling that their clarity was the very
                    reflection of their pure soul, and I was drawn to them with a fondness that
                    would soon transform into an abiding friendship.</p>
                <p>We talked about our reason for being there, and <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName> seemed willing to do the work. After admiring the works of
                    the two artists, it was agreed that she would write that very evening to
                        <persName key="allatiniE">my fiancé</persName>, to come to an agreement with
                    him, and they decided to meet the day of our marriage. During the reception that
                    followed the marriage ceremony, I presented the young couple to <persName
                        key="allatiniE">my husband</persName>; as with me, they also became friends.
                    We saw each other again in two days, for a long time while having tea at
                    the <placeName key="viennoise">Boulangerie Viennoise</placeName>; it was there
                    that all the details of the volume were decided.</p>
                <p>We left that same evening for our honeymoon in <placeName key="rome"
                        >Rome</placeName>. Upon my return, five months later, we took up again our
                    friendly relations that became more and more cordial and affectionate. I had
                    just lost <persName>my mother</persName> and was
                    expecting <persName key="allatiniJ">my first child</persName>. My Scandinavian
                    friends embraced me and I found great comfort in their affection on days when,
                    without news of my <persName key="allatiniE">husband</persName>, they increased
                    their attention and tried to distract me as best as they could, to turn my thoughts
                    away from my anxiety.</p>
                <p>In May 1918, the Supreme War Council of the Allied Armies was formed at
                        <placeName key="versailles">Versailles</placeName>. <persName
                        key="robilantM">General Nichola de Robilant</persName>, my <persName
                        key="allatiniE">husband’s</persName> commander and old friend of the family,
                    was appointed to represent <placeName key="italy">Italy</placeName>. Upon his
                    arrival, he came to see me, accompanied by his aide-de-camp <persName
                        key="carpegnaM">Count Mario di Carrobio</persName>, as handsome as a young
                    god, cloaked in the superb blue cape worn by cavalry officers. Hardly into our
                    conversation the <persName key="robilantM">adorable general</persName> asked me
                    with a mischievous air: “What would you say if <persName key="allatiniE"
                        >Eric</persName> were named to <placeName key="versailles"
                        >Versailles</placeName>? Would you be annoyed?”</p>
                <p>I almost threw my arms around his neck.</p>
                <p>Several days later <persName key="allatiniE">my husband</persName> arrived in
                    Paris to take up his new post and shortly thereafter I got settled in <placeName
                        key="versailles">Versailles</placeName> with <persName key="allatiniJ">my
                        baby girl</persName>. We led a delightful life getting together with other
                    young couples from all over the world, with many of whom we formed lasting
                    friendships. </p>
                <p>The Wegeners came to visit us often in the charming villa that we had rented and
                    decided to spend the end of summer and a part of autumn in <placeName
                        key="versailles">Versailles</placeName>. They took a small apartment on the
                        <placeName key="hotelReservoirs">rue des Réservoirs</placeName> and we saw
                    each other every day. I recall, not without emotion, the exquisite mornings in
                    the park of the château in the company of <persName key="wegenerE"
                        >Einar</persName> (his friends called him <persName key="wegenerE"
                        >Bé</persName>), while he introduced me, all the while painting, to the
                    hidden beauties of the gardens. It was he who showed me that each pond was of a
                    different color, something that I had never noticed. He had a childlike soul,
                    pure, open to Nature and all of her marvels. We got along very well; for that
                    matter, who would not have gotten along with that charming boy, full of
                    sweetness and tenderness. He adored his <persName key="wegenerG">wife</persName>
                    and endeavored to spare her the least burdens of daily life; it was he who
                    ordered from suppliers, such as color merchants, wrote to editors, bought supplies, so that she could
                    devote herself entirely to her art. For her part, she showed towards him an
                    almost maternal affection. Everyone in the quarter loved <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>, so polite, so full of tact and kindness. The
                    shopkeepers got him coal and the sweet necessities, even in periods of rationing
                    when it was difficult to obtain them. The two spouses never left each other,
                    sharing each joy, each emotion, sleeping side by side with their little fox
                    terrier, <persName key="hvappe">“Vâpe.”</persName>
                </p>
                <p>They left their studio on the <placeName key="studioLille">rue de Lille</placeName> in
                        <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> and moved to the <placeName
                        key="champs">Champs de Mars</placeName> area, into one larger and
                    nicer than the former. We were then living near the <placeName key="lAlmaPlace"
                        >Place de l’Alma</placeName>, which allowed us to see them often, even in
                    that city where, because of distances, it is difficult to see friends as often
                    as one would like.</p>
                <p>I remember a somewhat curious little event that happened to me at the Wegeners.
                    They had invited us to dinner to introduce us to one of their best friends and oldest
                    friends, the <persName key="tb">Danish diplomat T.B.</persName>, a highly
                    cultured man. </p>
                <p>“You will see how irresistible and captivating he is,” <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName> told me, “his conversation is dazzling and he knows the
                    eighteenth century better than anyone, but he has one big flaw: he cannot see a
                    pretty woman without trying to seduce her, and I must warn you that he is very
                    persistent, especially with blondes.”</p>
                <p>That night at dinner she introduced me to this <persName key="tb">Nordic Don
                        Juan</persName>, who had arrived that morning from <placeName
                        key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName> and who had to leave a few days
                    later for his new post in <placeName key="madrid">Madrid</placeName>. I was
                    seated next to him at dinner, and I don’t know if the trip had tired him to the
                    point of being a dolt, but he said nothing at all to me and dropped the
                    conversation each time I made an effort to engage him. After what <persName
                        key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> had told me, I must admit I was a bit
                    piqued. During the salad course <persName key="tb">my
                        neighbor</persName> placed his foot on mine, like a heavy caress. “This is
                    too much, I said to myself, he acts exhausted, ignores me completely, and then
                    he thinks he can play footsy with me…and in socks yet!” Since for the occasion
                    the culprit had removed his shoe, I tried to withdraw my foot without drawing
                    the attention of the other guests, a difficult task, my aggressor’s being
                    tenacious and heavy. I had hardly broken loose when he began again. I felt
                    myself turning red: to my horror, the keen foot was slowly climbing and was now
                    above my ankle while its owner kept his impassive and hypocritically serene
                    look. Such slyness made me lose it: “You’ll see,” I said to myself, and
                    gathering all my forces I gave him a mighty kick. A dog’s cry rang out: the real
                    culprit was <persName key="hvappe">the fox terrier</persName>, who got punished.
                    This proved, once again, that one should be wary of one’s imagination.</p>
                <p>I recall another little event that took place at the Wegeners. I was supposed to
                    have dinner at my friend <persName key="schildtBar">Baby de
                        Friedlander-Fuld’s</persName> place—now the baroness
                    Goldschmidt-Rothschild—who was stopping in Paris. Then we planned to go together
                    to <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> and <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda’s</persName> who were having a small party. When I arrived at
                        <persName key="schildtBar">Baby’s</persName> I noticed that she seemed
                    disappointed. “I’m furious,” she said, “I wanted so much to wear my new bronze
                    tulle dress tonight and I can’t!” </p>
                <p>“What happened? Didn’t they deliver it?”</p>
                <p>“No, it’s over there, behind you, on the chair.”</p>
                <p>“Doesn’t it fit? Is it too tight, too big? We can maybe fix that.”</p>
                <p>“No, none of that, on the contrary, it fits marvelously well, but that animal
                        <persName>Hellstern</persName> didn’t deliver my brown satin
                    shoes.”</p>
                <p>“Don’t you have an old pair of brown ones that you could wear?”</p>
                <p>“No, the only pair I have is in a dreadful state; the tips are so worn that
                    they’re white and one can see the lining.”</p>
                <p>I had a brilliant idea: “We just have to rub them with a bar of chocolate and no
                    one will notice.” We ran to the kitchen and, several minutes later, my <persName
                        key="schildtBar">friend</persName> came to table in a ravishing dress with
                    impeccable brown shoes.</p>
                <p>When we arrived at the Wegeners, she received compliments from everyone. We sat
                    down and they began to play a little music. The little dog <persName
                        key="hvappe">Vâpe</persName>, who, as you know, has a particular fondness
                    for feet, came to lie down at my friend <persName key="schildtBar"
                        >Baby’s</persName> feet. As soon as she picked up the scent of chocolate,
                    she leaped on the tips of the shoes and began to lick them voraciously. We tried
                    to stop her, but she began to growl in a menacing way. There was a general burst
                    of laughter and we had to explain the origin of this feast, which was a huge
                    success.</p>
                <p>But let’s get back to our business, that is, the painters. When one day I was
                    admiring the ravishing back of a nude painted by <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName>, she confided to me: “You will never guess who posed for
                    that back…it’s <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> in person. For some time
                    now he has been serving as my model, which helps me a lot since I would have a
                    hard time finding another back like it.“ The painting represented a sort of
                    blonde bacchante with short hair crowned with vines, nonchalantly reclining on a
                    day bed, her head slightly tilted and turned toward the viewer. The legs were
                    also <persName key="wegenerE">Bé’s</persName>. One would have sworn they were a
                    woman’s legs, as they were so long and tapered. I couldn’t get over it!
                        <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> had taken a photo of <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> during one of the sessions, and I begged her
                    to bring it to the restaurant where we planned to dine with our husbands and
                    mutual friends. We passed around the photo that amazed everyone. Our friend, the
                        <persName key="marquisSG">Marquise de S.G.</persName>, whose husband was
                    late, cried out: “Let’s play a joke on <persName key="marquisSG"
                        >Emilio</persName>, he’ll be here any second.” <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName> would show him the photo of one of her friends and see if
                    he recognized <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>. Like a good Neapolitan,
                    a skirt chaser, the <persName key="marquisSG">Marquis</persName> completely lost
                    his head over this ravishing nude: “Oh, <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName>, who is this? You say that it’s a friend who posed to
                    please you…but I must meet her right away. Swear that you’ll introduce me to
                    her.” Hardly able to control her desire to laugh, <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName> promised him, but added that the person in question was
                    rather shy and away from <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> at the
                    moment. The more she presented difficulties, the more upset the <persName
                        key="marquisSG">Marquis</persName> became. He even enlisted <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> to be a witness to his wife’s promise. We were
                    all laughing so much we were crying. <persName key="marquisSG">Emilio</persName>
                    refused to give back the photo. He kept it in his wallet and afterwards not a
                    day passed that he didn’t ask about the blond bacchante’s return. It got to the
                    point where once, leaving a soirée, he handed the famous photo instead of his
                    number to the woman tending the cloakroom. “You old bastard! Who do you take me
                    for?,” screamed the aging virgin, throwing it in his face.</p>
                <p>Faced with the tragic turn the events were taking, we decided to reveal the truth
                    to the red-faced <persName key="marquisSG">Marquis</persName>. He took it badly,
                    tore up the photo in a bout of black rage, and for weeks spoke not a word to any
                    of us.</p>
                <p>I can’t help to digress once more from my topic to recount an anecdote that dates
                    from about fifty years ago, the hero of which is the <persName key="naplesArchbishop">Archbishop of Naples</persName>, the
                        <persName key="marquisSG">Marquis</persName>’ uncle. This prelate, known for
                    his greed, had for years one valet who served as a factotum, and to whom he
                    gave, however, only eight liras a month in salary. This servant came one day to
                    ask for a raise.</p>
                <p>“<persName key="naplesArchbishop">Monsignor</persName> knows how attached I am to him and that I would be heartbroken to have
                    to leave his service, but I cannot go on like this. The cost of living is rising
                    every day and I cannot even buy the necessities with my eight liras. I come then
                    to pray Monsignor to give me at least two more liras per month.” </p>
                <p>“What you say is true,” replied his <persName key="naplesArchbishop">Excellency</persName>, “but with much regret, it is
                    impossible for me to give you more. However, since I understand very well that
                    your current salary is insufficient and since I am very satisfied with your
                    services, I want to do something for you. I will accord you, from today on, two
                    hours of freedom every afternoon, from one to three o’clock, at the time when
                    traffic is the most dense on the Château de l’Oeuf bridge, so that you can go
                    there to beg. Thus, everything will work out for the best.”</p>
                <p>And so, every day one would see, at the entrance to the bridge, the <persName key="naplesArchbishop">Archbishop</persName>’s
                    valet with his hand out. And that shocked no one…Oh, sweet <placeName
                        key="naples">Naples</placeName>.</p>
                <p>I return to the Wegeners, not to leave them again. I asked <persName
                        key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> when she recognized <persName key="wegenerE"
                        >Bé</persName>’s feminine contours for the first time.</p>
                <p>“It goes back a long time,” she answered, “even before the war. We were still in
                        <placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName> and I was doing the
                    portrait of a well-known actress. One day she telephoned at the last moment to
                    cancel. I was furious, and disappointed, having set aside my afternoon for her.
                    Seeing me frustrated by not being able to continue my work, <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> offered to replace the model, at least for
                    the dress, if he was able to fit into it. I was stunned to see that, not only
                    did it fit him beautifully, but also that he had a woman’s shoulders,
                    magnificent. I amused myself by completing the illusion by putting a blond wig
                    that I had gotten at the carnival on his head and making him up as best as I could.
                    I began then to paint and was surprised, in the middle of work, by the real
                    model who came to excuse herself for having broken her word. Seeing her dress on
                    another person, she was a bit surprised, but did not recognize <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>. For a minute I let her think that a friend
                    had replaced her to do me a favor and allow me to make progress on the portrait.
                    The timbre of <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>’s voice ended up betraying
                    him and the young woman, laughing wholeheartedly, couldn’t get over her shock.
                    She invited herself to dinner, had some champagne brought up ‘to drink to the
                    good health of her new friend, <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>.’ During the
                    meal we baptized <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> with champagne, and from
                    then on, he posed often for me, dressing as a woman any chance he got. <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> loved this sort of work and liked to mystify
                    people, who invariably took him for a daughter of Eve. He was a sensation at
                    various masked balls and he impersonated <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>
                    more and more. One evening when I had a cold and couldn’t go out, he put on my
                    prettiest low cut dress and I carefully did his hair and made him up. He went
                    with one of our young friends to a dinner, followed by dancing, hosted every two
                    weeks at a club for artists and other cosmopolitan individuals, to which we
                    belonged. Except for these young friends and a woman we knew, no one else was in
                    on the secret. They introduced the newcomer as <persName key="wegenerE">Einar
                        Wegener’s</persName> sister and my sister-in-law, adding that we were at
                    home with the grippe. The beautiful <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> was a
                    big hit and stole the heart of a cavalry officer, the <persName key="countT"
                        >Count of T</persName>., who was about fifty-five or sixty years old. He
                    spent the entire evening lavishing her with compliments. She had to promise to
                    allow him to see her again. He insisted on escorting her home and left her
                    regretfully. Two days later, as I worked alone in my studio, someone knocked on
                    the door. Imagine my surprise when the mature and mannerly <persName
                        key="countT">gentleman</persName> whom <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>
                    had described to me as her beau stood on the threshold, a bit shy, his arms
                    filled with flowers. I almost dropped mine.</p>
                <p>“‘Is this the home of <persName key="lili">Mademoiselle Lily Wegener</persName>,’
                    mumbled <persName key="countT">the poor man</persName>. ‘Would you do me the
                    courtesy of telling her that <persName key="countT">Colonel de T.</persName>
                    would like to see her.’</p>
                <p>“I invited him to come in and sit down explaining that my sister-in-law was out
                    and would be back late. He seemed shattered and stayed for a good half hour
                    talking to me about <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’s physical and mental
                    charms. While I agreed with him, it was all I could do to keep a straight face.
                    I took the initiative to tell him that this young person would soon be leaving
                    to deal with family matters in <placeName key="denmark">Denmark</placeName>.</p>
                <p>“The <persName key="countT">Count de T.</persName> finally left, assuring me that
                    he would be back soon. He kept his word. In the meantime our friend, <persName
                        key="madameB">Madame de B.</persName> who was at the famous dinner and
                    witnessed the <persName key="countT">soldier</persName>’s coup de foudre, came
                    to tell us that the poor <persName key="countT">colonel</persName>, more and
                    more irrational, thought of nothing but <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> and
                    even spoke of divorcing his wife to marry her. And so when he came to see her, I
                    told him that she had left suddenly the day before for <placeName
                        key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName>. The wretch was in despair. He
                    confided in <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> and told him he was surprised
                    to find how little he resembled his delightful sister. ‘Perhaps in the
                    expression of the eyes, but that’s all.’ It took a heroic effort not to betray
                    ourselves and maintain demeanor that fit the situation.</p>
                <p>“Afterwards, we had cards of <placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName>
                    sent to <persName key="madameB">Madame de B.</persName> signed ‘<persName
                        key="lili">Lily</persName>’ on which the young person confirmed the
                    lengthiness of her stay, leaving him with vague plans for marriage, all of which
                    to calm the unhappy victim.</p>
                <p>“Happily, time did it’s work and we no longer saw the <persName key="countT"
                        >Count de T.</persName>.”</p>
                <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> knew <persName key="wegenerE"
                        >Bé</persName> as an adolescent taking drawing and painting classes at the
                        <placeName key="academyArt">Copenhagen Fine Arts Academy</placeName>. The
                    young artist had a deep affection for the student and he became her best friend.
                        <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> was very flattered and <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, madly in love, pined away, realizing that
                    he would never be anything more to her than a dear friend and confidant. When
                    she was seventeen, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> had a romantic
                    disappointment following which she became sad and indifferent to other men who
                    flirted with her. At this time she discovered that poor <persName key="wegenerE"
                        >Einar</persName> was dying of love for her. He had a heart attack and
                    doctors said that this nervous state would be fatal. Already wounded, the young
                    girl could not stand the idea of losing the person dearest to her, after her
                    mother. She ran to <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>’s bedside and told him
                    that she had reconsidered and consented to become his wife. The effect was
                    magical and the young man, suddenly better, was soon able to walk the blond
                    daughter of pastor Gotlieb [sic.] to the altar. These two children, barely
                    seventeen and twenty years old, shared a childlike innocence and young <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, a virgin like his wife, had never asked
                    himself if he was up to the duties that his new situation demanded. Naïve and
                    knowing only imperfectly what marriage had in store for girls, <persName
                        key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> was only half surprised at how sweet and
                    superficial the caresses of her husband were. They were perfectly satisfied with
                    each other and when on some spring evenings the young woman experienced longings
                    that she could not define, their life together was so harmonious, so smooth and
                    tender, that she attached only a vague importance to them. After long months,
                    they noted that sexual joys were denied to their union, which did not prevent
                    them in any way from continuing to live in perfect harmony. They had the same tastes
                    in art, the same concept of life and, finally, they could not even for an
                    instant do without one another. They loved each other and fought like two
                    children. I can still hear <persName key="gottliebMrs">Madame Gottlieb</persName>,
                    during a visit to Paris, cry, “When will you cease being children?” And
                        <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> answered: “But, <persName
                        key="gottliebMrs">maman</persName>, never I hope!”</p>
                <p>For some time, I had been noticing with anguish (or perhaps someone had brought
                    it to my attention) that <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>’s figure,
                    already effeminate, was becoming more and more ambiguous: his
                    jackets seemed more pinched at the waist, his chest bulged, and his swaying gait
                    recalled that of an odalisque; even his voice was taking on feminine
                    inflections. <persName key="allatiniE">My husband</persName> had noticed as well
                    and “one,” that is to say my family, my friends and acquaintances, finally all
                    the well-meaning tribe of those who please themselves by making you discover,
                    with touching solicitude, disagreeable things that you might have missed. “One”
                    was stunned, “one” disapproved of our relations and friendship with a being so
                    clearly ambiguous. I spoke to <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> about
                    what I had observed; she answered that she herself noticed it a long time ago,
                    even though she lived with him, and it was torturing her terribly. “But the most
                    lamentable thing,” she added, “is that <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>
                    also realized it and suffered more than you can imagine. He notices that one
                    turns around in the street, that one laughs when he gets on a bus, and he hears
                    outrageous things being shouted at him. Everyone takes him for a homosexual, and
                    you know as well as I do that he is as indifferent to men as to an old shoe. Do
                    you know what happened the other evening at a dinner at <persName key="bramsonK"
                        >Karen Bramson</persName>’s? There were a dozen of us and since some were
                    French, the conversation was in that language. Abruptly, in the middle of the
                    meal, <persName key="bramsonK">Karen Bramson</persName>, who as you know doesn’t
                    manage very well what passes through her head, cries across the table to
                        <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>: ‘You, Wegener, naturally you like
                    men?’ And <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, witty as usual, answered
                    her smiling, ‘No, madame, you’re wrong, I am lesbian.’</p>
                <p>“I even sent him to consult two physicians but one took him for a crazy person,
                    the other for a pervert, such that he came back more depressed than ever. He
                    even began to experience a kind of malaise every month and, what is even more
                    curious, is that his personality and mentality became feminized more than his
                    physique. He is only happy as <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> and spends
                    entire afternoons dressed as her, reading poetry, embroidering, baking or
                    playing with the little dog. He says that like this he forgets everything and
                    feels in his element. You and I alone can understand this situation, and I
                    haven’t spoken to anyone else about it; that would be to expose us, <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> and me, to those who would ridicule us, or,
                    like the physicians, take us for vile or crazy. You must understand my
                    desperation, seeing him suffer so and to be unable to do anything….”</p>
                <p>Towards spring <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>’s condition had grown
                    noticeably worse. <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> decided to spend a
                    few months in <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>, hoping that the change of
                    climate and of surroundings would do him good. They left, took a small apartment
                    with studio in the <placeName key="rome">Eternal City</placeName>. We didn’t see
                    them again for a long time and the news I received not at all reassuring:
                        <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> experienced more and more vertigo,
                    headaches and depression; <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> envisioned a
                    prompt return to <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> if this state of
                    affairs continued. It wasn’t until the end of autumn that we saw our friends
                    again. They invited us to dinner in a little Italian restaurant near them.</p>
                <p>That morning I got a phone call from my friend, <persName key="warnekros"
                        >Professor W</persName>. —the celebrated German gynecologist—who was passing
                    through Paris. He was only free that very evening and wanted very much to see
                    us. I cancelled the date with the Wegeners, explaining the situation. At about
                    four o’clock there was another call from the <persName key="warnekros"
                        >physician</persName>, held up due to a car problem, on the outskirts of
                        <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>. He was very sorry but wouldn’t be
                    back until very late after an appointment, and our evening was ruined.</p>
                <p>“Let’s reset our dinner date with the <persName key="wegenerE"
                    >Einar</persName>s,” I said to my <persName key="allatiniE"
                    >husband</persName>.</p>
                <p>“No, we’ll see them another day. They’ll think we’re crazy to change our minds at
                    every moment.”</p>
                <p>At that moment I had a strange intuition that we should, at all costs, see our
                    friends that evening. It was like a command that I had received from a superior
                    will. I explained to my <persName key="allatiniE">husband</persName> that the
                    closeness of our relationship with the Wegeners was such that they would not
                    stand on ceremony. I let them know that we would come by to pick them up at
                    about eight o’clock.</p>
                <p>Although we expected to find <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> changed, we
                    had a horrible shock when we saw him. Our poor friend was a shadow of his former
                    self, gaunt, pasty complexion, sunken eyes surrounded by large dark circles,
                    with a hopeless expression that I’ll never forget. He made a heroic effort to
                    appear lighthearted during the meal, but in his eyes there persisted the look of
                    a tortured beast that I could not stand. Not being able to contain myself, I
                    took <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> aside and told her about my
                    painful impression.</p>
                <p>“I was going to speak to you myself about it, “she answered. “I’m sick about it!
                    Battered by atrocious constant suffering, the poor soul isn’t able to sleep. He
                    feels his forces diminishing every day and if no one can do anything to help
                    him, I fear the worst. He can’t go on like this! His male organs are atrophying
                    little by little, his breasts are developing, he endures tortures every month
                    and I don’t dare consult physicians here because of our first experience.”</p>
                <p>At that moment, I had a distinct vision of the tall figure of my friend,
                        <persName key="warnekros">Professor W.</persName>. His passage through Paris
                    seemed to be not a coincidence, but the hand of destiny. Seized by an
                    uncustomary eloquence, I laid out my plan to <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName>: call a big specialist the next morning, explain the case
                    in a few words and get an appointment. Comforted and full of hope, <persName
                        key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> promised to do her best to send her husband
                    to me the next morning. She had, however, a hard time convincing him; at the
                    last minute he wanted to back out, having abandoned all hope.</p>
                <p>The few details that I gave <persName key="warnekros">Professor W.</persName> on
                    the phone were enough to raise his interest; he immediately set a time.
                        <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> arrived at my place early; he was
                    very agitated and I had a hard time calming him, to convince him that everything
                    would work out once he was in the hands of the admirable <persName
                        key="warnekros">specialist</persName>.</p>
                <p>“I didn’t want to tell you in front of <persName key="wegenerG"
                    >Gerda</persName>,” he told me, “but I have decided to kill myself if I can’t
                    become who I really am, a woman. Think of it, <persName key="allatiniH"
                        >Hélène</persName>, I am no longer anything but a human wreck, a useless
                    waste. Physically and mentally ill—I can no longer even hold a brush, nor do
                    anything to help <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>—I refuse to be a
                    burden to her. She has been admirable with me; no one would be able to
                    understand to what extent…except you perhaps? ...I promised both of you to
                    consult this great <persName key="warnekros">physician</persName>. This will be
                    my final attempt; if he can do nothing, I am determined to die… it will be a
                    relief to me… and also to my dear <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>…when
                    the first sadness goes away. I will no longer hamper her life as I have been
                    doing for a long time. In my case, it would be cowardly to go on living. Look at
                    what I’ve become!”</p>
                <p>Saying this, he opened his shirt and bared the most beautiful woman’s breasts
                    that I had ever seen. I was overwhelmed and truly “realized” at that moment
                    everything that he had been telling me.</p>
                <p>When we got to my friend, <persName key="warnekros">Professor W.</persName>’s, I
                    acted as interpreter. I had to explain to him, in German, the progress of
                        <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>’s metamorphosis from the
                    beginning. I waited in an adjoining room while he examined him. He came back a
                    quarter of an hour later, seized by an agitation that stunned me in a man whom I
                    had never seen as anything but impassive.</p>
                <p>“Do you know, dear friend, that you have brought me a case that is unique in the
                    history of medical science, a case waited for during an entire existence,
                    without ever having been encountered: your friend is the only true hermaphrodite
                    who exists or has existed, for he had truly been a man, an undersized,
                    inadequate, atrophied man, but a man nonetheless in every accepted meaning of
                    the term. In general, the other beings to whom one applies this name are not
                    real hermaphrodites but only men afflicted with an inguinal hernia that keeps
                    their organs inside the body, thus one is able to take them for women. Following
                    a physical shock, an accident or some phenomenon like that, the suspended organ
                    descends abruptly and takes its normal place: the so-called woman then becomes a
                    man, but, in reality, she has always been one without suspecting it. While
                        <persName key="wegenerE">Wegener</persName> was first a man and has actually
                    evolved towards the feminine sex, which is totally different from ordinary cases
                    of hermaphroditism. He thus represents the first perfect example of the
                    androgyne. Actually, there exist in him both sexes and it is the struggle
                    between them that is torturing this poor being. If there is no intervention, he
                    will succumb in a short time, whether because of the struggle between them, or
                    by his own hand, since he is unable to endure this horrible suffering much
                    longer. I see only one way out: rid him of what remains of his first sex and
                    graft onto the ovaries—for he certainly has ovaries—new ovaries, in good
                    condition. Then later, when he can tolerate it, a third and final surgery to
                    open a normal path to genital function. I easily imagine the masculine
                    attentions with which your friend must have been harassed, for hermaphrodites
                    exercise a powerful sexual seduction on men, unknown to them. All this will
                    allow you to understand something that one is generally ignorant of and which
                    causes so many injustices and calumnies in our pitiful society: many homosexuals
                    are beings who possess a male organ in which there are ovaries instead of
                    testicles. It’s the same for a lot of lesbians who have testicles where the
                    ovaries should be. These unhappy ones thus unjustly suffer public scorn and
                    disgust when their proclivities are –on the whole—normal and not vile and
                    perverse as one likes to make them feel.</p>
                <p>“I will prescribe first for your friend a treatment to prepare him to endure the
                    trial that awaits him. Towards the beginning of March I will notify him and he
                    will have to come to <placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName> immediately
                    where my colleague, <persName key="gohrbandt">Professor G.</persName> will perform
                    the first operation. As soon as he’s recovered he will come –or rather she will
                    come—to <placeName key="dresden">Dresden’s <placeName key="womensClinic"
                            >Frauenklinik [Women’s Clinic]</placeName></placeName> where I will
                    perform the second intervention, in which his true sex will be revealed. May he
                    have bon courage while waiting, which I’m certain that he will have, for one can
                    only bow before his valor.” Then, addressing <persName key="wegenerE"
                        >Einar</persName> himself: “Good bye then, dear sir, while waiting to be
                    able to say: Hello, dear miss.”</p>
                <p>It was a transformed <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> that I brought
                    back to his <persName key="wegenerG">wife</persName>! I have never seen such a
                    change in so little time. My <persName key="wegenerE">friend</persName>’s face
                    had gone from the most harrowing anguish to the most perfect serenity, like
                    those skies that, darkened by a storm, suddenly brighten, lit by a radiant
                    clarity. During the following two months, poor <persName key="wegenerE"
                        >Bé</persName>, as if touched by a magicians wand, regained physical and
                    mental strength. <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> told me often about
                    his joy and relief.</p>
                <p>It was on a beautiful morning in March that the two of us accompanied him to the
                        <placeName key="stationGareNord">Gare du Nord</placeName>. He got settled in his
                    compartment and, gallant as usual, he offered his reserved corner seat to a
                    young woman who thanked him with a charming smile. Her “Thank you, sir,” made us
                    laugh. We knew that <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> was wearing a man’s
                    suit for the last time, about which didn’t stop rejoicing about during the taxi
                    ride. <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> thought that she had the time to
                    finish a very important commission and to rejoin her husband before the
                    intervention but she had to leave precipitously that same week, notified by
                    telegram that “everything went admirably well.” Hardly arrived in <placeName
                        key="berlin">Berlin</placeName>, <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>,
                    examined by <persName key="hirschfeld">Marcus [Magnus] Hirschfeld</persName>
                    and several other <placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName> authorities,
                    underwent, at the hand of <persName key="gebhard">Professor G.</persName>, the
                    excision that would make him, definitively, <persName key="lili"
                    >Lily</persName>.</p>
                <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> brought women’s underwear, a pink
                    bathrobe and an entire arsenal of makeup and perfume to celebrate <persName
                        key="lili">Lily</persName> and give her a truly feminine appearance.</p>
                <p>Upon arriving at the <placeName key="womensClinic">clinic</placeName>, the
                        <persName key="wegenerG">traveler</persName> was first of all struck by the
                    change of the voice of her <persName key="wegenerE">former husband</persName>.
                    The operation was enough to transform timbre of his voice and it was a pretty <persName
                        key="lili">soprano</persName> who welcomed her. The <persName key="lili"
                        >patient</persName> rested, pale but radiant, on her pillows after having
                    valiantly endured the suffering that had released her—finally!—from the
                    chrysalis that had been so detested. She was pampered, spoiled, surrounded by
                    flowers, solicitude. The few Scandinavian friends who were in <placeName
                        key="berlin">Berlin</placeName> visited her every day. She was the idol of
                    the clinic, one spoke of nothing but her, of her courage, of her sweetness and
                    of her extraordinary adventure.</p>
                <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> quickly made up her dear <persName
                        key="lili">girl</persName> (for this was how she thought of her now), did
                    her hair, put on her nightgown and the pink robe that I had long promised
                        <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> for <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName> and that she brought her on my behalf. One can imagine the
                    great amazement of <persName key="gebhard">Professor G.</persName> upon entering
                    the room, that very evening, when he saw, in place of his patient, a ravishing
                        <persName key="lili">young lady</persName> all dolled up, perfumed and hair
                    curled to receive him.</p>
                <p>The weeks that followed were a dream come true for poor <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName>: for her first outing, <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName> surprised her with a beautiful fur coat and then took her
                    to the stores to choose everything that was still missing from her
                    trousseau.</p>
                <p>As planned, I had the honor to receive <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’s
                    first letter. The handwriting was so different that I could hardly believe,
                    while tearing it open, that it was written in her hand: in place of <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>’s thick down strokes, elegant and light
                    strokes flowed on the page, but what surprised me most was <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName>’s style, virginal, sensitive, delicate, the handwriting of
                    a young girl and a romantic one:</p>
                <p>“<placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName>. <date>March 10, 1930</date>. Dear
                    and great friend. I am so delighted by your letter and I kiss your dear name. I
                    am so happy but so very tired that it is impossible for me to write. The
                    operation lasted one hour and I screamed for hours afterwards (with a clear
                    voice like <persName key="schumannE">Elisabeth Schumann</persName>’s, according
                    to my superb surgeon.). <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> lived and
                        <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> will soon be a girl with a proper
                    passport. Spring sings in my heart and I cry from happiness and I am fearless
                    faced with all the suffering that awaits me. I adore you. <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName></p>
                <p>P.S. –<persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> has celebrated the funeral of his
                    life as a boy.”</p>
                <p>And again, <date>March 15</date>: “Everyone here spoils me and calls me <persName
                        key="lili">Lily</persName>. They compliment me a lot on my legs. That suits
                    me very well. I will never be a strong-minded woman. Don’t you think, dear
                        <persName key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName>, that I should have pink, not
                    red, nails for the big operation in <placeName key="dresden"
                    >Dresden</placeName>? At the moment I no longer try to contain my joy when I
                    feel so happy. <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> is fading away more and
                    more and <persName key="warnekros">Professor W.</persName> is going to give him
                    the coup de grâce.”</p>
                <p>Several weeks later, two elegant young women left for <placeName key="dresden"
                        >Dresden</placeName>’s <placeName key="womensClinic"
                        >Frauenklinik</placeName> and introduced themselves to <persName
                        key="warnekros">Professor W.</persName>, who, having not yet met <persName
                        key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> and having last seen a gaunt <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> in a man’s jacket, couldn’t identify the
                    seductive creatures who stood before him, laughing.</p>
                <p>The <placeName key="womensClinic">Frauenklinik</placeName> is really a city
                    having five hundred beds and all the modern amenities. <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName> was settled into the most beautiful room, and there too she
                    became the focus of general interest. The second operation was long and grave.
                    She came out of it very weak, but very happy, for the heart and new soul of a
                    young girl had given themselves to her savior, who had liberated her from a
                    martyr’s existence, in order to open for her the golden doors of life and hope. </p>
                <p><placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>, April 1930: “My whole life would
                    not suffice to thank you for having sent me to this extraordinary man, this
                    benevolent genius who gave me a new life. I adore my dear <persName
                        key="warnekros">Professor W</persName>….I love him, but with a measure of
                    respect, as if he were an all-powerful god. Dear <persName key="allatiniH"
                        >Hélène</persName>, you will understand your little <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName> when I tell you that I have never seen his eyes, because I
                    have never dared look at him. Often I would like to tell him something, I don’t
                    get any further than smiling stupidly and saying: ‘Yes, maître.’ I wish he were
                    a pasha or a sultan so that I could be his slave. <placeName key=""
                        >Frauenklinik</placeName> is an earthly paradise! I like my suffering better
                    here. So that is where I am! I have a new pair of ovaries that behave like
                    little fauns in my painful stomach. My room is the only one with a big mirror,
                    when He gives me permission to get up, I will be able to stand in front of it.
                        <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> wants to do <persName
                        key="warnekros">His</persName> portrait. What is this magic power that
                    affects everyone who comes near him? There is a charming young girl who comes to
                    clean my room, who said to me: ‘I clean to save my life, if <persName
                        key="warnekros">He</persName> ever saw a speck of dust and scolded me, I
                    would die!’ <persName key="allatiniH">Hélène, Hélène</persName>, how fantastic
                    is it that from a life headed down and at an end, He created a new life
                    overflowing with hope, love and spring. It’s the work of a god! What heartbreak,
                    the day when I will have to leave this <placeName key="womensClinic"
                        >clinic</placeName> in the forest of white birches. I have dreamed that
                        <persName key="warnekros">He</persName> will continue to operate on me until
                    there will be nothing left to <persName key="warnekros">Him</persName> but my
                    heart trembling in his sweet, fine hands. <persName key="allatiniH"
                        >Hélène</persName>, you have a heart of gold that you spend endlessly for
                    the happiness of others. I hope you will never regret all that you have done for
                    your little <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>. I, who am a little afraid of
                    my first steps in life, I feel protected by your friendship.”</p>
                <p>For his part, the celebrated <persName key="warnekros">surgeon</persName> seemed
                    touched by the sweetness and courage of his little patient and showed almost
                    paternal feelings for her, to which was now added a professional interest in
                    this most fascinating of all cases. <persName key="warnekros">Professor
                        W</persName>. had a lovely respect for <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName>, whose admirable conduct in a unique situation he
                    appreciated. He had given her the privilege of going up to his place to rest, or
                    paint, in his comfortable living room. In gratitude for everything he had done,
                    she undertook to do his portrait, in his white surgeon’s coat. The nurses and
                    the domestics took special care of the surgical patient, in order to please the
                        <persName key="warnekros">maître</persName>, all of them showering him with
                    fearful adoration, mixed with respect. He moved about on the waves of feminine
                    admiration like a sultan in his harem; the devotion of the entire staff has
                    become a sort of religious rapture.</p>
                <p>One afternoon, while <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> took her siesta,
                    stretched out on a chaise lounge in the clinic’s park, an old woman approached
                    her and engaged her in conversation: “How are you now, little lady? You seem to
                    have better color and you will soon be fully recovered from giving birth.” My
                    girl began to get up. “And your baby, is it a boy or girl?”</p>
                <p>“Neither,” replied <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> without blinking, “the
                    Good Lord sent me twins.”</p>
                <p><persName key="lili">Lily</persName> left the <placeName key="womensClinic"
                        >clinic</placeName> and her dear savior with regret and went to complete her
                    recovery in the mountains of <placeName key="saxony">Saxony</placeName>, in the
                    company of <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>.</p>
                <p>”He has sent us for several days in <placeName key="erzgebirge"
                        >Erzgebirge</placeName>, between <placeName key="saxony">Saxony</placeName>
                    and <placeName key="bohemia">Bohemia</placeName>, but it is so cold here that we
                    are going to leave this place where we are shivering in our little summer
                    frocks.”</p>
                <p>They returned to take leave of the <persName key="warnekros">professor</persName>
                    and left for <placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName>, to get their
                    marriage annulled and put <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’s papers in
                    order. She obtained from the <persName key="king">King of <placeName
                            key="denmark">Denmark</placeName></persName> a change of her family name
                    to Elbe, after <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>’s river, witness to
                    her renaissance. <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> spent a long visit with
                    her family, trembling when she went out, afraid of being recognized, dreading
                    the moment when her metamorphosis was made known, making her the prey of
                    journalists who would make her a national phenomenon. She didn’t want to touch a
                    palette, nor anything that could remind her of <persName key="wegenerE"
                        >Bé</persName>. She spent her days sewing, looking in the mirror,
                    embroidering, doing her nails. She was modest to a fault, whereas <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> loved to recount salacious jokes, she blushed
                    at the drop of a hat and in contrast to her first incarnation (<persName
                        key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> was a confirmed atheist), she became
                    edifyingly pious, with an intense mysticism. Her second brother, <persName
                        key="brotherSing">Holger</persName>, and her
                        <persName>sister-in-law</persName>, with whom <persName key="wegenerE"
                        >Bé</persName> got along very well, were touchingly good to <persName
                        key="lili">Lily</persName> and welcomed her wholeheartedly. Worn out from
                    the mental tension of these last months and knowing that <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName> was in good hands, <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName> gave in to her <persName>mother</persName>’s insistence
                    that she wanted to take her to rest in <placeName key="italy">Italy</placeName>,
                    and left with her for <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>. They stayed at a
                    family-run pension owned by a Danish woman that they knew. It took <persName
                        key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> all she had to distract herself and go out
                    with Italian friends, for, since the annulment of her marriage, <persName key="gottliebMrs">Madame
                        Gottlieb</persName>, believing that she had reverted to a time when her
                    daughter was an adolescent, gave her no freedom and watched over her like a
                    dragon. The old woman, wanting to know Pompeii, decided to visit with her
                    daughter for a week. Under the constant supervision of her mother, the young
                    woman looked for a way to free herself, to be able, finally, to relax. The
                    morning of the return, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>, disconcerted,
                    walked around in the old part of <placeName key="naples">Naples</placeName>,
                    when she noticed a small church that drew her to it mysteriously. She entered
                    and approached the altar of the Virgin, she prayed her to come to her aid, to
                    protect her and guide her life towards a loyal and good person who would love
                    her sincerely and with whom she could share the rest of her existence. She left
                    comforted, and that evening, in the train bringing them back to <placeName
                        key="rome">Rome</placeName>, she resolved to let her
                        <persName>mother</persName> return to <placeName key="denmark"
                        >Denmark</placeName> alone and to prolong her stay in <placeName key="italy"
                        >Italy</placeName>. At the pension, a pile of mail waited for her. As she
                    moved towards the hotel salon to go through it, a masculine figure got up to
                    greet her. She recognized an aviation officer who had been introduced to her
                    before her trip to <placeName key="naples">Naples</placeName>. “Allow me to
                    offer you my respects, madame, and tell you how happy I am about your return. I
                    was afraid that you had left <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName> definitively
                    and this house had lost its charm during your absence.”</p>
                <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> responded with a few words and accepted
                    a cigarette. After this first conversation <persName key="portaF">Captain Porta</persName>
                    waited each evening for the young woman’s return, and their liking for each
                    other grew more and more. The day of <persName>Madame Gottlieb</persName>’s
                    departure, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> was surprised to find the
                    officer waiting for her at the station exit. “I wanted to be sure that you would
                    still be here for me,” he said with emotion. Won over by the passion of this
                    handsome and likeable boy, she agreed to listen to him. They discovered that
                    they got along famously, had the same tastes, and when <persName key ="portaF">Fernando
                        Porta</persName> asked her to become his wife, she accepted with a full
                    heart after having told him of her past and of the adventure, so unbelievable,
                    that had cast a shadow over her. “You are now doubly dear to me,” he answered,
                    “and admiration filled with respect is mingled with my tenderness; <persName
                        key="lili">Lily</persName> will be our child. I understand that you do not
                    wish to abandon her. She will always have a room in our home, a place in our
                    household.”</p>
                <p>When <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> told us of her engagement, I felt
                    great joy. She was finally receiving the recompense she so deserved, the
                    happiness that I had always wished for her. During a short trip to <placeName
                        key="rome">Rome</placeName>, my husband had the opportunity to meet
                        “<persName>Nando</persName>” and found him most charming. He belonged to one
                    of the best Livornese families and had just been appointed vice-consul to
                        <placeName>Marrakech</placeName>, where they would soon be married. The
                    first few days of June <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> would leave for
                        <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>; she would spend two weeks with us,
                    before leaving for <placeName>Morocco</placeName> where the happy couple would
                    be waiting for her. The time passed quickly and soon came the moment when a
                    group of friends accompanied <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> to the
                    station. She was radiant in spite of a shadow of regret at the thought of
                    leaving poor <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> behind her. But it was only a
                    shadow, in effect, for wasn’t she supposed to rejoin her, and don’t two months
                    pass quickly, especial when one is happy. The two women embraced one more time:
                    “Until we meet again, little <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>, until we meet
                    again, in <placeName>Marrakech</placeName>!” “See you soon, dear <persName
                        key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>, as always!” </p>
                <p>The whistle blows, the train moves off, handkerchiefs are waving; for a long time
                        <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> follows with her eyes the slender
                    figure of her beloved girl and, at the very moment when the train makes a curve
                    and disappears from sight, she experiences a sudden and harrowing dread, a
                    tightening of her heart, as if she were seeing <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName> for the last time!...</p>
                <p>April, May, June… I began to prepare for the arrival of <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName>. I broke the news of the death of her friend <persName
                        key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> to my <persName>daughter</persName>, who loved
                    him so tenderly. I dried her tears and tried to calm her announcing that
                        <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>’s sister, <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName>, was coming to visit us for several days and that she so
                    resembled her poor brother that she would surely replace him in her affection.
                    Then I wrote to <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> to be dressed in mourning
                    upon her arrival.</p>
                <p>Having thus definitively buried poor <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>, I
                    prepared <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’s room. To flatter her vanity, I
                    had embroidered sheets put on the bed, put a large mirror on the wall, and I
                    spread small luxuries around: candies, collars, perfumes, ribbons, sure to
                    please her.</p>
                <p>The day before she was to arrive, we were totally stunned and disappointed to
                    receive the following letter from our friend: “My very dear <persName
                        key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName>, I left from <placeName key="copenhagen"
                        >Copenhagen</placeName> for <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>
                    Wednesday morning. That evening I telephoned my <persName key="warnekros"
                        >Idol</persName> in <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>, from
                        <placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName>. Then I came Thursday evening to
                    the <placeName key="womensClinic">Frauenklinik</placeName>. An hour later he
                    decided to operate on me again. I am so exhausted by the preparatory treatment
                    that I am undergoing, that I can hardly write. Maybe surprise and a little fear
                    have something to do with it—since I know that it is very serious this time.
                    When I say that I’m afraid, it is rather for him, who is superbly courageous and
                    will stop at nothing to make me happy! Please forgive me if I don’t come to
                        <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> right away, but when I’m in his
                    presence I forget everything else. In <placeName key="denmark"
                        >Denmark</placeName> I had become a less timid person and for a few instants
                    I had been able to speak freely; but that was short-lived and all that’s left of
                    me is a humble little thing before this great adored maître. I have already gone
                    to bed and although he hasn’t told me, I know that the operation will be
                    tomorrow morning and that it will be very complicated. Even death seems sweet to
                    me here where my heart lives forever, but I understand that death would be a
                    betrayal to him. Therefore, there is a legitimate little delay in my arrival in
                        <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>, dear friend, but when I do come I
                    will be marriageable and who knows if one fine day I won’t also have
                    children?”</p>
                <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> received a similar letter and not only
                    did she feel a violent disappointment, but in reading it she also felt a
                    justified furor. Hadn’t she recommended to <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>,
                    during her time in <placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName>, to take
                    at least a year’s rest before having another surgery? She made her swear it,
                    fearing the magnetic attraction that the <persName key="warnekros"
                        >Professor</persName> cast over his patient would persuade her to desire the
                    surgery sooner, in order to be following once again in his adored wake. With
                    that, it was impossible to do anything, even send a telegram, since according to
                    the date, <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> should be on the operating table
                    at the moment that <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> was reading the
                    letter. Taken by a veritable despair, by rage, confronted with a fait accompli,
                    she opened the door to the room she had prepared for <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName> with such tenderness. Upon going into it, in spite of the
                    torrid heat that prevailed in <placeName key="marrakech">Marrakesh</placeName> in that season, a
                    glacial chill penetrated her and it seemed that the room had been plunged into a
                    greenish light; under the mosquito net, she felt the presence of a dead person.
                    She recoiled, felt a shiver and a few moments later it was with difficulty that
                    her <persName>husband</persName> was able to calm her fears.</p>
                <p>In <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>, the surgery, like almost 
                    all or almost all operations, was successful, but poor <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>
                    suffered like a condemned person and was unable to get her strength back.
                        <persName key="warnekros">Professor W</persName>. had to admit to himself
                    that his patient’s organism would not be able to fight against this last ordeal,
                    and feeling himself impotent to save her, his visits became less and less
                    frequent. <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’s passionate adoration for her
                    surgeon had become her unique reason to live; and so, deprived of his presence,
                    she no longer forced herself to react and stopped fighting to recover her
                    health. She was tormented by the thought that she had been to him only something
                    to experiment on. The time had come for vacations and the professor left the
                    clinic to take the rest indispensable to his profession. It was also a relief to
                    no longer feel his heart tighten when entering <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName>’s room; he realized that in spite of all that she had
                    endured and that he himself had tried, the poor creature was doomed. His
                    departure finally caused the unhappy girl to give into despair and to aggravate
                    the bitterness that she had served as a guinea pig for this person whom she
                    loved more than her life so much that she let herself die.</p>
                <p>We learned all of this afterwards, for the little nurse who had taken care of
                        <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> until the end, recounted her agony to
                        <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> when she went to <placeName
                        key="dresden">Dresden</placeName> a year later. In the midst of atrocious
                    physical and mental suffering, the heroic girl thought of only one thing: that
                        <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> knew nothing of this and wasn’t
                    troubled in her happiness. As for herself, at the price of much effort, she hid
                    her true condition from her, writing letters full of joy and hope for a rapid
                    recovery. <persName key="doctorF">Doctor F</persName>., assistant to the maître, a man full of
                    heart and pity, had done all that he could to soften the last weeks of the poor
                    little patient, coming to see her often, sending his wife, who brightened her
                    room with flowers and brought their little monkey to distract her. In the last
                    days of August, feeling that her agony was soon to end, <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName> asked for a notary to do her will. She left the little that
                    she had to <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>. She asked the little nurse
                    to fix her up after her death, coiffed and made up as <persName key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName> liked to do, and to remember her thus.</p>
                <p>“When I die let one put, Before nailing my coffin, A bit of rouge on my cheek, A
                    bit of black around my eyes.” From “la Coquetterie Posthume” [Posthumous Vanity]
                    of <persName key="gautierTheo">Théophile Gautier</persName></p>
                <p>She even recommended that they put pink polish on her nails.</p>
                <p>At the beginning of September she wrote with difficulty to <persName
                        key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> that she was much better and would have the
                    joy to be able, after a little while, to join <persName key="portaF">Nando</persName> and
                    her, in <placeName key="marrakech">Marrakech</placeName>. To me, she wrote:</p>
                <p>“I am beginning to get up and will soon be able to take a few steps in the
                    garden. I think happily about the not so far off day when I will be able to
                    leave for <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> and about the happy moments
                    that I will spend with all of you so dear to me; to the moment when I can
                    embrace you and express my gratitude for having known, thanks to your
                    intervention, my true life, my life as a woman. May you be blessed for that, my
                    dear <persName key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName>.”</p>
                <p>In spite of having been formally forbidden to inform anyone whatsoever, the
                    little nurse had secretly written the whole truth to <persName key="wegenerHo"
                        >Holger Wegener</persName>, the brother whom <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName> loved so very much. The end was now too close to inform
                        <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>; the decline being so rapid. It
                    had been a great and final joy for the dying one. She felt at peace surrounded
                    by true affection and died gently, her hand in his, her thoughts far away across
                    the sea towards that land of <placeName>Africa</placeName> that she would never
                    know….</p>
                <p>Under a slab of white stone, inscribed <persName key="lili">LILY ELBE</persName>
                    12 septembre 1931 repose the remains of little <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName>, but her soul, pure and beautiful, contemplates with bliss
                    the happiness of she who was the most dear to her. That is her reward for having
                    so suffered and so loved. </p>
                <p>If, as such a close witness to this story, I was determined to write an exact
                    account, it is in order to annihilate all that has been published about this
                    painful affair. With malicious intent, or as a farcical spectacle, one has tried
                    to debase two of the best people, whose honorable souls and high-mindedness
                    could serve as an example to a great many human beings, especially those who
                    have so unjustly slandered them. I believe in so doing to make myself worthy of
                    a memory that is so profoundly dear to me and of a friendship that I place among
                    the most beautiful that I possess.</p>
                <p>Translated by Anne M. Callahan Professor Emerita of French Loyola University
                    Chicago </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
