<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- RJP43 2019-02-12: I have decided to encode these songs slightly differently with regards to structure because of the way they appeared on genius.com and because of how they are delievered. The first song has a very clear breakup of verses and chorus with repetition typical to music nowadays. The second song is delivered more like a spoken word poem so I thought it best to prioritize individual lines instead of larger chunks like verse/chorus. -->

<favoriteSongs>
    <song fav="1">
<titie>Alien Boy</titie>
<artist>Oliver Tree</artist>
<producitionStmt>Produced by Casey Mattson, Imad Royal &amp; Oliver Tree</producitionStmt>
<album>Alien Boy - EP</album>
<chorus>I fell down to earth
From a hundred miles away and somehow
I still make it work
But it's overrated and somehow played out</chorus>
<verse n="1">Three doors down so you can't ignore it
I'll hunt you down like a tyrannosaurus
My teeth are sharp like the great white shark
Let me taste that flesh, it's my favourite part
Got an eagle beak, with the ostrich feet
7 spider eyes for every day of the week
Means I'm still up working while your bitch ass sleeps
I'm an alien among the human beings</verse>
<chorus>I fell down to earth
From a hundred miles away and somehow
I still make it work
But it's overrated and somehow played out</chorus>
<verse n="2">Ten doors down but you still can't see me
I talk a lot of shit so you won't believe me
I really wouldn't say anything else
I shouldn't be standing here all by myself
'Cause I'm out there
Tried to tell you that I'm out here on my own
I told you I was out there
Tried to tell you that I'm out here on my own</verse>
<chorus>I fell down to earth
From a hundred miles away and somehow
I still make it work
But it's overrated and somehow played out</chorus>
<bridge>I won't be here long at all</bridge>
<chorus>I fell down to earth
From a hundred miles away and somehow
I still make it work
But it's overrated and somehow played out</chorus>
</song>
<song fav="2">
<title>3%</title>
<artist>Hobo Johnson</artist>
<album>The Rise of Hobo Johnson</album>
    You should go and quit your job<lb/>
    And make all of those dreams come true<lb/>
    How is your self esteem? Huh?<lb/>
    That's important in what you're about to do<lb/>
    Don't talk to your friends<lb/>
    Their opinions hold so much weight<lb/>
    And that doesn't make sense<lb/>
    Even your family<lb/>
    Parents just don't understand<lb/>
    Except for <person>Will Smith</person>, he's got a great understanding<lb/>
    Make the time<lb/>
    Drop school, and people, and work to play<lb/>
    Music all night<lb/>
    You'll make a dollar an hour, at least you'll like your life<lb/>
    And roll with the punches even when it feels like you're getting <censor>fucking</censor> jumped but you're a real bad judge of it<lb/>
    Hold on tight, boy. Might be a <censor>fuckin'</censor>, hell of a ride<lb/>
    But, but, but, they said it's a three-percent chance<lb/>
    That I'm gonna make it<lb/>
    That's a little bit less than what it is in my mind<lb/>
    But it's ok, I think I can take it<lb/>
    They said it's a three-percent chance<lb/>
    My friends<lb/>
    That's what they said<lb/>
    And then I sat there and thought about it and almost believed it for a sec<lb/>
    But I think that they'll love me<lb/>
    Even if my soul is tainted and ugly<lb/>
    Tainted enough where no one should ever want stuff from me<lb/>
    But I'm lucky, lovely people say such nice things for no reason<lb/>
    Except for the songs that I sing them<lb/>
    When I was eighteen, I <censor>fucking</censor> prayed to God<lb/>
    That one day, I'll sing and the crowd would stop<lb/>
    But I'm still waiting<lb/>
    For the jaws to be dropped and the bras to be sailing<lb/>
    I'm still waiting<lb/>
    For the big contract and a payment<lb/>
    I'm still waiting<lb/>
    For all of my own friends to eat all of their own words<lb/>
    I bet it don't taste like blood, sweat, and tears, and the fear of regret and that ever elusive<lb/>
    Three-percent chance<lb/>
    That I'm gonna make it<lb/>
    It's a little bit less than what it is in my mind<lb/>
    But it's okay, I think I can take it<lb/>
    They said it's a three-percent, my friend<lb/>
    That's what they said<lb/>
    And then I sat there and thought about it<lb/>
    And almost believed it for a sec<lb/>
    But, now it's me versus the world<lb/>
    In a competition to see who can be less <censor>shitty</censor><lb/>
    Hold your own and if it floats your boat<lb/>
    You should row that boat home<lb/>
    But if my boat starts to sink, I'll probably stop singing and writing poems and cut my fucking hair and quit eating like I'm homeless, get a job!<lb/>
    But yesterday I said, but i made two-hundreds dollars in my first week just playing music and being who I want to be<lb/>
    She said. You think that's acceptable? You think that's an acceptable amount? I made twice the amount working at a shitty fucking job that I hate and every morning when I wake up I get really sad<lb/>
And I was just about to say at my friend's birthday party before they cut me off I was just about to say WAIT WAIT WAIT WAIT
You think that's an acceptable amount?<lb/>
    It's a three-percent chance<lb/>
    You'll be happy<lb/>
    Doing the same thing you do everyday for the next ten years<lb/>
    I think it's a three-percent chance<lb/>
    Then when I say, "Today's the day!"<lb/>
    You'll understand<lb/>
</song></favoriteSongs>
