<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../../schema/out/LEDA_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    rendition="lilielbe.org/context/Chapters/HAllatiniChapter.html"
    xml:base="https://gitlab.com/ctsdh/lili-elbe-code/raw/master/XSLT_sandbox/readingViews/input/bookSections/HAllatiniChapter.xml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Il et Elle</title>
                <title type="alternative">He and She</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="allatiniH" role="AUT">Hélène Allatini</persName>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Photographed by</resp>
                    <persName>Ashley Howdeshell</persName>
                    <persName ref="mg">Matthew Gallagher</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Images prepared by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mg">Matthew Gallagher</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="bc">Cristiana Bertola</persName>
                    <persName ref="kk">Katarzyna Klimek</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="ac" role="TRL">Anne M. Callahan</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation reviewed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="plc">Pamela L. Caughie</persName>
                    <persName ref="bc">Cristiana Bertola</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="ak">Abdurrafey Khan</persName>
                    <persName ref="bc">Cristiana Bertola</persName>
                    <persName ref="kk">Katarzyna Klimek</persName>
                    <persName ref="ep">Eleni Pamboukis</persName>
                    <persName ref="si">Scholastique Iradukunda</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance and/or XML proofing completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
                    <persName ref="am">Anna McCue</persName>
                    <persName ref="db">Darcy Brady</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>XML transformed into HTML
                            <date><!-- exact transformation date yyyy-mm-dd --></date> by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>HTML proofing completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="bc">Cristiana Bertola</persName>
                    <persName ref="db">Darcy Brady</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Loyola University Chicago</sponsor>
                <sponsor>Loyola's Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Lili Elbe Digital Archive</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when="2019-07-06">July 6th, 2019</date>
                <availability>
                    <p select="source">Private Collection.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                        Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc source="Codex" xml:lang="fre-B">
                <p>A 40-page printed chapter included in a hardbound book.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy source="https://arc-staging.dh.tamu.edu/index.php/Submitting_RDF">
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="discipline">
                        <catDesc>Literature</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="genre">
                        <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="text">
                        <catDesc>https://gitlab.com/ctsdh/lili-elbe-code/raw/master/XSLT_sandbox/plainText/output/HAllatiniChapter.txt</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="dc" xml:id="date">
                        <catDesc>1939</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="dcterms" xml:id="isPartOf" xml:lang="fre-B">
                        <catDesc>Originally published in <hi rend="italics">Mosaïques</hi></catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <!--<category source="dcterms" xml:id="isPartOf_trans" xml:lang="eng">
                    <catDesc><!-\- book or periodical title translated-\-></catDesc>
                </category>-->
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>We are in the process of re-encoding Allatini's chapter so that the French
                        original and the English translation match paragraph by paragraph. The
                        revised version will be available by January 2020.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>We have removed the hyphenation that appears in the printed text during
                        digitization and encoding. Original hyphenation can be consulted in the
                        facsimile images.</p>
                </hyphenation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="original">
                <div rend="chapter" n="?">
                    <pb source="Copyright"
                        facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_03.jpg"/>
                    <head>IL ET ELLE</head>
                    <pb n="198" facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_04.jpg"/>
                    <p><!-- going through and grabbing articles within Key ID tags AM 12.2.19 -->Ce
                        fut vers la fin de l'année 1916 que je fis leur connaissance. <persName
                            key="allatiniE">Mon fiancé</persName> se battait alors dans l'armée
                        italienne, sur le front <placeName key="dolomites">des
                        Dolomites</placeName>. Dans ses moments de repos, il écrivait des contes de
                        fées, destinés à nos futurs enfants. Comme il appréciait le talent de
                        l'artiste danoise <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda Wegener</persName>, dont
                        les dessins paraissaient dans <hi rend="italics">La Vie Parisienne</hi>, que
                        je lui envoyais régulièrement, il m'avait chargée de m'adresser à elle pour
                        les illustrations de ses contes. Je savais qu'elle avait fait une très jolie
                        couverture pour un livre de <persName key="magreM">Maurice Magre</persName>,
                        je demandai donc à <persName>mon vieil ami</persName> de nous mettre en
                        rapport. C'est ainsi que nous sonnions, quelques jours plus tard, à la porte
                            d'<placeName key="studioLille">un atelier de la rue de
                        Lille</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>Nous pénétrâmes dans une grande pièce arrangée avec goût : quelques meubles
                        anciens, des châles espagnols, des vases de fleurs et les toiles du ménage
                        scandinave, car <persName key="wegenerE">le mari</persName> aussi était
                        peintre. <pb style="page" n="199"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_05.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> Paysagiste accompli, il excellait
                        dans la perspective. <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> et <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Einar Wegener</persName> nous offrirent des sièges et
                        prirent eux-mêmes place en face de nous sur un grand divan noir et or, garni
                        de coussins aux coloris divers. Ainsi, côte à côte, ils me rappelaient les
                        personnages des contes d'<persName key="andersen">Andersen</persName>,
                        particulièrement ceux de <hi rend="italics">La Reine de Neiges :</hi>
                        <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda Wegener</persName> si blonde, si claire,
                        personnifiait, pour moi, l'autre Gerda, celle qui était allée, au péril de
                        sa vie, rechercher son cher Kaj dans le palais enchanté, tandis qu'<persName
                            key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> était une exacte réplique de ce
                        <!-- 2019-04-01: not sure what a Kaj is? RJP:9/30/19 - Comparing Gerda to Gerda (fictional), a character in “The Snow Queen” (1844), a fairy tale by Hans Christian Andersen and Kaj is
Kaj (fictional),  a character in “The Snow Queen” (1844), a fairy tale by Hans Christian Andersen
 -->
                        Kaj au sourire espiègle, se jouant sur de lèvres bien dessinées. <persName
                            key="wegenerG">La jeune artiste</persName> portait les cheveux tirés en
                        arrière, noués en un chignon bas sur la nuque, et deux rouleaux, pareils aux
                        marteaux du XVIII<hi rend="super">e</hi> siècle, ornaient ses tempes; un
                        ruban de velours noir faisait ressortir davantage la blancheur de sa gorge.
                        Dans une cage voisine, deux perruches inséparables — l'une vert acide et
                        l'autre cendre verte — s'ébattaient joyeusement. Elles semblaient l’emblème
                        vivant de leurs maîtres, qu’on sentait si tendrement unis, inséparables eux
                        aussi. Une égale limpidité éclairait les prunelles dorées d'<persName
                            key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> et le regard céruléen de <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>. On avait le sentiment que leur clarté
                        était le reflet même de leur âme nette et propre, et je fus entraînée vers
                        eux par un courant de sympathie, qui devait se transformer bientôt en une
                        indissoluble amitié.</p>
                    <p>Nous causâmes du motif qui nous amenait, et <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> parut très désireuse d'exécuter ce travail. <pb
                            style="page" n="200"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_06.jpg"/> Après
                        que nous eûmes admiré les œuvres des deux artistes, il fut convenu qu'elle
                        écrirait le soir même à <persName key="allatiniE">mon fiancé</persName>,
                        pour se mettre d'accord avec lui, et ils décidèrent de faire sa connaissance
                        le jour de notre mariage. Au cours de la réception qui suivit la cérémonie
                        nuptiale, je présentai le jeune ménage à <persName key="allatiniE">mon
                            mari</persName>; comme moi, il le prit aussitôt en amitié. Nous nous
                        revîmes le surlendemain, longuement, en prenant le thé à <placeName
                            key="viennoise">la Boulangerie Viennoise</placeName>; ce fut là qu'on
                        décida de tous les détails du volume.</p>
                    <p>Nous partîmes le même soir en voyage de noces, pour <placeName key="rome"
                            >Rome</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>Dès mon retour, cinq mois plus tard, nos relations amicales reprirent, de
                        plus en plus cordiales et affectueuses. Je venais de perdre ma
                            <persName>mère</persName> et j'attendais <persName key="allatiniJ">mon
                            premier enfant</persName>. Mes amis scandinaves m'entourèrent et je
                        trouvai un grand réconfort dans leur affection les jours où, sans nouvelles
                        de <persName key="allatiniE">mon mari</persName>, ils se multipliaient en
                        attentions et tâchaient de me divertir de leur mieux, pour me détourner de
                        mon angoisse.</p>
                    <p>Au mois de mai 1918, se forma à <placeName key="versailles"
                            >Versailles</placeName>,
                        <!-- KK: 2019-04-01: do i encode the counsil in any specific way?--> le
                        Conseil Supérieur de Guerre des Alliés. Le <persName key="robilantM">général
                            Nicolis de
                        Robilant</persName><!-- KK: 2019-04-01: Is the a reason why its "robilantM" and not "robilantN" in the prosopography?-->,
                        chef de <persName key="allatiniE">mon mari</persName> et vieil ami de sa
                        famille, fut désigné pour représenter l'<placeName key="italy"
                            >Italie</placeName>. Dès son arrivée, il vint me voir, accompagné de son
                        officier d'ordonnance, le comte <persName key="carrobioM">Mario di
                            Carrobio</persName>, beau comme un jeune dieu, drapé dans la superbe
                        cape bleu de ciel des officiers de cavalerie. A peine entré en conversation,
                            <pb style="page" n="201"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_07.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/>
                        <persName key="robilantM">l'adorable général</persName> me dit d'une air
                        malicieux : « Que diriez-vous si <persName key="allatiniE">Eric</persName>
                        était nommé à <placeName key="versailles">Versailles</placeName>? En
                        seriez-vous très ennuyée? »</p>
                    <p>Je faillis lui sauter au cou.</p>
                    <p>Quelques jours plus tard, <persName key="allatiniE">mon mari</persName>
                        arrivait à <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> pour rejoindre son
                        nouveau poste et, peu de temps après, je m'établissais à <placeName
                            key="versailles">Versailles</placeName>, avec <persName key="allatiniJ"
                            >ma petite fille</persName>. Nous y menions une vie délicieuse,
                        fréquentant les autres jeunes ménages des quatre nations, parmi lesquels
                        nous cimentâmes quelques amitiés fidèles.</p>
                    <p><!-- removing all of these instances of the Wegeners tagged as one. AM 12.3.19 -->Le
                        couple Wegener vint nous voir souvent dans <placeName>la charmante
                            villa</placeName> que nous avions louée, et décida de passer la fin de
                        l'été et une partie de l'automne à <placeName key="versailles"
                            >Versailles</placeName>. Ils prirent un petit appartement <choice><orig/><reg>à</reg></choice><placeName
                            key="reservoirs">rue de
                        Réservoirs</placeName>
                        et nous nous vîmes quotidiennement. Je me rappelle, non sans émotion, les
                        exquises matinées dans <placeName>le parc du Château</placeName>, aux côtés
                            d'<persName key="wegenerE"
                        >Einar</persName>,<!--BC: 2019-03-28: There shouldn't be a comma preceding a parenthesis.-->
                            (<persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> pour ses intimes), tandis qu'il
                        m'initiait, tout en peignant, aux beautés cachées des jardins. Ce fut lui
                        qui me montra que chaque bassin était d'une couleur différente, chose que je
                        n'avais jamais remarquée. Il avait une âme <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >d'enfant</persName>, pure, ouverte à la nature et à toutes ses
                        merveilles. Nous nous entendions fort bien; d'ailleurs, qui ne se serait
                        entendu avec <persName key="wegenerE">ce charmant garçon</persName>, plein
                        de douceur et de tendresse. Il adorait <persName key="wegenerG">sa
                            femme</persName> et s'efforçait de lui épargner les moindres corvées de
                        la vie courante; c'était lui qui commandait aux
                            <persName>fournisseurs</persName>, aux <persName>marchands de
                            couleurs</persName>, écrivait aux <persName>éditeurs</persName>,
                        achetait les provisions, afin <pb style="page" n="202"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_08.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> qu'elle pût se consacrer entièrement
                        à son art. De son côté, elle lui témoignait une affection presque
                        maternelle. Dans le quartier, tout le monde aimait <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Bé</persName>, si poli, si plein de tact et de gentillesse;
                            <persName>les commerçants</persName> lui procuraient tout le charbon et
                        le sucre nécessaires, même dans les périodes de restrictions où il était le
                        plus difficile d'en obtenir. Les deux époux ne se quittaient jamais,
                        partageant chaque joie, chaque émotion, dormant côte à côte avec leur petite
                        chienne fox, « <persName key="hvappe">Vâpe</persName> ».</p>
                    <p><choice><orig>A</orig><reg>À</reg></choice>
                            <placeName
                            key="paris">Paris</placeName>, ils quittèrent leur atelier de <placeName
                            key="studioLille">la rue de Lille</placeName>, pour s'installer dans les
                        environs du <placeName key="champs"
                        >Champ-de-Mars</placeName><!--BC: 2019-03-28: In prosopography, Champ is misspelled as "champs".-->,
                        dans un atelier plus grand et plus agréable que le précédent. Nous habitions
                        alors près de <placeName key="lAlmaPlace">la place de l'Alma</placeName>, ce
                        qui nous permettait de les voir souvent, même dans <placeName key="paris"
                            >cette ville</placeName> où il est si difficile, à cause des distances,
                        de fréquenter ses amis comme on le voudrait.</p>
                    <p>Je me souviens d'une petite histoire assez curieuse qui m'advint chez les
                        Wegener. Ils nous avaient invités à dîner, pour nous faire connaître un de
                        leurs meilleurs et plus anciens amis, le diplomate danois <persName key="tb"
                            >T. B.</persName>, homme fort cultivé.</p>
                    <p>— Vous verrez combien il est irrésistible et captivant, me dit <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>, « il a une conversation éblouissante et
                        connaît son XVIII<hi rend="super">e</hi>siècle comme personne, mais il a un
                        grand défaut : il ne
                        peut <!-- BC caught a missing negative form. we corrected this throughout using choice markup AM 12.6.19 --><choice><orig/><reg>pas</reg></choice>
                        voir une jolie femme sans lui faire la cour, et je vous préviens qu'il est
                        très entreprenant, surtout avec les
                        blondes! »<!-- anchor comment about the weird quote marks --><!--BC: 2019-03-28: The use of the quotation marks in this place is not justified.--></p>
                    <p>Le soir du dîner, elle me présenta <persName key="tb">ce Don Juan</persName><!-- not literally Don Juan. maybe an anchor comment would be appropriate AM 12.6.19 -->
                        <pb style="page" n="203"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_09.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> nordique; arrivé le matin même de
                            <placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhague</placeName>, il devait repartir
                        quelques jours plus tard pour <placeName key="madrid">Madrid</placeName>,
                        son nouveau poste. J'êtais sa voisine de table, et je ne
                        sais <choice><orig/><reg>pas</reg></choice>
                        si la fatigue du voyage l'avait abruti à ce point, mais il ne m'adressa pas
                        la parole et laissa même tomber la conversation chaque fois que je fis un
                        effort pour l'engager. Après les propos de <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName>, je commençais, je l'avoue, à me sentir un peu piquée.
                        Nous en étions à la salade, quand le pied de <persName key="tb">mon
                            voisin</persName> vint se poser sur le mien, comme une lourde caresse.
                        « Ça, c'est trop fort, me dis-je, il prend un air accablé, m'ignore
                        complètement et puis, il s'imagine qu'il peut me faire du pied... et en
                        chaussettes encore! » Car, pour l'occasion, le coupable avait enlevé son
                        soulier! J'essayais de retirer mon pied, sans attirer l'attention des
                            <persName>autres convives</persName>, tâche difficile, celui de
                            <persName key="tb">mon agresseur</persName> étant tenace et pesant.
                        <choice><orig>A</orig><reg>À</reg></choice> peine
                        l'avais-je dégagé qu'il s'en emparait à nouveau. Je me sentais devenir
                        cramoisie : à ma grande terreur, le pied entreprenant montait lentement et
                        arrivait déjà plus haut que la cheville, tandis que son <persName key="tb"
                            >propriétaire</persName> continuait à garder son air impassible et
                        hypocritement serein. Une pareille sournoiserie me fit sortir de moi-même :
                        « Tu vas voir » me dis-je, et, rassemblant toutes mes forces, je lui envoyai
                        un formidable coup de pied. Un hurlement canin retentit : c'était <persName
                            key="hvappe">la petite chienne fox</persName> la véritable coupable, qui
                        avait reçu le châtiment. Ceci prouve, une fois de plus, qu'il faut se méfier
                        de son imagination.</p>
                    <pb style="page" n="204"
                        facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_10.jpg"/>
                    <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/>
                    <p>Je me rappelle un autre petit fait, qui advint aussi chez les Wegener. Je
                        devais dîner chez mon amie <persName key="schildtBar">Baby de
                            Friedlander-Fuld</persName>
                        — <!--BC: 2019-03-28:This is a horizontal parenthesis, how should it be marked up?-->maintenant
                            <persName key="schildtBar">baronne de Goldschmidt-Rothschild</persName>
                        — <!--BC: 2019-03-28: This is a horizontal parenthesis, how should it be marked up?-->de
                        passage à <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>. Nous projetions d'aller
                        ensuite toutes deux chez <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> et
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> qui donnaient une petite fête.
                        En arrivant chez <persName key="schildtBar">Baby</persName>, je remarquai
                        son air désappointé. « Je suis furieuse, me dit-elle, moi qui me réjouissais
                        tant de mettre ce soir ma nouvelle robe de tulle mordoré brodée d'or, je ne
                        puis le faire! »</p>
                    <p>— Qu'y a-t-il? T'a-t-on manqué de parole?</p>
                    <p>— Non, elle est là, derrière toi, sur une chaise.</p>
                    <p>— Mais alors, va-t-elle mal? est-elle trop étroite... Trop large? Il y a
                        peut-être moyen de l'arranger...</p>
                    <p>— Non, rien de cela, au contraire, elle me va à merveille, mais cet animal
                            d'<persName>Hellstern</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-28: Hellstern and Sons may be the name of the shoemaker referenced here. As a manufacturer and/or as a historic person, how should he be marked up?-->
                        ne m'a pas livré mes souliers de satin marron...</p>
                    <p>— N'as-tu donc pas une vieille paire d'un brun quelconque qui pourrait
                        aller?</p>
                    <p>— Non, la seule paire que j'aie est dans un tel état qu'il n'y faut pas
                        songer; les bouts sont blancs et si usés qu'on voit la doublure.</p>
                    <p>J'eus une inspiration de génie : « Il n'y a qu'à les frotter avec une barre de
                        chocolat et on ne s'apercevra de rien. » On courut à la cuisine et, quelques
                        minutes plus tard, mon amie apparaissait à table dans une ravissante
                        robe, avec des souliers marron impeccables.</p>
                    <p>En arrivant chez les Wegener, elle reçut des <pb style="page" n="205"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_11.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> compliments de tout le monde. Nous
                        nous assîmes et on commença de faire un peu de musique. La petite chienne
                            <persName key="hvappe">Vâpe</persName> qui, vous le savez, avait une
                        attirance particulière pour les pieds, vint se coucher devant ceux de mon
                        amie <persName key="schildtBar">Baby</persName>, mais à peine eut-elle
                        flairé l'odeur du chocolat, qu'elle se précipita sur le bout des souliers et
                        se mit à les lécher goulument. On essaya de l'en empêcher, mais elle
                        commença à grogner d'une façon peu rassurante. Finalement, elle arracha une
                        des chaussures du pied de <persName>sa
                        propriétaire</persName><!-- this is saying "his owner" but that could be Gerda or Einar AM 12.2.19 -->
                        et se sauva sous une commode pour s'en régaler plus à l'aise. Ce fut un
                        éclat de rire général et nous dûmes expliquer l'origine de ce festin, ce qui
                        obtint le plus vif succès.</p>
                    <p>Mais revenons à nos moutons, ou plutôt à nos peintres. Comme j'admirais, un
                        jour, le ravissant dos d'un nu de femme exécuté par <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName>, celle-ci me confia : « Vous ne devinerez jamais qui a
                        posé pour ce dos... c'est <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> en
                        personne. Depuis quelque temps déjà, il me sert de modèle, ce qui m'est fort
                        commode, car, nulle part, je ne pourrais trouver un dos pareil. »
                        <choice>  
                            <orig>La</orig>  
                            <reg>Le</reg>  
                        </choice> 
                         tableau représentait une sorte de bacchante blonde, aux cheveux courts,
                        couronnée de pampres et allongée nonchalamment sur un lit de repos, la tête
                        légèrement inclinée et tournée vers le public. Les jambes étaient aussi
                        celles de <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>. On eut juré des jambes de
                        femme, si longues et fuselées. Je n'en revenais pas! <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> avait pris une petite photo d'<persName
                            key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> pendant une séance, et je la suppliai de
                        l'emporter au restaurant, où nous devions dîner avec nos maris et des <pb
                            style="page" n="206"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_12.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> amis communs. On fit circuler
                        l'image qui stupéfia tout le monde. Notre amie, <persName key="marquiseSG"
                            >la marquise de S. G.</persName>, dont le mari était en retard, s'écria :
                        « Faisons une farce à <persName key="marquis">Emilio</persName>, il va
                        arriver d'un instant à l'autre. Que <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> lui montre la photo comme celle d'une de ses amies, et
                        nous verrons s'il reconnaît <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>. » En
                        bon Napolitain, coureur de femmes, <persName key="marquis">le
                            marquis</persName> fut complètement affolé par ce nu ravissant : « Oh! Qui
                        est-ce, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>? Vous dites que c'est une
                        amie à vous qui a posé pour vous faire plaisir... mais il faut que je la
                        connaisse tout de suite. Jurez-moi que vous me présenterez à elle. »
                        Contenant mal son envie de rire, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>
                        le lui promit, mais ajouta que la personne en question était assez farouche
                        et d'ailleurs, absente de <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> en ce
                        moment. Plus elle faisait surgir de difficultés, plus le pauvre <persName
                            key="marquis">marquis</persName> s'enflammait. Il prenait même <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> à témoin, le priant de rappeler à <persName
                            key="wegenerG">sa femme</persName>, s'il le fallait, la promesse qu'elle
                        venait de faire. Nous en pleurions de rire. Le brave <persName
                            key="marquiseSG">Emilio</persName> refusa net de rendre la photo. Il la
                        garda dans son portefeuille et, depuis, il ne se passa pas de jour qu'il ne
                        se renseignât sur le retour de <persName key="wegenerE">la belle
                            bacchante</persName>. Il en avait à ce point perdu la tête qu'en sortant
                        d'une grande soirée, au moment de présenter son numéro de vestiaire, il
                        donna par erreur la fameuse photo : « Vieux saligaud! Pour qui me
                        prenez-vous? » lui cria <persName>la vierge
                        mûre</persName><!--BC: 2019-030-22: Should this character be given a key ID?-->
                        du vestiaire, en la lui lançant presque au visage.</p>
                    <p>Devant le tour tragique que semblaient prendre les événements, nous décidâmes
                        de révéler la vérité <pb style="page" n="207"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_13.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> à l'incandescent <persName
                            key="marquis">marquis</persName>. Il le prit fort mal, déchira la photo,
                        dans un accès de rage noire, et, pendant des semaines, n'adressa plus la
                        parole à aucun de nous.</p>
                    <p>Je ne
                        puis <choice><orig/><reg>pas</reg></choice>
                        m'empêcher de sortir encore une fois de mon sujet, pour vous raconter une
                        anecdote qui date d'environ cinquante ans et dont le héros est <persName
                            key="naplesArchbishop">l'archevêque</persName> de <placeName
                            key="naples">Naples</placeName>, oncle de notre <persName key="marquis"
                            >marquis</persName>.</p>
                    <p>Ce <persName key="naplesArchbishop">prélat</persName>, connu pour son
                        avarice, avait depuis des années <persName>un unique valet</persName> qui
                        servait d'homme à tout faire, et auquel il ne donnait cependant que huit
                        lires par mois d'appointements. Ce serviteur vint un jour lui demander une
                        augmentation.</p>
                    <p>— <persName key="naplesArchbishop">Monseigneur</persName> sait combien je lui
                        suis attaché et que je serais inconsolable de devoir quitter son service,
                        mais je ne puis
                        <choice><orig/><reg>pas</reg></choice> continuer
                        ainsi. Le prix de la vie augmente tous les jours et je n'arrive plus à
                        m'acheter l'essentiel, avec mes huit lires. D'ailleurs, tous les autres
                        gagnent jusqu'à vingt lires et vont encore être augmentés. Je viens donc
                        prier <persName key="naplesArchbishop">Monseigneur</persName> de m'accorder
                        au moins deux lires de plus par mois.</p>
                    <p>— Ce que tu viens de dire est juste, répliqua <persName
                            key="naplesArchbishop">Son Excellence</persName>, mais, à mon vif
                        regret, il m'est impossible de te donner davantage. Cependant, comme je
                        comprends fort bien que ton salaire actuel soit insuffisant et comme je suis
                        très satisfait de tes services, je veux faire quelque chose pour toi. Je
                        t'accorde donc, à partir d'aujourd'hui, deux heures de liberté chaque
                        après-midi, de une à trois heures, au moment où la circulation est le <pb
                            style="page" n="208"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_14.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> plus dense, sur <placeName>le Pont du
                            Château de
                        l'Œuf</placeName><!-- BC: 2019-03-22: This place isn't included in the proposography. Should it get a key ID?-->,
                        tu pourras y aller mendier. Ainsi, tout s'arrangera pour le mieux. »</p>
                    <p>Et l'on pu voir quotidiennement, à l'entrée du
                        <placeName>Pont</placeName><!--BC: 2019-03-22: This place (le Pont du Château de l'Oeuf) isn't included in the proposography. Should it get a key ID?-->,
                        le <persName>valet</persName>
                        <!--BC: 2019=03-22: Should this character appear in the prosopography and get a key ID?-->
                        de <persName key="naplesArchbishop">l'archevêque</persName> tendre la main.
                        Et cela ne choquait personne... O dolce <placeName key="naples"
                            >Napoli</placeName>!</p>
                    <p>Je reviens aux Wegener pour ne plus les quitter. Je demandai à <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> depuis quand elle s'était aperçue, pour
                        la première fois, des contours féminins de <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Bé</persName>.</p>
                    <p>— Cela remonte loin, me répondit-elle, même avant la guerre. Nous étions
                        encore à <placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhague</placeName> et je faisais le
                        portrait d'<persName key="larsen">une actrice</persName> très connue. Un
                        jour, elle téléphona, au dernier moment, pour décommander la séance. J'étais
                        furieuse et déçue, ayant gardé mon après-midi pour elle. <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>, me voyant contrariée de ne 
                        pouvoir <choice><orig/><reg>pas</reg></choice>
                        avancer mon travail, s'offrit à remplacer <persName key="larsen">le
                            modèle</persName>, du moins pour la robe, s'il parvenait à la passer. Je
                        fus stupéfaite de voir que, non seulement elle lui allait à merveille, mais
                        encore qu'il avait des épaules de femme, éblouissantes. Je m'amusai alors à
                        compléter l'illusion en posant sur sa tête une perruque blonde, qui me
                        restait du carnaval et en le fardant de mon mieux. Je me mis ensuite à
                        peindre et fus surprise, en plein travail, par <persName key="larsen">mon
                            véritable modèle</persName>, qui venait s'excuser de m'avoir fait faux
                        bond. En voyant sa robe sur une autre personne, elle fut un peu étonnée,
                        mais ne reconnut pas <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>. Pendant un
                        bon moment je lui fis croire qu'une amie l'avait remplacée pour me rendre
                        service <pb style="page" n="209"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_15.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mozaïques"/> et me permettre d'avancer son
                        portrait. Le timbre de voix de <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> finit
                        par le trahir et <persName key="larsen">la jeune femme</persName>, riant à
                        gorge déployée, ne parvenait pas à revenir de son ébahissement. Elle
                        s'invita à dîner et fit monter du champagne « pour boire à la santé de sa
                        nouvelle amie, <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> ». Pendant le repas, on
                        baptisa <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> au champagne, et depuis lors,
                        il posa souvent pour moi, se déguisant en femme chaque fois que l'occasion
                        s'en présentait. <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> adorait ce genre de
                        travail et aimait à mystifier les gens, qui le prenaient invariablement pour
                        une fille d'Eve.
                        <!--BC: 2019-03-22: This is a figure of speech, but it referes to a person, though biblical figure. Should it be marked up and given a key ID?-->
                        <choice><orig>A</orig><reg>À</reg></choice>
                        divers bals costumés, il fit sensation et prit de plus en plus l'habitude de
                        personnifier <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>. Un soir, qu'enrhumée, je
                        ne pouvais
                        <choice><orig/><reg>pas</reg></choice> sortir,
                        il mit ma plus jolie robe décolletée. Après que je l'eus soigneusement
                        coiffé et maquillé, il se rendit, en compagnie d'<persName>un de nos jeunes
                            amis</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-22: Should he be given a key ID? -->, à
                        un dîner suivi de soirée dansante qu'on donnait chaque quinzaine à un club
                            d'<persName>artistes</persName> et de <persName>gens du
                                monde</persName> auquel nous appartenions. <choice><orig>A</orig><reg>À</reg></choice> part ce
                            <persName>jeune
                        ami</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-22: Should he be given a key ID?--> et
                            <persName key="madameB">une dame</persName> de notre connaissance,
                        personne n'était dans le secret. Tous deux présentèrent <persName key="lili"
                            >la nouvelle venue</persName> comme la sœur du peintre <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Einar Wegener</persName> et ma belle-sœur, ajoutant que
                        nous étions retenus à la maison par la grippe. La belle <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> eut un succès fou et décrocha d'une façon foudroyante
                        le cœur d'un officier de cavalerie, <persName key="countT">le comte de
                            T.</persName>, âgé de cinquante-cinq à soixante ans, qui, de toute la
                        soirée, ne la quitta pas et l'accabla de compliments. Elle dut promettre de
                        le revoir; il tint à la reconduire jusque chez elle et prit congé d'elle <pb
                            style="page" n="210"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_16.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mozaïques"/> à regret. Le surlendemain, comme je
                        travaillais seule dans mon atelier, on sonna à la porte; quelle ne fut pas ma
                        surprise en me trouvant face à face avec le <persName key="countT"
                            >monsieur</persName>, mûr et correct, que <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> m'avait décrit comme son amoureux et qui se tenait sur
                        le seuil, un peu gêné, les bras chargés de fleurs. Les miens faillirent en
                        tomber!</p>
                    <p>– N'est-ce pas ici que demeure
                            <!-- don't know if the superscript will render inside the persName AM 12.3.19 --><persName
                            key="lili">M<hi rend="super">lle</hi> Lily
                        Wegener</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-22: Lily Wegener is not mentioned underneath the key ID "lili".-->?
                        balbutia <persName key="countT">le pauvre homme</persName>. Auriez-vous
                        l'obligeance de lui dire que <persName key="countT">le colonel de
                            T.</persName> désirerait la voir.</p>
                    <p>Je le priai d'entrer et de s'asseoir, expliquant que, malheureusement,
                            <persName key="lili">ma belle-sœur</persName> était sortie et rentrerait
                        tard. Il en parut bouleversé et resta une bonne demi-heure à m'entretenir
                        des qualités physiques et morales de <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>.
                        Tout en approuvant, j'avais toutes les peines du monde à garder mon sérieux.
                        Je pris cependant l'initiative de lui apprendre que <persName key="lili"
                            >cette enfant</persName> allait repartir bientót, ayant à régler des
                        affaires de famille au <placeName key="denmark">Danemark</placeName>. Enfin
                            <persName key="countT">le comte de T.</persName> se retira, en
                        m'assurant qu'il ne tarderait pas à revenir. Il tint parole. Entretemps,
                        notre amie,
                            <!-- don't know if the superscript will render inside the persName AM 12.3.19 --><persName
                            key="madameB">M<hi rend="super">me</hi> de B.</persName>, qui avait
                        assisté au fameux dîner et au coup de foudre militaire, vint nous raconter
                        que <persName key="countT">le pauvre colonel</persName>, de plus en plus
                        fou, ne songeait qu'à <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> et parlait même
                        de divorcer pour l'épouser. Aussi, quand il revint pour la voir, lui
                        annonçai-je qu'elle était partie subitement la veille, pour <placeName
                            key="copenhagen">Copenhague</placeName>. Le malheureux fut au désespoir.
                        Il se confia à <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>, et lui dit son
                        étonnement de lui trouver si peu de ressemblance <pb style="page" n="211"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_17.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mozaïques"/> avec sa délicieuse sœur. « Peut-être
                        un rien dans le regard, mais c'est bien tout. » Il nous fallut des efforts
                        héroïques pour ne pas nous trahir et reconduire <persName key="countT">le
                            colonel</persName>, en gardant l'air qui convenait à la situation.</p>
                    <p>Par la suite, nous fîmes envoyer à
                            <!-- don't know if the superscript will render inside the persName AM 12.3.19 --><persName
                            key="madameB">M<hi rend="super">me</hi>de B.</persName> des cartes de
                            <placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhague</placeName> signées « <persName
                            key="lili">Lily</persName> », où <persName key="lili">cette jeune
                            personne</persName> lui confirmait la longueur de son séjour et lui
                        laissait entrevoir de vagues projets de mariage, tout cela pour calmer
                            <persName key="countT">sa malheureuse victime</persName>.</p>
                    <p>Le temps fit heureusement son œuvre, et nous ne revîmes plus <persName
                            key="countT">le comte de T.</persName></p>
                    <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> avait connu <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> adolescent, en
                        suivant les cours de dessin et de peinture à <placeName key="academyArt"
                            >l'Académie des Beaux-Arts</placeName> de <placeName key="copenhagen"
                            >Copenhague</placeName>. <persName key="wegenerG">La jeune
                            artiste</persName> avait voué à <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >l'étudiant</persName> une profonde affection et il était devenu son
                        meilleur ami. <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> était très courtisée
                        et <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, violemment épris, dépérissait,
                        en se rendant compte qu'il ne serait jamais pour elle qu'un très cher ami et
                        confident. <choice><orig>A</orig><reg>À</reg></choice>
                        dix-sept ans, la jolie <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> eut une
                        déception amoureuse, à la suite de laquelle elle devint triste et
                        indifférente aux hommages de ses autres flirts. A ce moment, elle apprit que
                        le pauvre <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> se mourait d'amour pour
                        elle. Il souffrait de crises cardiaques et <persName>les médecins</persName>
                        déclaraient que cet état nerveux pouvait devenir fatal. Déjà meurtrie dans
                        son inclination, <persName key="wegenerG">la jeune fille</persName> ne put
                        supporter l'idée de perdre <persName key="wegenerE">l'être</persName> qui
                        lui était le plus cher, après <persName key="gottliebMrs">sa
                        mère</persName>. Elle courut au chevet de <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Bé</persName> lui dire qu'elle avait réfléchi <pb style="page" n="212"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_18.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mozaïques"/> et consentait à devenir sa femme.
                        L'effet fut magique et, <!--BC: 2019-03-23: There shouldn't be a comma between two independent clauses.--><!-- @@@@AM fix later!!!! -->
                        <persName key="wegenerE">le jeune homme</persName>, subitement remis, put
                        bientôt conduire à l'autel <persName key="wegenerG">la blonde
                            fille</persName> du <persName>pasteur Got<choice>
                                <orig/>
                                <reg>t</reg>
                            </choice>lieb</persName>. <persName>Ces
                        enfants</persName> de
                        dix-sept et vingt ans à peine, étaient d'une candeur puérile et le jeune
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, aussi vierge que <persName
                            key="wegenerG">sa petite épouse</persName>, ne s'était jamais demandé
                        si, physiquement, il serait à la hauteur des devoirs que son nouvel état lui
                        imposait. Naïve, et ne sachant qu'imparfaitement ce que le mariage réserve
                        aux filles, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> ne s'étonna qu'à
                        moitié, en constatant combien douces et superficielles étaient les caresses
                        qu'elle recevait de <persName key="wegenerE">son heureux époux</persName>.
                        Ils étaient pleinement satisfaits l'un de l'autre et, quand <persName
                            key="wegenerG">la jeune femme</persName> éprouvait certains soirs de
                        printemps quelque langueur qu'elle ne parvenait pas à définir, la vie en
                        commmun était si harmonieuse, si lisse et tendre, qu'elle n'y attachait
                        qu'une vague importance. Au bout de longs mois, tous deux constatèrent que
                        les joies sexuelles avaient été refusées à leur union, ce qui ne les empêcha
                        nullement de continuer à vivre en parfaite harmonie. Ils avaient les mêmes
                        goûts en art, la même conception de la vie; enfin, ils ne pouvaient, même un
                        instant, se passer l'un de l'autre. Ils s'aimaient et se disputaient comme
                        deux gosses et j'entends encore
                            <!-- don't know whether the superscript will render within the persName AM 12.3.19 --><persName
                            key="gottliebMrs">M<hi rend="super">me</hi> Gottlieb</persName>
                        s'écrier, lors d'une de ses visites à <placeName key="paris"
                            >Paris</placeName> : « Mais quand cesserez-vous donc d'être des enfants? »
                        Et <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> de
                        <!--BC: 2019-03-23: I doubt that the preposition "de" was necessary here.--><!-- AM check later -->
                        lui rèpondre: « Mais, <persName key="gottliebMrs">maman</persName>, j'espère
                        bien jamais! »</p>
                    <p>Depuis quelque temps, je remarquais avec angoisse,<!--BC: 2019-03-23: The comma should not precede a parenthesis.-->
                        <pb style="page" n="213"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_19.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mozaïques"/> (ou plutôt on me l'avait fait
                        remarquer), que la silhouette de <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>,
                        déjà efféminée, devenait de plus en plus équivoque : ses vestons semblaient
                        plus pincés à la taille, sa poitrine se bombait, sa démarche ondulante
                        rappelait celle d'une odalisque; sa voix même prenait des inflexions
                        féminines. <persName key="allatiniE">Mon mari</persName> l'avait constaté
                        aussi et « on », c'est-à-dire ma famille, mon entourage, mes
                            <persName>connaissances</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-28: Should "acquaintances" get a key ID?-->,
                        enfin toute la tribu bienveillante des <persName>créatures</persName> qui se
                        plaisent à vous faire découvrir, avec une touchante sollicitude, les choses
                        désagréables qui auraient pu vous échapper. « On » s'étonnait, « on »
                        désapprouvait même nos relations et notre amitié avec <persName
                            key="wegenerE">un être</persName> aussi nettement ambigu. Je parlai à
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> de ce que j'avais observé;
                        elle me répondit qu'elle-même le constatait depuis longtemps, bien qu'elle
                        vécût avec <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, et s'en tourmentait
                        terriblement. « Mais le plus lamentable, ajouta-t-elle, est que <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> aussi s'en rend compte et en souffre
                        au-delà de tout ce que vous pouvez imaginer. Il s'aperçoit qu'on se retourne
                        dans la rue, que l'on rit quand il entre dans un autobus, et s'entend même
                        interpeller quelquefois d'une façon outrageante. Tout le monde le prend pour
                        un inverti, alors que vous savez, comme moi, que les hommes lui sont aussi
                        indifférents que sa première pantoufle. Savez-vous ce qui est arrivé,
                        l'autre soir, à un dîner chez <persName key="bramsonK">Karen
                            Bramson</persName>? Nous étions une dizaine et comme il y avait des
                        Français, la conversation se tenait en cette langue. Brusquement, au milieu
                        du repas, <persName key="bramsonK">Karen</persName>
                        <pb style="page" n="214"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_20.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mozaïques"/>
                        <persName key="bramsonK">Bramson</persName> qui, vous le savez, dit sans
                        ménagement tout ce qui lui passe par la tête, crie à travers la table à <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> : « Vous, <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Wegener</persName>, naturellement, vous êtes pour hommes? » et <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, plein d'esprit comme d'habitude, lui
                        répond en souriant : « Non,
                        <!-- removed tag for Branson here. we didn't tag addresses like these in the editions, and we only tagged salutations in the letters when there was a key ID AM 12.3.19 -->madame,
                        vous vous trompez, je suis lesbienne. »</p>
                    <p>Je l'ai même envoyé consulter deux
                        <persName>médecins</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-23: Should this noun be given a key ID?-->,
                        mais l'un l'a pris pour un fou, l'autre pour un pervers, en sorte qu'il est
                        revenu plus déprimé qu'avant. Il commence même à éprouver des sortes de
                        malaises tous les mois et, ce qu'il y a de plus curieux, c'est que son
                        caractère et sa mentalité se féminisent encore plus que son être physique.
                        Il n'est heureux qu'en <hi rend="italics"><persName key="lili"
                                >Lily</persName></hi> et passe, ainsi constumé, des après-midi
                        entiers, lisant des poèmes, brodant, faisant de la pâtisserie ou jouant avec
                        la petite chienne. Il dit qu'alors, il oublie tout et se sent dans son
                        véritable élément. Seules, vous et moi pouvons comprendre cette situation,
                        aussi n'en ai-je parlé à personne; je m'exposerais à ce qu'on nous tourne en
                        ridicule, <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> et moi, ou à ce qu'on nous
                        prenne, comme <persName>les
                        médecins</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-23: Should this noun be given a key ID?-->
                        l'ont fait, pour des vicieux ou des détraqués. Vous devez sentir combien je
                        suis désespérée de le voir ainsi souffrir et de n'y rien pouvoir... »</p>
                    <p>Vers le printemps, l'état de <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> s'étant
                        sensiblement aggravé, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> décida de
                        passer quelques mois à <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>, espérant que
                        le changement de climat et de milieu lui ferait du bien. Ils partirent donc
                        et louèrent un petit appartement, avec atelier, <pb style="page" n="215"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_21.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> dans <placeName key="rome">la Ville
                            Eternelle</placeName><!--BC: 2019-03-23: La Ville Eternelle does not appear under the key ID "rome."-->.
                        Nous restâmes longtemps sous les
                        revoir<!--BC: 2019-03-23: This should not be "sous", but "sans", as in "we didn't see them again for a long time", it needs to be rectified.-->
                        et les nouvelles que je recevais d'eux étaient rien moins que rassurantes :
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> souffrait de plus en plus de
                        vertiges, de maux de tête et de dépression morale; <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> prévoyait un prompt retour à <placeName key="paris"
                            >Paris</placeName>, au cas où cet état de choses continuerait. Ce ne fut
                        qu'à la fin de l'automne que nous retrouvâmes nos
                        amis.
                        Ils nous invitèrent à dîner, dans un petit restaurant italien de leur
                        quartier.</p>
                    <p>Le matin, je reçus un coup de téléphone de mon ami,<persName key="warnekros"
                            >le professeur
                        W.</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-23: Le professeur W. does not appear under the key ID "warnekros"-->, — <!--BC: 2019-03-23: This is an horizontal parenthesis, how should it be marked up?-->le
                        célèbre gynécologue allemand
                        — <!--BC: 2019-03-23: This is an horizontal parenthesis, how should it be marked up?-->qui
                        se trouvait de passage à <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>. Il
                        n'était libre que ce soir-là et désirait beaucoup nous voir. Je décommandai
                        donc <persName key="wegenerE">les
                        Wegener</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-23: This is a collective noun, yet we have only the key IDs for each of the Wageners. How should this noun be marked up? Should it be given a new key ID?-->,
                        en leur expliquant le cas. Vers quatre heures, nouveau coup de téléphone du
                            <persName key="warnekros">practicien</persName>, retenu par une panne de
                        voiture, aux environs de <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>. Il était
                        navré mais ne pourrait être de retour que très tard, après sa consultation,
                        et notre soirée était dans l'eau.</p>
                    <p>— Rattrapons notre dîner avec les
                        Einar,
                        dis-je à <persName key="allatiniE">mon mari</persName>.</p>
                    <p>— Mais non, on les verra un autre jour, ils nous croiront fous de changer
                        ainsi, à chaque instant.</p>
                    <p>A<!--BC: 2019-03-23: It may be because of the font choice, but this preposition needs an accent, as in À.-->
                        ce moment, j'eus l'intuition mystérieuse que nous devions, coûte que coûte,
                        voir nos amis ce même soir. C'était comme un ordre que je recevais,
                        l'influence d'une volonté supérieure à la mienne. J'expliquai à <persName
                            key="allatiniE">mon mari</persName> que notre intimité avec <pb
                            style="page" n="216"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_22.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> les Wegener était telle qu'ils ne se
                        formaliseraient point d'un message. Je les prévins donc que nous passerions
                        quand même les prendre vers huit heures.</p>
                    <p>Quoique préparés à trouver <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> changé,
                        nous eûmes un affreux choc en le revoyant. <persName key="wegenerE">Notre
                            pauvre ami</persName> n'était plus que l'ombre de lui-même, hâve, le
                        teint terreux, les yeux enfoncés dans les orbites, entourés de grands
                        cercles bistres, avec une expression désespérée que je n'oublierai jamais.
                        Il fit d'héroïques efforts pour paraître gai pendant le repas, mais, dans
                        son regard, persistait cet air de bête martyrisée que je ne pouvais
                        <!--BC: 2019-03-23: Here, I think we should have the negative particle "pas".-->supporter.
                        N'y tenant plus, je pris <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> à part et
                        lui confiai ma pénible impression.</p>
                    <p>— J'allais vous en parler moi-même, me répondit-elle. J'en suis malade!
                        Labouré de souffrances atroces et presque continuelles, <persName
                            key="wegenerE">le pauvre être</persName> ne dort plus. Il sent ses
                        forces décliner chaque jour et si on ne peut
                        <!--BC: 2019-03-23: Here, I think we should have the negative particle "pas".-->faire
                        quelque chose pour le soulager, je crains le pire, car il n'en peut plus!
                        Ses organes masculins s'atrophient de plus en plus, sa poitrine se
                        développe, il endure des tortures chaque mois et je
                        n'ose<!--BC: 2019-03-23: Here, I think we should have the negative particle "pas".-->
                        m'adresser aux
                        <persName>médecins</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-23: Should this noun be given a key ID?-->
                        d'ici, après notre première expérience.</p>
                    <p>A<!--BC: 2019-03-23: The preposition should have an accent, as in À.--> ce
                        moment, j'eus la vision distincte de la longue silhouette de mon ami,
                            <persName key="warnekros">le professeur W.</persName> Son passage à
                            <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> m'apparut, non point comme une
                        coïncidence, mais comme le doigt de la destinée. Saisie d'une éloquence qui
                        ne m'était pas habituelle, j'exposai mon plan à <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> : téléphoner <pb style="page" n="217"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_23.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> le lendemain matin au <persName
                            key="warnekros">grand spécialiste</persName>, lui expliquer le cas en
                        quelques mots, et obtenir un rendez-vous pour <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Bé</persName>. Réconfortée et remplie d'espoir, <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> me promit de faire de son mieux auprès
                        de <persName key="wegenerE">son mari</persName>, pour me l'envoyer le
                        lendemain matin. Elle eut cependant le plus grand mal à le décider : au
                        dernier moment, il voulait se dérober, ayant perdu confiance en toutes
                        choses.</p>
                    <p>Les quelques détails que je donnai, par téléphone, au <persName
                            key="warnekros">professeur W.</persName> suffirent à éveiller son
                        intérêt; il me fixa aussitôt un rendez-vous. <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Einar</persName> arriva chez moi bien à l'avance; il était extrêmement
                        agité et je parvins difficilement à le calmer, à le convaincre que tout
                        s'arrangerait, dès qu'il serait entre les mains de <persName key="warnekros"
                            >l'admirable spécialiste</persName>.</p>
                    <p>— Je ne voulais pas vous le dire devant <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName>, me dit-il, mais je suis décidé à me suicider si je ne
                        puis devenir ce que je suis réellement, une femme. Songez, ma chère
                            <persName key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName>, que je ne suis plus qu'une
                        loque humaine, un déchet inutile. Malade physiquement et moralement
                        — <!--BC: 2019-03-25: How should a horizontal parenthesis be marked up?-->je
                        ne puis même plus tenir un pinceau, ni faire la moindre chose pour aider <persName
                            key="wegenerG"
                        >Gerda</persName> — <!--BC: 2019-03-25: How should a horizontal parenthesis be marked up?-->je
                        ne resterai jamais à sa charge. Elle a été admirable pour moi, personne ne
                        peut savoir ou comprendre à quel point... sauf vous peut-être?... Je vous ai
                        promis, à toutes deux, de consulter <persName key="warnekros">ce grand
                            médecin</persName>. Ce sera ma dernière tentative; s'il ne peut rien, je
                        suis décidé à disparaître... ce sera un soulagement pour moi... et aussi
                        pour ma chère <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>... après le premier
                        chagrin passé. Je n'entraverai plus sa <pb style="page" n="218"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_24.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> vie, comme je le fais depuis
                        longtemps. Dans mon cas, vivre serait une lâcheté. Regardez où j'en
                        suis!...</p>
                    <p>Ce disant, il écarta sa chemise et découvrit les plus beaux seins de femme
                        que j'aie jamais vus. J'en fus saisie et « réalisai » vraiment à cet instant
                        tout ce qu'il venait de me dire.</p>
                    <p>Quand nous arrivâmes chez mon ami, <persName key="warnekros">le professeur
                            W.</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-24: A comma is needed here.-->ce fut moi
                        qui servit d'interprète. Je dus lui expliquer, en allemand, la progression
                        de la métamorphose d'<persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> depuis
                        l'origine. J'attendis dans une pièce voisine, pendant qu'il l'examinait. Il
                        revint un quart d'heure plus tard, en proie à une agitation qui m'étonna
                        chez <persName key="warnekros">un homme</persName> que je n'avais jamais vu
                        qu'impassible.</p>
                    <p>— Savez-vous, <persName key="allatiniH">chère amie</persName>, que vous m'avez
                        amené un cas unique dans l'histoire de la science médicale, un cas attendu
                        pendant toute une existence sans jamais le rencontrer : <persName
                            key="wegenerE">votre ami</persName> est le seul <hi rend="italics"
                            >véritable</hi> hermaphrodite qui existe ou ait existé, car il a été
                        vraiment <persName>homme</persName>, un <persName>homme</persName> chétif,
                        débile, atrophié, mais un homme quand même, dans toute l'acception du terme.
                        En général, les autres êtres, auxquels on donne ce nom, ne sont pas de réels
                            <persName>hermaphrodites</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-24: A comma is needed here.--> mais
                        seulement des hommes affligés d'une hernie inguinale, qui retient leurs
                        organes à l'intérieur du corps, en sorte qu'un peut les prendre pour des
                        femmes. A<!--BC: 2019-03-24: This preposition should be written as À.--> la
                        suite d'un choc physique, d'un accident ou de tout autre phénomène de ce
                        genre, le sexe suspendu descend brusquement et occupe sa <pb style="page"
                            n="219" facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_25.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> place normale : <persName>la
                            soi-disant femme</persName> devient alors <persName>un homme</persName>,
                        mais, en réalité, elle l'a toujours été sans qu'on puisse le soupçonner,
                        tandis que <persName key="wegenerE">Wegener</persName>, lui, a été d'abord
                            <persName>un homme</persName> et évolue actuellement vers le sexe
                        féminin, ce qui est tout différent des cas d'hermaphrodisme ordinaires. Il
                        représente donc le premier type parfait de <persName>l'androgyne</persName>.
                        Actuellement, il a en lui les deux sexes et c'est le combat qui se livre
                        entre eux qui martyrise ainsi ce pauvre être. Si l'on n'intervient pas, il
                        succombera sous peu, que ce soit par la violence du conflit ou par sa propre
                        main, car il est incapable de supporter longtemps ses atroces souffrances.
                        Je ne vois qu'une issue : le débarrasser de ce qui reste de son premier sexe,
                        et greffer aux ovaires
                        — <!--BC: 2019-03-24: This is a horizontal parenthesis. How should it be marked up?-->qu'il
                        possède certainement
                        — <!--BC: 2019-03-24: This is a horizontal parenthesis. How should it be marked up?-->des
                        ovaires neufs, en bon état, puis, plus tard, quand il sera capable de le
                        supporter, faire une troisième et dernière opération, qui ouvrira une voie
                        normale aux fonctions génitales. Je devine aisément les assiduités
                        masculines dont votre ami a dû être harcelé, car <persName>les
                            hermaphrodites</persName> ont une puissance de séduction sexuelle aiguë
                        sur <persName>les hommes</persName>, à leur insu. Tout ceci vous fera
                        comprendre une chose, qu'on ignore en général et qui cause tant d'injustices
                        et de calomnies dans notre impitoyable société : beaucoup
                            d'<persName>invertis</persName> sont des êtres qui possèdent un sexe
                        masculin dans lequel se trouvent des ovaires, à la place des testicules. Il
                        en est de même pour beaucoup de <persName>lesbiennes</persName>, qui ont des
                        testicules à la place où devraient se trouver <pb style="page" n="220"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_26.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> leurs ovaires. Ces malheureux
                        souffrent donc injustement du mépris et du dégoût publics, alors que leurs
                        penchants sont
                        – <!--BC: 2019-03-24: This is a horizontal parenthesis. How should it be marked up?-->somme
                        toute
                        – <!--BC: 2019-03-24: This is a horizontal parenthesis. How should it be marked up?-->normaux
                        et non vicieux et pervers, comme on se plaît à le leur faire sentir.</p>
                    <p>Je prescrirai d'abord à <persName key="wegenerE">votre ami</persName> un
                        traitement, pour le préparer à surmonter l'épreuve qui l'attend. Vers le
                        début de mars, je le préviendrai et il faudra qu'il vienne immédiatement à
                            <placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName> où mon collègue, <persName
                            key="gohrbandtE">le professeur G.</persName>, pratiquera la première
                        opération. Dès qu'il en sera remis, il viendra
                        – <!--BC: 2019-03-24: This is a horizontal parenthesis. How should it be marked up?-->
                        ou plutôt <hi rend="italics">elle</hi> viendra
                        – <!--BC: 2019-03-24: This is a horizontal parenthesis. How should it be marked up?-->à
                        la <placeName key="womensClinic">Frauenklinik</placeName> de <placeName
                            key="dresden">Dresde</placeName>, où je ferai la deuxième intervention,
                        par laquelle s'affirmera son véritable sexe. Qu'il ait donc bon courage, en
                        attendant; je suis d'ailleurs certain qu'il l'aura, car on ne peut que
                        s'incliner devant sa vaillance. Puis, s'adressant à <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Einar</persName> lui-même : « Au revoir donc, cher monsieur, en attendant
                        de pouvoir vous dire : Bonjour, chère mademoiselle! »</p>
                    <p>Ce fut un <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> transfiguré que je
                        ramenai à <persName key="wegenerG">sa femme</persName>! Je n'ai jamais vu
                        pareil changement en si peu de temps. Le visage de <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >mon ami</persName> avait passé de la plus déchirante angoisse à la plus
                        parfaite sérénité, comme ces cieux qui, assombris par un orage,
                        s'éclaircissent tout à coup, illuminés d'une rayonnante clarté.</p>
                    <p>Pendant les deux mois qui suivirent, le pauvre <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Bé</persName>, comme touché par la baguette d'un magicien, reprenait
                        des forces morales et physiques; <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>
                        me redisait souvent sa joie et son soulagement.</p>
                    <pb style="page" n="221"
                        facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_27.jpg"/>
                    <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/>
                    <p>Ce fut par un beau matin de mars que, seules toutes deux, selon son désir,
                        nous l'accompagnâmes à <placeName>la gare du
                        Nord</placeName><!--BC: 2019-03-24: I have not found a placeName,nor a key ID for "la gare du Nord."-->.
                        Il s'installa dans son compartiment et, galant comme toujours, céda son coin
                        réservé à <persName>une jeune
                        femme</persName><!--Should this character be given a key ID?-->, qui l'en
                        remercia d'un sourire charmant. Son « Merci, monsieur » nous fit rire, nous
                        savions que <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> portait pour la dernière
                        fois son costume masculin, ce dont il n'avait cessé de se réjouir pendant le
                        trajet en taxi. <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> pensait avoir le
                        temps de terminer une commande très importante et de rejoindre <persName
                            key="wegenerE">son mari</persName> avant l'intervention, mais elle dut
                        partir précipitamment, dans la même semaine, avertie par dépêche que « tout
                        s'était admirablement passé ».
                        A<!--BC: 2019-03-24: This preposition should be written as "À".--> peine
                        arrivée à <placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName>, <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, examiné par <persName key="hirschfeld"
                            >Marcus Hirschfeld</persName> et quelques autres
                        somnités<!--BC: 2019-03-24: This is a misspelling. The correct form is "sommités."--> berlinoises,
                        avait subi, de la main du <persName key="gohrbandtE">professeur
                            G.</persName>, l'ablation qui devait faire de lui une <persName
                            key="lili">Lily</persName> définitive.</p>
                    <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> emportait du linge de femme, une
                        robe de chambre rose et tout un arsenal de fards et de parfums : de quoi
                        réjouir <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> et lui donner son véritable
                        aspect féminin.</p>
                    <p>En arrivant à <placeName key="gebhardSanatorium">la clinique</placeName>
                        <persName key="wegenerG">la voyageuse</persName> fut tout d'abord frappée du
                        changement de voix de <persName key="wegenerE">son
                        ex-mari</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-24: I assume that, as an "ex", Einar Wegener is referenced here.-->.
                        L'opération avait suffi pour en transformer le timbre et ce fut un joli
                        soprano qui l'accueillit. <persName key="lili"
                        >L'opérée</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-24: The feminine form of the noun and of the following adjectives makes clear that Lily is referenced here.-->reposait
                        pâle, mais radieuse, sur ses oreillers, après avoir supporté vaillamment les
                        souffrances qui l'avaient délivrée
                        – <!--BC: 2019-03-24: How should I mark up this horizantal parenthesis?-->
                        enfin!
                        –<!--BC: 2019-03-24: How should I mark up this horizantal parenthesis?-->de
                        sa chrysalide tant détestée. Elle était choyée, gâtée, <pb style="page"
                            n="222" facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_28.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/> entourée de fleurs, de prévenances.
                        Les quelques <persName>amis
                        scandinaves</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-24: Should these get a persName and a key ID?-->,qui
                        se trouvaient à <placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName>, venaient la voir
                        quotidiennement. Elle était l'idole de <placeName key="gebhardSanatorium">la
                            clinique</placeName>, on n'y parlait que d'elle, de son courage, de sa
                        douceur et de son aventure extraordinaire.</p>
                    <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> eut vite fait de farder <persName
                            key="lili">sa chère
                        fille</persName>,<!--BC: 2019-03-24: There shouldn't be a comma before a parenthesis.-->(car
                        c'est ainsi qu'elle la considérait désormais), de la coiffer, de lui passer
                        la chemise de nuit et la matinée de soie rose que j'avais depuis longtemps
                        promises à <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> pour <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> et qu'elle lui apportait de ma part. On juge de la
                        stupéfaction du <persName key="gohrbandtE">professeur G.</persName> en
                        pénétrant dans la chambre, ce soir même, lorsqu'il aperçut, à la place de
                            <!-- in the editions, where language is gender neutral, we don't tag "the patient" as either Lili or Einar AM 12.3.19 --><persName
                            key="lili">son
                        malade</persName><!--BC: 2019-03-24: I assume that Lili is referenced here.-->,
                            <persName key="lili">une ravissante demoiselle</persName> toute
                        pomponnée, parfumée et frisée pour le recevoir.</p>
                    <p>Les semaines qui suivirent furent pour la pauvre <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> un rêve enchanteur : pour sa première sortie, <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> lui fit la surprise d'un beau manteau de
                        fourrure et l'emmena ensuite dans les magasins, choisir tout ce qui manquait
                        encore à son trousseau.</p>
                    <p>Comme il était convenu, j'eus les honneurs de la première lettre de <persName
                            key="lili">Lily</persName>. L'écriture en était tellement différente que
                        j'eus peine à croire, en la décachetant, qu'elle était écrite de sa main : à
                        la place des épais jambages d'<persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>,
                        couraient sur le papier des traits élégants et légers, mais ce qui me
                        surprit plus que tout, ce fut le style de <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName>, virginal, sensible, délicat, un véritable style de
                        jeune fille, et de jeune fille sentimentale : « <placeName key="berlin"
                            >Berlin</placeName>. 10 mars 1930.<!--BC: 2019-03-24: The words that follow the quote mark are italicized, except the digits. How should they be marked up?--><!--BC: 2019-03-24: How do I mark up the end of a paragraph that also happens to be the heading of the following letter?-->
                        <pb style="page" n="223"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_29.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" rend="Mosaïques"/>
                        <hi rend="italics">Chère et grande <persName key="allatiniH"
                            >amie</persName>. Je suis si ravie de votre lettre et j'embrasse votre
                            nom chéri. Je suis si heureuse mais tellement fatiguée qu'il m'est
                            impossible d'écrire. L'opération a duré une heure et j'ai hurlé pendant
                            des heures après (avec une voix claire comme celle d'<persName
                                key="schumannE">Elisabeth Schumann</persName>, selon l'avis de
                                <persName key="gohrbandtE">mon superbe chirurgien</persName>).
                                <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> a vécu et <persName
                                key="lili">Lily</persName> est bientôt une fille avec son passeport
                            en règle. Le printemps chante dans mon cœur et je pleure de bonheur et
                            je suis sans peur devant toutes les douleurs qui m'attendent. Je vous
                            adore. <persName key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName></hi>.<!--BC: 2019-03-24: I think that "Lily" is just the signature, not the beginning of a new line. If so, how should it be marked up?--></p>
                    <!--BC: 2019-03-24: There is a free line between these two paragraphs. How should it be marked up?-->
                    <!-- I removed the paragraph element for the free line between these two paragraphs so the paragraph numbers line up across the French and English translation DB 4.14.2020-->
                    <p>P. S. — <hi rend="italics"><persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> a fêté
                            l'enterrement de sa vie de garçon. »</hi></p>
                    <!--BC: 2019-03-24: There is a free line between these two paragraphs. How should it be marked up?-->
                    <p>Et encore, le 15 mars : « <hi rend="italics">Tout le monde me gâte ici et
                            m'appelle <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>. Ils me font beaucoup de
                            compliments surtout pour mes jambes. Ça me va très bien. Je ne serai
                            certainement jamais une femme de tête. Ne trouvez-vous pas, chère
                                <persName key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName>, que je dois avoir des
                            ongles roses, et pas rouges, pour la grande opération de <placeName
                                key="dresden">Dresde</placeName>? Maintenant je ne me retiens plus
                            de montrer ma joie quand je me sens trop heureuse. <persName
                                key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> s'estompe de plus en plus et <persName
                                key="warnekros">le professeur W.</persName> va lui porter le coup de
                            grâce.</hi> »</p>
                    <!--BC: 2019-03-24: There is a free line between these two paragraphs. How should it be marked up?-->
                    <!--I removed the paragraph element for the free line between these two paragraphs so the paragraph numbers line up across the French and English translation DB 4.14.2020-->
                    <p>Quelques semaines plus tard, deux élégantes <persName>jeunes
                            femmes</persName><!--These two "young women" are Gerda and Lili. How should this plural noun be marked up? Should it be given a key ID?--> débarquaient
                        à la <placeName key="womensClinic">Frauenklinik</placeName> de <placeName
                            key="dresden">Dresde</placeName> et se présentaient devant <persName
                            key="warnekros">le professeur W.</persName>, <pb style="page" n="224"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_30.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/> qui, ne connaissant pas encore <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> et ayant quitté un <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> cadavérique et en veston, n'arrivait pas à
                        identifier les séduisantes créatures qui se tenaient devant lui, en
                        riant.</p>
                    <p><placeName key="womensClinic">La <hi rend="italics"
                            >Frauenklinik</hi></placeName> est une véritable ville contenant cinq
                        cents lits et tous les perfectionnements modernes. <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> fut installée dans la plus belle chambre et, là
                        <!-- is the accent over the "a" supposed to be there? --> encore, elle
                        devint le point culminant de l'intérêt général. La seconde opération fut
                        longue et grave. Elle en sortit très faible, mais très heureuse, car son
                        cœur et sa nouvelle âme de jeune fille s'étaient donnés à son sauveur, à
                        celui qui l'avait libérée d'une existence de martyr, pour lui ouvrir les
                        portes dorées de la vie et de l'espérance.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italics"><placeName key="dresden">Dresde</placeName>, 7 avril</hi>
                        1930 : <hi rend="italics"> « Toute ma vie ne suffira pas pour vous remercier
                            de m'avoir envoyée chez cet homme extraordinaire, ce génie bienfaisant
                            qui m'a donné une nouvelle vie. J'adore mon cher <persName
                                key="warnekros">professeur W.</persName> ... je l'aime, mais avec un
                            mélange de respect, comme s'il était plutôt un dieu tout-puissant. Chère
                                <persName key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName>, vous comprenez votre
                            petite <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> quand je vous dis que je n'ai
                            jamais vu ses yeux, parce que je n'ai jamais osé le regarder. Je
                            voudrais souvent lui dire quelque chose, mais je n'arrive jamais plus
                            loin que de sourire bêtèment et dire : « Oui, maître ». Je voudrais qu'il
                            soit un pacha ou sultan pour être son esclave. <placeName
                                key="womensClinic">Frauenklinik</placeName> est un paradis
                            terrestre!
                            <!-- kk: 3/27/2019: the "j" isn't capitalized, but i believe it should be -->
                            j'aime même mes souffrances ici. Voilà où j'en » <pb style="page" n="225"
                                facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_31.jpg"/>
                            <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/> suis! J'ai une nouvelle paire
                            d'ovaires qui se comportent comme des petits fauves dans mon ventre
                            endolori. Ma chambre est la seule qui ait une grande glace, quand
                        </hi>Il <hi rend="italics">me donnera le droit de me lever, je pourrai me
                            mettre devant. <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> veut faire
                        </hi> Son <hi rend="italics"> portrait. Quel est donc ce pouvoir magique qui
                            influence toutes celles qui l'approchent. Il y a une charmante jeune
                            fille qui vient nettoyer dans ma chambre, qui m'a dit : « Je nettoie
                            comme pour sauver ma vie, si jamais </hi> Il <hi rend="italics"> voyait
                            un grain de poussière et s'il me faisait un reproche, j'en mourrais! »
                                <persName key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName>, <persName
                                key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName> comme c'est fantastique, d'une vie
                            qui s'en allait vers la terre et la fin, comme une récompense, il a créé
                            une nouvelle vie débordante d'espérance, d'amour et de printemps. C'est
                            l'œuvre d'un dieu! Quel déchirement, le jour où je devrai quitter cette
                            clinique, dans sa forêt de bouleaux blancs. J'ai rêvé qu'</hi> Il <hi
                            rend="italics">continuerait de m'opérer jusqu'au moment où il ne
                            </hi>Lui<hi rend="italics"> resterait que mon cœur tremblant entre
                            </hi>Ses<hi rend="italics"> mains si douces et fines. <persName
                                key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName>, vous avez un cœur d'or que vous
                            dépensez sans cesse pour le bonheur des autres. J'espère que vous ne
                            regretterez jamais tout ce que vous avez fait pour votre petite
                                <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>. Moi qui ai un peu peur de mes
                            premiers pas dans la vie, je me sens protégée par votre amitié.
                        »</hi></p>
                    <p>De son côté, <persName key="warnekros">le célèbre chirurgien</persName> se
                        montrait touché par la douceur et le courage de sa petite malade et lui
                        témoignait des sentiments quasi-paternels,<pb style="page" n="226"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_32.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/> auxquels venait s'ajouter l'intérêt
                        professionnel pour ce cas passionnant entre tous. <persName key="warnekros"
                            >Le professeur W.</persName> avait de charmants égards pour <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>, dont il appréciait la conduite admirable
                        dans une situation aussi particulière. Il lui avait accordé le privilège de
                        monter chez lui se reposer, ou peindre, dans son confortable living-room. En
                        gage de reconnaissance pour tout ce qu'il avait fait, elle entreprit son
                        portrait, en blouse blanche de chirurgien. Les infirmières et les servantes
                        étaient aux petits soins pour l'opérée, afin de plaire au maître, qu'elles
                        entouraient toutes d'une adoration craintive, mêlée de respect. Lui, se
                        mouvait dans ces ondes d'amour et d'admiration féminine, comme un sultan
                        dans son sérail; la dévotion de tout ce personnel était devenue une sorte
                        d'extase religieuse.</p>
                    <p>Un après-midi, comme <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> faisait la sieste,
                        étendue sur une chaise-longue, dans le parc de la clinique, une vieille dame
                        s'approcha d'elle et engagea la conversation : « Comment allez-vous
                        maintenant, petite madame? Vous me semblez avoir meilleure mine et vous serez
                        bientôt tout à fait remise de votre accouchement. Ma fille, elle, commence à
                        se lever. Et votre bébé, est-ce un garçon ou une fille? » </p>
                    <p>– L'un et l'autre, répondit <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> sans
                        sourciller, le Bon Dieu m'a envoyé des jumeaux. »</p>
                    <p><persName key="lili">Lily</persName> quitta la clinique et son cher seigneur
                        avec regret et alla finir de se remettre dans les montagnes de la <placeName
                            key="saxony">Saxe</placeName>, en compagnie de <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName>. </p>
                    <pb style="page" n="227"
                        facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_33.jpg"/>
                    <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/>
                    <p>« Il <hi rend="italics"> nous a envoyées, pour quelques jours, dans
                                <placeName key="erzgebirge">l'Erzgebirge</placeName></hi>, <hi rend="italics">entre
                                <placeName key="saxony">la Saxe</placeName> et <placeName
                                key="bohemia">la Bohême</placeName>, mais il fait si froid ici que
                            nous allons quitter ces lieux où nous grelottons, dans nos petites robes
                            d'été.</hi> »</p>
                    <p>Elles revinrent donc prendre congé du <persName key="warnekros"
                            >professeur</persName> et partirent pour <placeName key="copenhagen"
                            >Copenhague</placeName>, y faire annuler leur mariage et mettre en règle
                        les papiers de <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>. Celle-ci obtint du
                            <persName key="king">roi de <placeName key="denmark"
                                >Danemark</placeName></persName> la transformation de son nom de
                        famille en celui d'<hi rend="italics">Elbe</hi>, qu'elle avait choisi
                        d'après le fleuve qui arrose <placeName key="dresden">Dresde</placeName>,
                        témoin de sa renaissance. <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> fit un long
                        séjour dans sa famille, tremblant quand elle sortait, craignant d'être
                        reconnue, redoutant aussi le moment où sa métamorphose serait signalée, la
                        rendant ainsi la proie des journalistes, qui feraient d'elle un phénomène
                        national. Elle ne voulait plus toucher une palette, ni quoi que ce fut
                        pouvant lui rappeler <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>. Elle passait
                        ses journées à coudre, à se regarder dans la glace, à broder, à se faire les
                        ongles. Elle était devenue pudique à l'excès — alors que <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> se plaisait à raconter les anecdotes les
                        plus grivoises — elle rougissait pour un rien et, contrairement à sa
                        première incarnation (<persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> était un
                        parfait athée), était devenue d'une piété édifiante, d'un mysticisme
                        intense. Son second frère, <persName key="wegenerHo">Holger</persName>, et
                        sa belle-sœur, avec lesquels <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> s'était
                        toujours bien entendu, furent envers <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>
                        d'une bonté touchante et compréhensive et l'accueillirent de tout leur cœur.
                        Exténuée par la tension morale de ces derniers mois et sachant sa petite
                            <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> en <pb style="page" n="228"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_34.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/> bonnes mains, <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> céda aux instances
                        <!--BC: 2019-04-10: I think this is a text error, it makes more sense to use "insistances".-->
                        de sa <persName key="gottliebMrs">mère</persName>, qui voulait l'emmener se reposer en <placeName key="italy"
                            >Italie</placeName>, et partit avec elle pour <placeName key="rome"
                            >Rome</placeName>. Elles descendirent dans une pension de famille tenue
                        par une Danoise, qu'elles connaissaient. <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> eut là toutes les peinnes
                        <!--BC: 2019-04-10: This is a text error: the correct form of the noun is "peines".-->du
                        monde à se distraire et à sortir avec ses amis italiens, car, depuis
                        l'annulation du mariage,
                            <!-- not sure whether the superscript will render within the persName AM 12.3.19 --><persName
                            key="gottliebMrs">M<hi rend="super">me</hi> Gottlieb</persName>, se
                        croyant revenue au temps où sa fille était adolescente, ne lui laissait
                        aucune liberté et veillait sur elle comme un dragon. La vieille dame,
                        désirant connaître <placeName key="pompeii">Pompéi</placeName>, décida d'y
                        aller passer, avec sa fille, une huitaine de jours. Constamment sous la
                        tutelle maternelle, la jeune femme cherchait le moyen de s'en affranchir,
                        pour pouvoir, enfin, se détendre. Le matin du retour, <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>, désemparée, se promenait dans le vieux
                            <placeName key="naples"
                        >Naples</placeName><!-- I feel like we should choice markup this as Napoli AM 12.3.19 -->,
                        quand elle aperçut une petite église qui l'attirait mystérieusement. Elle y
                        entra et, s'approchant de l'autel de la Vierge, elle la supplia de lui venir
                        en aide, de la protéger et de guider sa vie vers un être loyal et bon, qui
                        l'aimerait sincèrement et avec lequel elle pourrait partager le reste de son
                        existence. Elle sortit soulagée et, le soir, dans le train qui les ramenait
                        à <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>, elle prit la résolution de laisser
                        sa mère retourner seule au <placeName key="denmark">Danemark</placeName> et
                        de prolonger son séjour en <placeName key="italy">Italie</placeName>. A la
                        pension de famille, un volumineux courrier l'attendait. Comme elle se
                        dirigeait vers le salon de l'hôtel pour le dépouiller, une silhouette
                        masculine se leva pour la saluer. Elle reconnut un officier aviateur, qui lui
                        avait été présenté, avant son <pb style="page" n="229"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_35.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/> voyage à <placeName key="naples"
                            >Naples</placeName><!-- again, choice markup for Napoli? AM 12.3.19 -->.
                        « Permettez-moi de déposer mes hommages à vos pieds, madame, et de vous
                        exprimer ma joie de votre retour. Je craignais que vous ayez quitté
                        définitivement <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>, et cette maison avait
                        perdu son charme pendant votre absence. » <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> répondit quelques mots et accepta une cigarette. Après
                        cette première conversation, le capitaine <persName key="portaF"
                            >Porta</persName> guettait chaque soir le retour de la jeune femme, et
                        leur sympathie mutuelle s'accentuait de plus en plus. Le jour du départ de
                            <!-- not sure whether the superscript will render within the persName AM 12.3.19 --><persName
                            key="gottliebMrs">M<hi rend="super">me</hi> Gottlieb</persName>,
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> eut la surprise de trouver
                        l'officier l'attendant à la sortie de la gare. « Je voulais m'assurer que
                        vous me resteriez », lui dit-il d'une voix émue. Gagnée par la flamme de ce
                        beau et sympathique garçon, elle consentit à l'écouter. Ils découvrirent
                        qu'ils s'entendaient à merveille, avaient les mêmes goûts et, quand
                            <persName key="portaF">Fernando Porta</persName> lui demandaa de devenir
                        sa femme, elle accepta de tout son ceur, après lui avoir raconté son passé
                        et l'aventure, si fantastique, qui l'avait assombri. « Vous m'êtes maintenant
                        doublement chère, lui répondit-il, et une admiration pleine de respect se
                        mêle à ma tendresse; <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> sera notre fille.
                        Je comprends que vous ne veuillez pas l'abandonner. Elle aura toujours sa
                        chambre chez nous, sa place à notre foyer. »</p>
                    <p>Quand <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> nous apprit ses fiançailles,
                        j'en éprouvai une grande joie. Elle recevait enfin la récompense qu'elle
                        avait si bien méritée, le bonheur que je lui avais toujours souhaité.
                        Pendant un court voyage à <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>, mon mari
                        eut l'occasion de faire la connaissance de « <persName key="portaF"
                            >Nando</persName> » et le trouva des <pb style="page" n="230"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_36.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/> plus charmants
                        <!--BC: 2019-04-10: I don't know what allatiniH wants to say here, but this is a lack of agreement between the number of the pronoun, singular, and that of its qualifiers, which is plural. Please check with the translator and see what does she think of this.-->
                        Il appartenait à l'une de meilleures familles livournaises et venait d'être
                        nommé vice-consul à <placeName key="marrakech">Marrakech</placeName>. Il s'y
                        rendit, au début de février, pour préparer l'installation tandis que
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> retournait à <placeName
                            key="copenhagen">Copenhague</placeName> pour régler ses affaires,
                        organiser son exposition de peinture et passer quelques semaines avec
                            <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>. Elle voulut aussi, au cours de ce
                        séjour, se convertir à la religion catholique, pour partager la foi de son
                        futur mari. Elle le voulait surtout, par reconnaissance envers la Vierge,
                        qui avait exaucé sa prière. </p>
                    <p>A son arrivée, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> fut touchée jusqu'au
                        fond du cœur par la joie débordante avec laquelle <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> l'accueillit et accueillit aussi sa nouvelle félicité.
                        Le temps passa vite et délicieusement, tandis que <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> échafaudait mille projets d'avenir, que <persName
                            key="lili">Lily</persName> écoutait avec un mélancolique ravissement : 
                        au début d'avril, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> rejoindrait son
                        <persName key="portaF">fiancé</persName> à <placeName key="marrakech">Marrakech</placeName>, où ils se
                        marieraient aussitôt; dès les premiers jours de juin, <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> partirait pour <placeName key="paris"
                        >Paris</placeName>; elle passerait deux semaines chez nous, avant de
                        s'embarquer pour le <placeName key="morocco">Maroc</placeName>, où l'heureux
                        couple l'attendrait. Le temps s'écoula rapidement et bientôt, vint le moment
                        où un groupe d'amis accompagna <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> à
                        la gare. Elle était radieuse, malgré une ombre de regret, à la pensée de
                        laisser derrière elle la pauvre <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>, mais
                        ce n'était qu'une ombre, en effet, car ne devait-elle pas la rejoindre, et
                        deux mois sont si vite passés, surtout quand on est heureux. Les deux femmes
                        s'embrassèrent une dernière fois : « A bientôt, petite <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName>, à bientôt, à <pb style="page" n="231"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_37.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/>
                        <placeName key="marrakech">Marrakech</placeName> » « A bientôt, chère
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>, à toujours! »</p>
                    <p>Un coup de sifflet, le train s'ébranle, les mouchoirs s'agitent; longtemps,
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> suit des yeux la silhouette
                        élancée de sa fille bien-aimée et, au moment où le train décrit une courbe
                        qui la dérobe à sa vue, elle éprouve une angoisse soudaine et déchirante, un
                        serrement de cœur, comme si elle voyait <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>
                        pour la dernière fois!...</p>
                    <p>Avril, mai, juin... Je commençai à préparer l'arrivée de <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName>. J'annonçai, avec ménagement, à ma petite fille, la
                        mort de son ami <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>, qu'elle aimait
                        tendrement. Je séchai ses larmes et tâchai de la calmer en lui annonçant que
                        la sœur d'<persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName>, allait venir chez nous pour quelques jours et qu'elle
                        ressemblait tant à son pauvre frère, qu'elle le remplacerait sûrement dans
                        son affection, puis, j'écrivis à <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> de ne
                        pas manquer de se mettre en grand deuil pour son arrivée.</p>
                    <p>Ayant ainsi enterré définitivement le pauvre <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Bé</persName>, je préparai la chambre de <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName>. Pour flatter sa coquetterie, je fis mettre au lit des
                        draps brodés, au mur une grande glace, puis, j'éparpillai mille petits
                        riens : bonbons, colliers, parfums, rubans, destinés à lui faire plaisir. Je
                        commandai ses fleurs préférées. </p>
                    <p>La veille du jour où elle devait arriver,
                        quel<!--BC: 2019-04-10: I am not sure, but the translator can verify if "quels" is not a better fit in the context.-->
                        ne furent pas notre étonnement et notre déception en recevant la lettre
                        suivante : « <hi rend="italics">Ma très chère <persName key="allatiniH"
                                >Hélène</persName>, je suis partie de <placeName key="copenhagen"
                                >Copenhague</placeName> mercredi matin pour <placeName key="paris"
                                >Paris</placeName>. De <placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName>,
                            le soir, j'ai téléphoné à <pb style="page" n="232"
                                facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_38.jpg"/>
                            <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/>
                            <persName key="warnekros">mon
                            Idole</persName><!-- bumped "mon" to the next page to keep "mon Idole" together and tag AM 12.3.19 -->,
                            à <placeName key="dresden">Dresde</placeName>. Puis je suis venue jeudi
                            soir à <placeName key="womensClinic">Frauenklinik</placeName>. Une heure
                            après, il avait décidé de m'opérer à nouveau. Je suis si fatiguée du
                            traitement préparatoire que je subis, que je peux à peine écrire.
                            Peut-être la surprise et un petit peu de peur y sont pour quelque chose,
                            — car je sais que c'est très sérieux cette fois. Quand je dis que j'ai
                            peur, c'est plutôt pour</hi> lui, <hi rend="italics">qui est superbe de
                            courage et qui n'épargne rien pour me rendre heureuse. Ainsi, je pourrai
                            rester quelques mois auprès de</hi> lui <hi rend="italics"> et ça vaut
                            toutes les douleurs du monde! Je vous prie donc de me pardonner si je ne
                            viens pas tout de suite à <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> mais,
                            devant</hi> lui, <hi rend="italics"> j'oublie tout. J'étais au
                                <placeName key="denmark">Danemark</placeName>, devenue une personne
                            pas trop timide et, pendant quelques instants, j'ai pu</hi> lui<hi
                            rend="italics"> parler librement; mais ça n'a pas duré, et il ne reste
                                de moi qu'une petite chose humble devant ce grand maître adoré. Je suis
                            déjà couchée et quoiqu'il ne me l'ait pas dit, je sais que l'opération
                            sera pour demain matin et qu'elle sera très compliquée. Même la mort me
                            paraît douce ici où on garde toujours mon cœur, mais je comprends que la
                            mort serait comme une trahison envers</hi> lui. <hi rend="italics">
                            Donc, voilà un petit retard légal de mon arivée à <placeName key="paris"
                                >Paris</placeName> chez vous, chère amie mais, quand je viendrai, je
                            serai à marier et qui sait si un beau jour je n'aurai pas aussi des
                            enfants?</hi> »</p>
                    <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> reçut une lettre dans le même
                        esprit et non seulement elle en conçut une violente déception, mais encore,
                        elle fut saisie, en la lisant, d'une légitime fureur. N'avait-elle pas
                        recommandé mille <pb style="page" n="233"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_39.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/> fois à <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName>, lors de son séjour à <placeName key="copenhagen"
                            >Copenhague</placeName>, de prendre au moins une année de repos, avant
                        de se faire opérer à nouveau! Elle le lui avait fait jurer, redoutant que
                        l'attraction que <persName key="warnekros">le professeur W.</persName>
                        exerçait sur la malade, n'incitât celle-ci à désirer l'intervention
                        chirurgicale, pour se retrouver plus tôt dans son sillage adoré. Avec cela,
                        impossible d'agir, même par dépêche, car, d'après la date, <persName
                            key="lili">Lily</persName> devait être sur la table d'opération au
                        moment où <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> lisait la lettre. En
                        proie à un véritable désespoir, à la rage qu'on éprouve devant un fait
                        accompli, elle ouvrit la porte de la chambre qu'elle avait préparée pour
                            <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>, avec toute sa tendresse. En y
                        entrant, malgré la chaleur torride qui régnait à <placeName key="marrakech"
                            >Marrakech</placeName> dans cette saison, elle fut pénétrée d'un froid
                        glacial et il lui sembla que la pièce était plongée dans une lumière
                        verdâtre; sous la blancheur de la moustiquaire, elle sentit la présence d'un
                        mort. Elle recula, saisie d'un frisson
                        et,<!--BC: 2019-04-10: This comma shouldn't be here.--> son mari, survenu
                        quelques instants plus tard, parvint difficilement à calmer ses
                        craintes.</p>
                    <p>A <placeName key="dresden">Dresde</placeName>, l'opération, comme toutes les
                        opérations ou presque, avait bien réussi, mais la pauvre <persName
                            key="lili">Lily</persName> souffrait comme une damnée et n'arrivait pas
                        à reprendre des forces. Le <persName key="warnekros">professeur
                            W.</persName> dut alors se rendre compte que l'organisme de sa malade ne
                        résisterait pas à cette dernière épreuve et, se sentant impuissant à la
                        sauver, il espaça de plus en plus ses visites. L'adoration passionnée de
                            <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> pour son chirurgien était devenue
                        son unique raison d'exister; aussi, privée de sa présence, ne
                        s'efforça-t-elle <pb style="page" n="234"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_40.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/> plus de réagir et cessa-t-elle de lutter
                        pour recouvrer la santé. Elle fut obsédée par la pensée de lui avoir servi
                        uniquement de terrain d'expérience. Les vacances survenant, le professeur
                        quitta la clinique pour prendre un repos rendu indispensable par le
                        surmenage de sa profession; ce lui fut aussi un soulagement de ne plus
                        sentir son cœur se serrer quand, pénétrant dans la chambre de <persName
                            key="lili"
                        >Lily</persName><!--BC: 2019-04-10: Here, we should have a comma.--> il se
                        rendait compte que, malgré ce qu'elle avait supporté et ce que lui-même
                        avait tenté, la pauvre créature était condamnée. Ce départ acheva de
                        désespérer la malheureuse fille et d'augmenter en elle l'amertume d'avoir
                            <hi rend="italics">servi de cobaye</hi> à l'être qu'elle aimait plus que
                        sa vie, et elle se laissa mourir.</p>
                    <p>Nous apprîmes tout cela par la suite, car la petite infirmière, qui avait
                        soigné <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> jusqu'à la fin, raconta son
                        calvaire à <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>, quand celle-ci se
                        rendit à <placeName key="dresden">Dresde</placeName>, un an plus tard. Parmi
                        ses affreuses souffrances physiques et morales, l'héroïque fille n'avait
                        pensé qu'à une chose : que <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> n'en sût
                        rien et ne fût pas troublée dans son bonheur. Elle-même, au prix de quels
                        efforts, lui cachait son véritable état, en lui écrivant des lettres pleines
                        de joie et d'espoir de rapide guérison. Le <!-- KK: 4/02/2019: what is the D'F? does it need an element on it?-->
                        <persName>D<hi rend="super">r</hi> F.</persName>, assistant <persName key="warnekros">du
                            maître</persName><!-- Elsewhere, Warnekros is called the maitre, so I think he should be tagged. AM 12.3.19 -->,
                        homme plein de cœur et de pitié, avait fait ce qu'il avait pu pour adoucir
                        les dernières semaines de la pauvre petite malade, venant la voir à tout
                        instant, lui envoyant sa femme, qui égayait sa chambre de fleurs et lui
                        apportait leur petit singe pour la distraire. Dans les derniers <pb
                            style="page" n="235"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_41.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/> jours d'août, sentant que son martyre
                        allait bientôt prendre fin, <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> avait
                        demandé le notaire pour rédiger son testament. Elle laissait le peu qu'elle
                        possédait à <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>. Elle demandait à sa
                        petite infirmière de la bien parer après sa mort, coiffée et maquillée comme
                            <persName key="wegenerG">M<hi rend="super">me</hi> Gerda</persName>
                        aimait à le faire, et en souvenir d'elle.</p>
                    <!--KK:4/2/2019: Here is a place I formatted it like it was in the text, but becasue it's formatted like a poem, I'm not sure how to put that into code; or whether it even needs to be shown in the code-->
                    <p> « <hi rend="italics">Quand je mourrai que l'on me mette, / Avant de clouer
                            mon cercueil, / Un peu de rouge à la pommette, / Un peu de noir au bord
                            de l'œil.</hi> » </p>
                    <!-- I figure slashes are the best way to indicate line breaks that are not paragraphs. AM 12.3.19 -->
                    <p>Comme dans la « Coquetterie Posthume » de <persName key="gautierTheo"
                            >Théophile Gautier</persName>.</p>
                    <p>Elle avait même recommandé qu'on mit du vernis rose sur ses ongles.</p>
                    <p>Au début de septembre, elle écrivit péniblement à <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> qu'elle allait beaucoup mieux et se faisait une joie de
                        pouvoir, sous peu, les rejoindre, <persName key="portaF">Nando</persName> et
                        elle, à <placeName key="marrakech">Marrakech</placeName>. A moi-même, elle
                        écrivit :</p>
                    <p>« <hi rend="italics">Je commence à me lever et pourrai bientôt faire quelques
                            pas dans le jardin. Je pense avec bonheur au jour proche où je pourrai
                            partir pour <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> et aux heureux
                            moments que je passerai parmi vous tous, qui m'êtes si chers, à
                            l'instant où je pourrai vous embrasser et vous dire toute ma gratitude
                            d'avoir connu, grâce à votre intermédiaire, ma vraie vie, ma vie de
                            femme. Soyez bénie pour cela, ma chère <persName key="allatiniH"
                                >Hélène</persName>.</hi> »</p>
                    <pb style="page" n="236"
                        facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_42.jpg"/>
                    <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/>
                    <p>Malgré la défense formelle d'informer qui que ce fût, la petite infirmière
                        avait écrit, en cachette, toute la vérité à <persName key="wegenerHo">Holger
                            Wegener</persName>, le frère que <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>
                        aimait tant. La fin était maintenant trop proche pour prévenir <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>, tant le déclin avait été rapide. Ce
                        fut, pour la mourante, une grande et dernière joie de revoir son frère. Elle
                        se sentit en paix, entourée d'une réelle affection et s'éteignit doucement,
                        sa main dans la sienne, la pensée au loin, au-delà de la mer, vers cette
                        terre d'<placeName key="africa">Afrique</placeName> qu'elle ne devait pas
                        connaître...</p>
                    <p>Sous une dalle de pierre blanche, qui porte pour toute inscription :</p>
                    <p><persName key="lili">LILY ELBE</persName></p>
                    <p><date>12 septembre 1931</date></p>
                    <p>reposent les restes de la petite <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>, mais
                        son âme, pure et belle, contemple avec ravissement le bonheur de celle
                        qu'elle a le plus chérie. C'est là sa récompense d'avoir tant souffert et
                        d'avoir tant aimé.</p>
                    <!-- There are the asterisks here forming a triangle-->
                    <p>Si — témoin si proche de cette histoire — j'ai tenu à en faire le récit
                        exact, c'est pour anéantir tout ce qui a été publié sur cette pénible
                        aventure. Dans une intention malsaine — ou burlesque — on a essayé d'avilir
                        deux êtres d'élite, dont la <pb style="page" n="237"
                            facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/books/Allatini_chapter_43.jpg"/>
                        <pb style="heading" n="Mosaïques"/> qualité d'âme et l'élévation de
                        sentiments pourraient servir d'exemple à bien des humains, surtout à ceux
                        qui les ont si injustement calomniés.</p>
                    <p>Je crois ainsi me rendre digne d'une mémoire qui m'est profondément chère et
                        d'une amitié que je place parmi les plus belles que je possède.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation">
                <div rend="chapter" n="?">
                    <head>HE AND SHE</head>
                    <p>It was near the end of the year 1916 that I met them. <persName
                            key="allatiniE">My fiancé</persName> was then fighting in the Italian army,
                        on <placeName key="dolomites">the Dolomites</placeName> front. During his
                        rest periods he was writing fairy tales for our future children. Since he
                        appreciated the talent of the Danish artist, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda
                            Wegener</persName>, whose drawings appeared in <hi rend="italics">La Vie
                            Parisienne</hi> that I sent to him regularly, he asked me to approach
                        her about doing the illustrations of his tales. I knew that she had done a
                        very pretty cover for a book by <persName key="magreM">Maurice
                            Magre</persName>, and so I asked my old friend to put me in touch. That
                        is how, several days later, we came to ring at the door of a <placeName
                            key="studioLille">studio on the rue de Lille.</placeName></p>
                    <p> We entered a large tastefully arranged room: antique furniture, Spanish
                        shawls, vases of flowers and the paintings of the Scandinavian couple,
                        because <persName key="wegenerE">the husband</persName> was also a painter. <pb n="199"/>
                        An accomplished landscape painter, he excelled in perspective. <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> and <persName key="wegenerE">Einar
                            Wegener</persName> offered us chairs and they sat down across from us on
                        a large black sofa, decorated with variously colored cushions. Thus, side by
                        side, they reminded me of characters in <persName key="andersen"
                            >Andersen</persName>’s tales, especially the ones in <hi rend="italics"
                            >The Snow Queen</hi>: <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda Wegener</persName>,
                        so blonde, so fair, personified for me the other <persName>Gerda</persName>,
                        the one who went off, risking her life, in search of her beloved
                            <persName>Kaj</persName> in the enchanted palace, while <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> was an exact replica of
                            <persName>Kaj</persName>, with a mischievous smile that played on his
                        well-drawn lips. The <persName key="wegenerG">young artist</persName> wore
                        her hair drawn back in a chignon on her neck, and two rolls, similar to
                        eighteenth-century hammers, adorned her temples; a black velvet ribbon
                        further brought out the whiteness of her neck. In a nearby cage, two
                        inseparable love birds — the one acid green and the other green ash — playfully
                        hit each other. They seemed to be a living symbol of their owners, who one
                        felt were tenderly united, inseparable as well. A similar clarity lit the
                        golden pupils of <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>’s eyes and
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>’s cerulean blue gaze. One had
                        the feeling that their clarity was the very reflection of their pure soul,
                        and I was drawn to them with a fondness that would soon transform into an
                        abiding friendship.</p>
                    <p>We talked about our reason for being there, and <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> seemed willing to do the work. <pb n="200"/> After admiring the
                        works of the two artists, it was agreed that she would write that very
                        evening to <persName key="allatiniE">my fiancé</persName>, to come to an
                        agreement with him, and they decided to meet the day of our marriage. During
                        the reception that followed the marriage ceremony, I presented the young
                        couple to <persName key="allatiniE">my husband</persName>; as with me, they
                        also became friends. We saw each other again in two days, for a long time
                        while having tea at <placeName key="viennoise">the Boulangerie
                            Viennoise</placeName>; it was there that all the details of the volume
                        were decided.</p>
                    <p>We left that same evening for our honeymoon in <placeName key="rome"
                            >Rome</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>Upon my return, five months later, we took up again our friendly relations
                        that became more and more cordial and affectionate. I had just lost
                            <persName>my mother</persName> and was expecting <persName
                            key="allatiniJ">my first child</persName>. My Scandinavian friends
                        embraced me and I found great comfort in their affection on days when,
                        without news of <persName key="allatiniE">my husband</persName>, they
                        increased their attention and tried to distract me as best as they could, to
                        turn my thoughts away from my anxiety.</p>
                    <p>In May 1918, the Supreme War Council of the Allied Armies was formed at
                            <placeName key="versailles">Versailles</placeName>. <persName
                            key="robilantM">General Nichola de Robilant</persName>, <persName
                            key="allatiniE">my husband</persName>’s commander and old friend of the
                        family, was appointed to represent <placeName key="italy">Italy</placeName>.
                        Upon his arrival, he came to see me, accompanied by his aide-de-camp
                            <persName key="carrobioM">Count Mario di Carrobio</persName>, as
                        handsome as a young god, cloaked in the superb blue cape worn by cavalry
                        officers. Hardly into our conversation the <persName key="robilantM"
                            >adorable general</persName> <pb n="201"/> asked me with a mischievous air: "What
                        would you say if <persName key="allatiniE">Eric</persName> were named to
                            <placeName key="versailles">Versailles</placeName>? Would you be
                        annoyed?"</p>
                    <p>I almost threw my arms around his neck.</p>
                    <p>Several days later <persName key="allatiniE">my husband</persName> arrived in
                            <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> to take up his new post and
                        shortly thereafter I got settled in <placeName key="versailles"
                            >Versailles</placeName> with <persName key="allatiniJ">my baby
                            girl</persName>. We led a delightful life getting together with other
                        young couples from all over the world, with many of whom we formed lasting
                        friendships. </p>
                    <p>The Wegeners came to visit us often in the charming villa that we had rented
                        and decided to spend the end of summer and a part of autumn in <placeName
                            key="versailles">Versailles</placeName>. They took a small apartment on
                        the <placeName key="hotelReservoirs">rue des Réservoirs</placeName> and we
                        saw each other every day. I recall, not without emotion, the exquisite
                        mornings in <placeName>the park of the château</placeName> in the company of
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> (his friends called him
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>), while he introduced me, all the
                        while painting, to the hidden beauties of the gardens. It was he who showed
                        me that each pond was of a different color, something that I had never
                        noticed. He had a childlike soul, pure, open to Nature and all of her
                        marvels. We got along very well; for that matter, who would not have gotten
                        along with <persName key="wegenerE">that charming boy</persName>, full of
                        sweetness and tenderness. He adored <persName key="wegenerG">his
                            wife</persName> and endeavored to spare her the least burdens of daily
                        life; it was he who ordered from art suppliers, such as color merchants,
                        wrote to editors, bought supplies, so <pb n="202"/> that she could devote herself entirely
                        to her art. For her part, she showed towards him an almost maternal
                        affection. Everyone in the quarter loved <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Bé</persName>, so polite, so full of tact and kindness. The shopkeepers
                        got him coal and the sweet necessities, even in periods of rationing when it
                        was difficult to obtain them. The two spouses never left each other, sharing
                        each joy, each emotion, sleeping side by side with their little fox terrier,
                            "<persName key="hvappe">Vâpe</persName>."</p>
                    <p>They left their studio on <placeName key="studioLille">the rue de
                            Lille</placeName> in <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> and moved
                        to <placeName key="champs">the Champs de Mars</placeName> area, into one
                        larger and nicer than the former. We were then living near <placeName
                            key="lAlmaPlace">the Place de l’Alma</placeName>, which allowed us to
                        see them often, even in that city where, because of distances, it is
                        difficult to see friends as often as one would like.</p>
                    <p>I remember a somewhat curious little event that happened to me at the
                        Wegeners. They had invited us to dinner to introduce us to one of their best
                        friends and oldest, the Danish diplomat <persName key="tb">T.B.</persName>,
                        a highly cultured man. </p>
                    <p>"You will see how irresistible and captivating he is," <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> told me, "his conversation is dazzling
                        and he knows the eighteenth century better than anyone, but he has one big
                        flaw: he cannot see a pretty woman without trying to seduce her, and I must
                        warn you that he is very persistent, especially with blondes."</p>
                    <p>That night at dinner she introduced me to this <persName key="tb">Nordic Don
                            Juan</persName>, <pb n="203"/> who had arrived that morning from <placeName
                            key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName> and who had to leave a few days
                        later for his new post in <placeName key="madrid">Madrid</placeName>. I was
                        seated next to him at dinner, and I don’t know if the trip had tired him to
                        the point of being a dolt, but he said nothing at all to me and dropped the
                        conversation each time I made an effort to engage him. After what <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> had told me, I must admit I was a bit
                        piqued. During the salad course <persName key="tb">my neighbor</persName>
                        placed his foot on mine, like a heavy caress. "This is too much, I said to
                        myself, he acts exhausted, ignores me completely, and then he thinks he can
                        play footsy with me...and in socks yet!" Since for the occasion the culprit
                        had removed his shoe, I tried to withdraw my foot without drawing the
                        attention of the other guests, a difficult task, my aggressor’s being
                        tenacious and heavy. I had hardly broken loose when he began again. I felt
                        myself turning red: to my horror, the keen foot was slowly climbing and was
                        now above my ankle while its owner kept his impassive and hypocritically
                        serene look. Such slyness made me lose it: "You’ll see," I said to myself,
                        and gathering all my forces I gave him a mighty kick. A dog’s cry rang out:
                        the real culprit was <persName key="hvappe">the fox terrier</persName>, who
                        got punished. This proved, once again, that one should be wary of one’s
                        imagination.</p> <pb n="204"/>
                    <p>I recall another little event that took place at the Wegeners. I was supposed
                        to have dinner at my friend <persName key="schildtBar">Baby de
                            Friedlander-Fuld’s</persName> place — now <persName key="schildtBar">the
                            baroness Goldschmidt-Rothschild</persName> — who was stopping in Paris.
                        Then we planned to go together to <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>
                        and <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>’s who were having a small
                        party. When I arrived at <persName key="schildtBar">Baby</persName>’s I
                        noticed that she seemed disappointed. "I’m furious," she said, "I wanted so
                        much to wear my new bronze tulle dress tonight and I can’t!" </p>
                    <p>"What happened? Didn’t they deliver it?"</p>
                    <p>"No, it’s over there, behind you, on the chair."</p>
                    <p>"Doesn’t it fit? Is it too tight, too big? We can maybe fix that."</p>
                    <p>"No, none of that, on the contrary, it fits marvelously well, but that animal
                            <persName>Hellstern</persName> didn’t deliver my brown satin shoes."</p>
                    <p>"Don’t you have an old pair of brown ones that you could wear?"</p>
                    <p>"No, the only pair I have is in a dreadful state; the tips are so worn that
                        they’re white and one can see the lining."</p>
                    <p>I had a brilliant idea: "We just have to rub them with a bar of chocolate and
                        no one will notice." We ran to the kitchen and, several minutes later,
                            <persName key="schildtBar">my friend</persName> came to the table in a
                        ravishing dress with impeccable brown shoes.</p>
                    <p>When we arrived at the Wegeners, she received <pb n="205"/> compliments from everyone. We
                        sat down and they began to play a little music. The little dog <persName
                            key="hvappe">Vâpe</persName>, who, as you know, has a particular
                        fondness for feet, came to lie down at my friend <persName key="schildtBar"
                            >Baby</persName>’s feet. As soon as she picked up the scent of
                        chocolate, she leaped on the tips of the shoes and began to lick them
                        voraciously. We tried to stop her, but she began to growl in a menacing way.
                        There was a general burst of laughter and we had to explain the origin of
                        this feast, which was a huge success.</p>
                    <p>But let’s get back to our business, that is, the painters. When one day I was
                        admiring the ravishing back of a nude painted by <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName>, she confided to me: "You will never guess who posed
                        for that back...it’s <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> in person. For
                        some time now he has been serving as my model, which helps me a lot since I
                        would have a hard time finding another back like it." The painting
                        represented a sort of blonde bacchante with short hair crowned with vines,
                        nonchalantly reclining on a day bed, her head slightly tilted and turned
                        toward the viewer. The legs were also <persName key="wegenerE"
                        >Bé</persName>’s. One would have sworn they were a woman’s legs, as they
                        were so long and tapered. I couldn’t get over it! <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> had taken a photo of <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Einar</persName> during one of the sessions, and I begged her to bring
                        it to the restaurant where we planned to dine with our husbands and <pb n="206"/> mutual
                        friends. We passed around the photo that amazed everyone. Our friend, the
                            <persName key="marquiseSG">Marquise de S.G.</persName>, whose husband
                        was late, cried out: "Let’s play a joke on <persName key="marquis"
                            >Emilio</persName>, he’ll be here any second." <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> would show him the photo of one of her friends and see
                        if he recognized <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>. Like a good
                        Neapolitan, a skirt chaser, the <persName key="marquis">Marquis</persName>
                        completely lost his head over this ravishing nude: "Oh, <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>, who is this? You say that it’s a friend
                        who posed to please you...but I must meet her right away. Swear that you’ll
                        introduce me to her." Hardly able to control her desire to laugh, <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> promised him, but added that the person
                        in question was rather shy and away from <placeName key="paris"
                            >Paris</placeName> at the moment. The more she presented difficulties,
                        the more upset the <persName key="marquis">Marquis</persName> became. He
                        even enlisted <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> to be a witness to
                            <persName key="wegenerG">his wife</persName>’s promise. We were all
                        laughing so much we were crying. <persName key="marquis">Emilio</persName>
                        refused to give back the photo. He kept it in his wallet and afterwards not
                        a day passed that he didn’t ask about the blond bacchante’s return. It got
                        to the point where once, leaving a soirée, he handed the famous photo
                        instead of his number to <persName>the woman</persName> tending the
                        cloakroom. "You old bastard! Who do you take me for?," screamed the aging
                        virgin, throwing it in his face.</p>
                    <p>Faced with the tragic turn the events were taking, we decided to reveal the
                        truth <pb n="207"/> to the red-faced <persName key="marquis">Marquis</persName>. He took
                        it badly, tore up the photo in a bout of black rage, and for weeks spoke not
                        a word to any of us.</p>
                    <p>I can’t help to digress once more from my topic to recount an anecdote that
                        dates from about fifty years ago, the hero of which is the <persName
                            key="naplesArchbishop">Archbishop of Naples</persName>, the <persName
                            key="marquis">Marquis</persName>’ uncle.</p>
                    <p>This prelate, known for his greed, had for years <persName>one
                            valet</persName> who served as a factotum, and to whom he gave, however,
                        only eight liras a month in salary. <persName>This servant</persName> came
                        one day to ask for a raise.</p>
                    <p>"<persName key="naplesArchbishop">Monsignor</persName> knows how attached I
                        am to him and that I would be heartbroken to have to leave his service, but
                        I cannot go on like this. The cost of living is rising every day and I
                        cannot even buy the necessities with my eight liras. I come then to pray
                            <persName key="naplesArchbishop">Monsignor</persName> to give me at
                        least two more liras per month."</p>
                    <p>"What you say is true," replied <persName key="naplesArchbishop">his
                            Excellency</persName>, "but with much regret, it is impossible for me to
                        give you more. However, since I understand very well that your current
                        salary is insufficient and since I am very satisfied with your services, I
                        want to do something for you. I will accord you, from today on, two hours of
                        freedom every afternoon, from one to three o’clock, at the time when traffic
                        is the <pb n="208"/> most dense on <!-- key ID? AM 11.26.19 --><placeName>the Château de
                            l’Oeuf bridge</placeName>, so that you can go there to beg. Thus,
                        everything will work out for the best."</p>
                    <p>And so, every day one would see, at the entrance to <placeName>the
                            bridge</placeName>, <persName><persName key="naplesArchbishop">the
                                Archbishop</persName>’s valet</persName> with his hand out. And that
                        shocked no one...Oh, sweet <placeName key="naples">Naples</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>I return to the Wegeners, not to leave them again. I asked <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> when she recognized <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>’s feminine contours for the first time.</p>
                    <p>"It goes back a long time," she answered, "even before the war. We were still
                        in <placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName> and I was doing the
                        portrait of <persName key="larssen">a well-known actress</persName>. One day
                        she telephoned at the last moment to cancel. I was furious, and
                        disappointed, having set aside my afternoon for her. Seeing me frustrated by
                        not being able to continue my work, <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Einar</persName> offered to replace the model, at least for the dress,
                        if he was able to fit into it. I was stunned to see that, not only did it
                        fit him beautifully, but also that he had a woman’s shoulders, magnificent.
                        I amused myself by completing the illusion by putting a blond wig that I had
                        gotten at the carnival on his head and making him up as best as I could. I
                        began then to paint and was surprised, in the middle of work, by <persName
                            key="larssen">the real model</persName> who came to excuse herself for
                        having broken her word. Seeing her dress on another person, she was a bit
                        surprised, but did not recognize <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>.
                        For a minute I let her think that a friend had replaced her to do me a favor <pb n="209"/> 
                        and allow me to make progress on the portrait. The timbre of <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>’s voice ended up betraying him and
                            <persName key="larssen">the young woman</persName>, laughing
                        wholeheartedly, couldn’t get over her shock. She invited herself to dinner,
                        had some champagne brought up "to drink to the good health of her new
                        friend, <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>." During the meal we baptized
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> with champagne, and from then on,
                        he posed often for me, dressing as a woman any chance he got. <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> loved this sort of work and liked to
                        mystify people, who invariably took him for a daughter of Eve. He was a
                        sensation at various masked balls and he impersonated <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> more and more. One evening when I had a cold and
                        couldn’t go out, he put on my prettiest low cut dress and I carefully did
                        his hair and made him up. He went with <persName>one of our young
                            friends</persName> to a dinner, followed by dancing, hosted every two
                        weeks at a club for artists and other cosmopolitan individuals, to which we
                        belonged. Except for these young friends and <persName>a woman</persName> we
                        knew, no one else was in on the secret. They introduced the newcomer as
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Einar Wegener’s</persName> sister and my
                        sister-in-law, adding that we were at home with the grippe. The beautiful
                            <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> was a big hit and stole the heart
                        of a cavalry officer, the <persName key="countT">Count of T</persName>., who
                        was about fifty-five or sixty years old. He spent the entire evening
                        lavishing her with compliments. She had to promise to allow him to see her
                        again. He insisted on escorting her home and left her <pb n="210"/> regretfully. Two days
                        later, as I worked alone in my studio, someone knocked on the door. Imagine
                        my surprise when <persName key="countT">the mature and mannerly
                            gentleman</persName> whom <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> had
                        described to me as her beau stood on the threshold, a bit shy, his arms
                        filled with flowers. I almost dropped mine.</p>
                    <p>"'Is this the home of <persName key="lili">Mademoiselle Lily
                            Wegener</persName>,' mumbled <persName key="countT">the poor
                            man</persName>. 'Would you do me the courtesy of telling her that
                            <persName key="countT">Colonel de T.</persName> would like to see
                        her.'</p>
                    <p>"I invited him to come in and sit down explaining that <persName key="lili">my sister-in-law</persName> was
                        out and would be back late. He seemed shattered and stayed for a good half
                        hour talking to me about <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’s physical and
                        mental charms. While I agreed with him, it was all I could do to keep a
                        straight face. I took the initiative to tell him that this young person
                        would soon be leaving to deal with family matters in <placeName
                            key="denmark">Denmark</placeName>. The <persName key="countT">Count de
                            T.</persName> finally left, assuring me that he would be back soon. He
                        kept his word. In the meantime our friend, <persName key="madameB">Madame de
                            B.</persName> who was at the famous dinner and witnessed <persName
                            key="countT">the soldier</persName>’s coup de foudre, came to tell us
                        that <persName key="countT">the poor colonel</persName>, more and more
                        irrational, thought of nothing but <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> and
                        even spoke of divorcing <persName>his wife</persName> to marry her. And so
                        when he came to see her, I told him that she had left suddenly the day
                        before for <placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName>. The wretch
                        was in despair. He confided in <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> and
                        told him he was surprised to find how little he resembled <pb n="211"/> his delightful
                        sister. ‘Perhaps in the expression of the eyes, but that’s all.’ It took a
                        heroic effort not to betray ourselves and maintain demeanor that fit the
                        situation.</p>
                    <p>"Afterwards, we had cards of <placeName key="copenhagen"
                            >Copenhagen</placeName> sent to <persName key="madameB">Madame de
                            B.</persName> signed ‘<persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’ on which the
                        young person confirmed the lengthiness of her stay, leaving him with vague
                        plans for marriage, all of which to calm the unhappy victim.</p>
                    <p>"Happily, time did it’s work and we no longer saw the <persName key="countT"
                            >Count de T.</persName>"</p>
                    <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> knew <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Bé</persName> as an adolescent taking drawing and painting classes at
                        the <placeName key="academyArt">Copenhagen Fine Arts Academy</placeName>.
                        The young artist had a deep affection for the student and he became her best
                        friend. <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> was very flattered and
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, madly in love, pined away,
                        realizing that he would never be anything more to her than a dear friend and
                        confidant. When she was seventeen, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>
                        had a romantic disappointment following which she became sad and indifferent
                        to other men who flirted with her. At this time she discovered that poor
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> was dying of love for her. He
                        had a heart attack and doctors said that this nervous state would be fatal.
                        Already wounded, the young girl could not stand the idea of losing the
                        person dearest to her, after her mother. She ran to <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Bé</persName>’s bedside and told him that she had reconsidered <pb n="212"/> and
                        consented to become his wife. The effect was magical and the young man,
                        suddenly better, was soon able to walk <persName key="wegenerG">the blond
                            daughter of <persName key="gottliebMr">pastor
                            Gottlieb</persName></persName> to the altar. These two children, barely
                        seventeen and twenty years old, shared a childlike innocence and young
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, a virgin like <persName
                            key="wegenerG">his wife</persName>, had never asked himself if he was up
                        to the duties that his new situation demanded. Naïve and knowing only
                        imperfectly what marriage had in store for girls, <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> was only half surprised at how sweet and superficial
                        the caresses of <persName key="wegenerE">her husband</persName> were. They
                        were perfectly satisfied with each other and when on some spring evenings
                            <persName key="wegenerG">the young woman</persName> experienced longings
                        that she could not define, their life together was so harmonious, so smooth
                        and tender, that she attached only a vague importance to them. After long
                        months, they noted that sexual joys were denied to their union, which did
                        not prevent them in any way from continuing to live in perfect harmony. They
                        had the same tastes in art, the same concept of life and, finally, they
                        could not even for an instant do without one another. They loved each other
                        and fought like two children. I can still hear <persName key="gottliebMrs"
                            >Madame Gottlieb</persName>, during a visit to <placeName key="paris"
                            >Paris</placeName>, cry, "When will you cease being children?" And
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> answered: "But, <persName
                            key="gottliebMrs">maman</persName>, never I hope!"</p>
                    <p>For some time, I had been noticing with anguish <pb n="213"/> (or perhaps someone had
                        brought it to my attention) that <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>’s
                        figure, already effeminate, was becoming more and more ambiguous: his
                        jackets seemed more pinched at the waist, his chest bulged, and his swaying
                        gait recalled that of an odalisque; even his voice was taking on feminine
                        inflections. <persName key="allatiniE">My husband</persName> had noticed as
                        well and "one," that is to say my family, my friends and acquaintances,
                        finally all the well-meaning tribe of those who please themselves by making
                        you discover, with touching solicitude, disagreeable things that you might
                        have missed. "One" was stunned, "one" disapproved of our relations and
                        friendship with a being so clearly ambiguous. I spoke to <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> about what I had observed; she answered
                        that she herself noticed it a long time ago, even though she lived with him,
                        and it was torturing her terribly. "But the most lamentable thing," she
                        added, "is that <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> also realized it and
                        suffered more than you can imagine. He notices that one turns around in the
                        street, that one laughs when he gets on a bus, and he hears outrageous
                        things being shouted at him. Everyone takes him for a homosexual, and you
                        know as well as I do that he is as indifferent to men as to an old shoe. Do
                        you know what happened the other evening at a dinner at <persName
                            key="bramsonK">Karen Bramson</persName>’s? There were a dozen of us and
                        since some were French, the conversation was in that language. Abruptly, in
                        the middle of the meal, <persName key="bramsonK">Karen Bramson</persName>, <pb n="214"/> 
                        who as you know doesn’t manage very well what passes through her head, cries
                        across the table to <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>: ‘You, <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Wegener</persName>, naturally you like men?’ And
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, witty as usual, answered her
                        smiling, ‘No, madame, you’re wrong, I am lesbian.’</p>
                    <p>"I even sent him to consult two physicians but one took him for a crazy
                        person, the other for a pervert, such that he came back more depressed than
                        ever. He even began to experience a kind of malaise every month and, what is
                        even more curious, is that his personality and mentality became feminized
                        more than his physique. He is only happy as <hi rend="italics"><persName
                                key="lili">Lily</persName></hi> and spends entire afternoons dressed
                        as her, reading poetry, embroidering, baking or playing with <persName
                            key="hvappe">the little dog</persName>. He says that like this he
                        forgets everything and feels in his element. You and I alone can understand
                        this situation, and I haven’t spoken to anyone else about it; that would be
                        to expose us, <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> and me, to those who
                        would ridicule us, or, like the physicians, take us for vile or crazy. You
                        must understand my desperation, seeing him suffer so and to be unable to do
                        anything..."</p>
                    <p>Towards spring <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>’s condition had grown
                        noticeably worse. <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> decided to spend
                        a few months in <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>, hoping that the
                        change of climate and of surroundings would do him good. They left, took
                            <placeName>a small apartment</placeName> with studio <pb n="215"/> in <placeName
                            key="rome">the Eternal City</placeName>. We didn’t see them again for a
                        long time and the news I received not at all reassuring: <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> experienced more and more vertigo,
                        headaches and depression; <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>
                        envisioned a prompt return to <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> if
                        this state of affairs continued. It wasn’t until the end of autumn that we
                        saw our friends again. They invited us to dinner in <placeName>a little
                            Italian restaurant</placeName> near them.</p>
                    <p>That morning I got a phone call from my friend, <persName key="warnekros"
                            >Professor W</persName>. — the celebrated German gynecologist — who was
                        passing through Paris. He was only free that very evening and wanted very
                        much to see us. I cancelled the date with the Wegeners, explaining the
                        situation. At about four o’clock there was another call from <persName
                            key="warnekros">the physician</persName>, held up due to a car problem,
                        on the outskirts of <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>. He was very
                        sorry but wouldn’t be back until very late after an appointment, and our
                        evening was ruined.</p>
                    <p>"Let’s reset our dinner date with the <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Einar</persName>s," I said to <persName key="allatiniE"
                            >my husband</persName>.</p>
                    <p>"No, we’ll see them another day. They’ll think we’re crazy to change our
                        minds at every moment."</p>
                    <p>At that moment I had a strange intuition that we should, at all costs, see
                        our friends that evening. It was like a command that I had received from a
                        superior will. I explained to <persName key="allatiniE"
                            >my husband</persName> that the closeness of our relationship with <pb n="216"/> the
                        Wegeners was such that they would not stand on ceremony. I let them know
                        that we would come by to pick them up at about eight o’clock.</p>
                    <p>Although we expected to find <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> changed,
                        we had a horrible shock when we saw him. <persName key="wegenerE">Our poor
                            friend</persName> was a shadow of his former self, gaunt, pasty
                        complexion, sunken eyes surrounded by large dark circles, with a hopeless
                        expression that I’ll never forget. He made a heroic effort to appear
                        lighthearted during the meal, but in his eyes there persisted the look of a
                        tortured beast that I could not stand. Not being able to contain myself, I
                        took <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> aside and told her about my
                        painful impression.</p>
                    <p>"I was going to speak to you myself about it," she answered. "I’m sick about
                        it! Battered by atrocious constant suffering, the poor soul isn’t able to
                        sleep. He feels his forces diminishing every day and if no one can do
                        anything to help him, I fear the worst. He can’t go on like this! His male
                        organs are atrophying little by little, his breasts are developing, he
                        endures tortures every month and I don’t dare consult physicians here
                        because of our first experience."</p>
                    <p>At that moment, I had a distinct vision of the tall figure of my friend,
                            <persName key="warnekros">Professor W.</persName> His passage through
                            <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> seemed to be not a coincidence,
                        but the hand of destiny. Seized by an uncustomary eloquence, I laid out my
                        plan to <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>: call <pb n="217"/> a big specialist the
                        next morning, explain the case in a few words and get an appointment.
                        Comforted and full of hope, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>
                        promised to do her best to send <persName key="wegenerE">her
                            husband</persName> to me the next morning. She had, however, a hard time
                        convincing him; at the last minute he wanted to back out, having abandoned
                        all hope.</p>
                    <p>The few details that I gave <persName key="warnekros">Professor W.</persName>
                        on the phone were enough to raise his interest; he immediately set a time.
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> arrived at my place early; he
                        was very agitated and I had a hard time calming him, to convince him that
                        everything would work out once he was in the hands of <persName
                            key="warnekros">the admirable specialist</persName>.</p>
                    <p>"I didn’t want to tell you in front of <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName>," he told me, "but I have decided to kill myself if I
                        can’t become who I really am, a woman. Think of it, <persName
                            key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName>, I am no longer anything but a human
                        wreck, a useless waste. Physically and mentally ill — I can no longer even
                        hold a brush, nor do anything to help <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName>— I refuse to be a burden to her. She has been admirable
                        with me; no one would be able to understand to what extent…except you
                        perhaps? ...I promised both of you to consult this great <persName
                            key="warnekros">physician</persName>. This will be my final attempt; if
                        he can do nothing, I am determined to die... it will be a relief to me...
                        and also to my dear <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>...when the
                        first sadness goes away. I will no longer hamper her <pb n="218"/> life as I have been
                        doing for a long time. In my case, it would be cowardly to go on living.
                        Look at what I’ve become!"</p>
                    <p>Saying this, he opened his shirt and bared the most beautiful woman’s breasts
                        that I had ever seen. I was overwhelmed and truly "realized" at that moment
                        everything that he had been telling me.</p>
                    <p>When we got to my friend, <persName key="warnekros">Professor
                        W.</persName>’s, I acted as interpreter. I had to explain to him, in German,
                        the progress of <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>’s metamorphosis
                        from the beginning. I waited in an adjoining room while he examined him. He
                        came back a quarter of an hour later, seized by an agitation that stunned me
                        in a man whom I had never seen as anything but impassive.</p>
                    <p>"Do you know, dear friend, that you have brought me a case that is unique in
                        the history of medical science, a case waited for during an entire
                        existence, without ever having been encountered: your friend is the only
                        true hermaphrodite who exists or has existed, for he had truly been a man,
                        an undersized, inadequate, atrophied man, but a man nonetheless in every
                        accepted meaning of the term. In general, the other beings to whom one
                        applies this name are not real hermaphrodites but only men afflicted with an
                        inguinal hernia that keeps their organs inside the body, thus one is able to
                        take them for women. Following a physical shock, an accident or some
                        phenomenon like that, the suspended organ descends abruptly and takes its <pb n="219"/> 
                        normal place: the so-called woman then becomes a man, but, in reality, she
                        has always been one without suspecting it. While <persName key="wegenerE"
                            >Wegener</persName> was first a man and has actually evolved towards the
                        feminine sex, which is totally different from ordinary cases of
                        hermaphroditism. He thus represents the first perfect example of the
                        androgyne. Actually, there exist in him both sexes and it is the struggle
                        between them that is torturing this poor being. If there is no intervention,
                        he will succumb in a short time, whether because of the struggle between
                        them, or by his own hand, since he is unable to endure this horrible
                        suffering much longer. I see only one way out: rid him of what remains of
                        his first sex and graft onto the ovaries — for he certainly has ovaries — new
                        ovaries, in good condition. Then later, when he can tolerate it, a third and
                        final surgery to open a normal path to genital function. I easily imagine
                        the masculine attentions with which your friend must have been harassed, for
                        hermaphrodites exercise a powerful sexual seduction on men, unknown to them.
                        All this will allow you to understand something that one is generally
                        ignorant of and which causes so many injustices and calumnies in our pitiful
                        society: many homosexuals are beings who possess a male organ in which there
                        are ovaries instead of testicles. It’s the same for a lot of lesbians who
                        have testicles where <pb n="220"/> the ovaries should be. These unhappy ones thus unjustly
                        suffer public scorn and disgust when their proclivities are — on the
                        whole — normal and not vile and perverse as one likes to make them feel.</p>
                    <p>"I will prescribe first for <persName key="wegenerE">your friend</persName> a
                        treatment to prepare him to endure the trial that awaits him. Towards the
                        beginning of March I will notify him and he will have to come to <placeName
                            key="berlin">Berlin</placeName> immediately where my colleague <persName
                            key="gohrbandtE">Professor G.</persName> will perform the first
                        operation. As soon as he’s recovered he will come — or rather <hi
                            rend="italics">she</hi> will come — to <placeName key="dresden"
                            >Dresden</placeName>’s <placeName key="womensClinic"
                            >Frauenklinik</placeName> [Women’s
                        Clinic]<!-- do we need this translation here? AM 12/2/19 --> where I will
                        perform the second intervention, in which his true sex will be revealed. May
                        he have <hi rend="italics">bon courage</hi> while waiting, which I’m certain
                        that he will have, for one can only bow before his valor." Then, addressing
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> himself: "Good bye then, dear
                        sir, while waiting to be able to say: Hello, dear miss."</p>
                    <p>It was a transformed <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> that I brought
                        back to <persName key="wegenerG">his wife</persName>! I have never seen such
                        a change in so little time. <persName key="wegenerE">My friend</persName>’s
                        face had gone from the most harrowing anguish to the most perfect serenity,
                        like those skies that, darkened by a storm, suddenly brighten, lit by a
                        radiant clarity.</p>
                    <p>During the following two months, poor <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>,
                        as if touched by a magician's wand, regained physical and mental strength.
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> told me often about his joy
                        and relief.</p> <pb n="221"/>
                    <p>It was on a beautiful morning in March that the two of us accompanied him to
                        the <placeName key="stationGareNord">Gare du Nord</placeName>. He got
                        settled in his compartment and, gallant as usual, he offered his reserved
                        corner seat to <persName>a young woman</persName> who thanked him with a
                        charming smile. Her "Thank you, sir," made us laugh. We knew that <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> was wearing a man’s suit for the last time,
                        about which he didn’t stop rejoicing about during the taxi ride. <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> thought that she had the time to finish
                        a very important commission and to rejoin <persName key="wegenerE">her
                            husband</persName> before the intervention but she had to leave
                        precipitously that same week, notified by telegram that "everything went
                        admirably well." Hardly arrived in <placeName key="berlin"
                            >Berlin</placeName>, <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>, examined
                        by <persName key="hirschfeld">Marcus [Magnus]
                        Hirschfeld</persName><!-- do we need Magnus in brackets here? AM 12/2/19 -->
                        and several other <placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName> authorities,
                        underwent, at the hand of <persName key="gebhard">Professor G.</persName>,
                        the excision that would make him, definitively, <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName>.</p>
                    <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> brought women’s underwear, a pink
                        bathrobe and an entire arsenal of makeup and perfume to celebrate <persName
                            key="lili">Lily</persName> and give her a truly feminine appearance.</p>
                    <p>Upon arriving at <placeName key="womensClinic">the clinic</placeName>,
                            <persName key="wegenerG">the traveler</persName> was first of all struck
                        by the change of the voice of <persName key="wegenerE">her former
                            husband</persName>. The operation was enough to transform timbre of his
                        voice and it was a pretty soprano who welcomed her.
                            <!-- in the editions I don't think we tagged "patient" so as to remain gender neutral AM 12.2.19 --><persName
                            key="lili">The patient</persName> rested, pale but radiant, on her
                        pillows after having valiantly endured the suffering that had released
                        her — finally! — from the chrysalis that had been so detested. She was pampered,
                        spoiled, <pb n="222"/> surrounded by flowers, solicitude. The few Scandinavian friends who
                        were in <placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName> visited her every day.
                        She was the idol of <placeName key="womensClinic">the clinic</placeName>,
                        one spoke of nothing but her, of her courage, of her sweetness and of her
                        extraordinary adventure.</p>
                    <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> quickly made up <persName
                            key="lili">her dear girl</persName> (for this was how she thought of her
                        now), did her hair, put on her nightgown and the pink robe that I had long
                        promised <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> for <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> and that she brought her on my behalf. One can imagine
                        the great amazement of <persName key="gebhard">Professor G.</persName> upon
                        entering the room, that very evening, when he saw, in place of his patient,
                            <persName key="lili">a ravishing young lady</persName> all dolled up,
                        perfumed and hair curled to receive him.</p>
                    <p>The weeks that followed were a dream come true for poor <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName>: for her first outing, <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> surprised her with a beautiful fur coat and then took
                        her to the stores to choose everything that was still missing from her
                        trousseau.</p>
                    <p>As planned, I had the honor to receive <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’s
                        first letter. The handwriting was so different that I could hardly believe,
                        while tearing it open, that it was written in her hand: in place of
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>’s thick down strokes, elegant
                        and light strokes flowed on the page, but what surprised me most was
                            <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’s style, virginal, sensitive,
                        delicate, the handwriting of a young girl and a romantic one: <hi
                            rend="italics">"<placeName key="berlin">Berlin</placeName>. <date>March
                                10, 1930</date>. <pb n="223"/> <persName key="allatiniH">Dear and great
                                friend</persName>. I am so delighted by your letter and I kiss your
                            dear name. I am so happy but so very tired that it is impossible for me
                            to write. The operation lasted one hour and I screamed for hours
                            afterwards (with a clear voice like <persName key="schumannE">Elisabeth
                                Schumann</persName>’s, according to <persName key="gebhard">my
                                superb surgeon</persName>.). <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>
                            lived and <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> will soon be a girl with
                            a proper passport. Spring sings in my heart and I cry from happiness and
                            I am fearless faced with all the suffering that awaits me. I adore you.
                                <persName key="lili">Lily</persName></hi></p>
                    <p>P.S. — <hi rend="italics"><persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> has
                            celebrated the funeral of his life as a boy."</hi></p>
                    <p>And again, <date>March 15</date>: <hi rend="italics">"Everyone here spoils me
                            and calls me <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>. They compliment me a
                            lot on my legs. That suits me very well. I will never be a strong-minded
                            woman. Don’t you think, dear <persName key="allatiniH"
                            >Hélène</persName>, that I should have pink, not red, nails for the big
                            operation in <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>? At the moment
                            I no longer try to contain my joy when I feel so happy. <persName
                                key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> is fading away more and more and
                                <persName key="warnekros">Professor W.</persName> is going to give
                            him the</hi> coup de grâce."</p>
                    <p>Several weeks later, two elegant young women left for <placeName
                            key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>’s <placeName key="womensClinic"
                            >Frauenklinik</placeName> and introduced themselves to <persName
                            key="warnekros">Professor W.</persName>, <pb n="224"/> who, having not yet met
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> and having last seen a gaunt
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> in a man’s jacket, couldn’t
                        identify the seductive creatures who stood before him, laughing.</p>
                    <p><placeName key="womensClinic">The Frauenklinik</placeName> is really a city
                        having five hundred beds and all the modern amenities. <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> was settled into the most beautiful room, and there too
                        she became the focus of general interest. The second operation was long and
                        grave. She came out of it very weak, but very happy, for the heart and new
                        soul of a young girl had given themselves to <persName key="warnekros">her savior</persName>, who had liberated
                        her from a martyr’s existence, in order to open for her the golden doors of
                        life and hope. </p>
                    <p><placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>, <date>April 1930</date>: <hi
                            rend="italics">"My whole life would not suffice to thank you for having
                            sent me to <persName key="warnekros">this extraordinary man</persName>,
                                <persName key="warnekros">this benevolent genius</persName> who gave
                            me a new life. I adore my dear <persName key="warnekros">Professor
                                W</persName>...I love him, but with a measure of respect, as if he
                            were an all-powerful god. Dear <persName key="allatiniH"
                                >Hélène</persName>, you will understand your little <persName
                                key="lili">Lily</persName> when I tell you that I have never seen
                            his eyes, because I have never dared look at him. Often I would like to
                            tell him something, I don’t get any further than smiling stupidly and
                            saying: ‘Yes, <hi rend="italics">maître</hi>.’ I wish he were a pasha or
                            a sultan so that I could be his slave. <placeName key="womensClinic"
                                >Frauenklinik</placeName> is an earthly paradise! I like my
                            suffering better here. So that is where I <pb n="225"/> am! I have a new pair of
                            ovaries that behave like little fauns in my painful stomach. My room is
                            the only one with a big mirror, when He gives me permission to get up, I
                            will be able to stand in front of it. <persName key="wegenerG"
                                >Gerda</persName> wants to do His portrait. What is this magic power
                            that affects everyone who comes near him? There is <persName>a charming
                                young girl</persName> who comes to clean my room, who said to me: ‘I
                            clean to save my life, if <persName key="warnekros">He</persName> ever
                            saw a speck of dust and scolded me, I would die!’ <persName
                                key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName>, <persName key="allatiniH"
                                >Hélène</persName>, how fantastic is it that from a life headed down
                            and at an end, He created a new life overflowing with hope, love and
                            spring. It’s the work of a god! What heartbreak, the day when I will
                            have to leave <placeName key="womensClinic">this clinic</placeName> in
                            the forest of white birches. I have dreamed that
                            <!-- removed tag for Warnekros around "He" AM 12.2.19 -->He will
                            continue to operate on me until there will be nothing left to Him but my
                            heart trembling in his sweet, fine hands. <persName key="allatiniH"
                                >Hélène</persName>, you have a heart of gold that you spend
                            endlessly for the happiness of others. I hope you will never regret all
                            that you have done for your little <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>.
                            I, who am a little afraid of my first steps in life, I feel protected by
                            your friendship."</hi></p>
                    <p>For his part, <persName key="warnekros">the celebrated surgeon</persName>
                        seemed touched by the sweetness and courage of <persName>his little
                            patient</persName> and showed almost paternal feelings <pb n="226"/> for her, to which
                        was now added a professional interest in this most fascinating of all cases.
                            <persName key="warnekros">Professor W</persName>. had a lovely respect
                        for <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>, whose admirable conduct in a
                        unique situation he appreciated. He had given her the privilege of going up
                        to his place to rest, or paint, in his comfortable living room. In gratitude
                        for everything he had done, she undertook to do his portrait, in his white
                        surgeon’s coat. The nurses and the domestics took special care of
                            <persName>the surgical patient</persName>, in order to please <persName
                            key="warnekros">the <hi rend="italics">maître</hi></persName>, all of
                        them showering him with fearful adoration, mixed with respect. He moved
                        about on the waves of feminine admiration like a sultan in his harem; the
                        devotion of the entire staff has become a sort of religious rapture.</p>
                    <p>One afternoon, while <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> took her siesta,
                        stretched out on a chaise lounge in <placeName><placeName key="womensClinic"
                                >the clinic</placeName>’s park</placeName>, <persName>an old
                            woman</persName> approached her and engaged her in conversation: "How
                        are you now, little lady? You seem to have better color and you will soon be
                        fully recovered from giving birth." <persName key="lili">My girl</persName>
                        began to get up. "And your baby, is it a boy or girl?"</p>
                    <p>"Neither," replied <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> without blinking,
                        "the Good Lord sent me twins."</p>
                    <p><persName key="lili">Lily</persName> left <placeName key="womensClinic">the
                            clinic</placeName> and <persName key="warnekros">her dear
                            savior</persName> with regret and went to complete her recovery in the
                        mountains of <placeName key="saxony">Saxony</placeName>, in the company of
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>.</p> <pb n="227"/>
                    <p><hi rend="italics">"He has sent us for several days in <placeName
                                key="erzgebirge">Erzgebirge</placeName>, between <placeName
                                key="saxony">Saxony</placeName> and <placeName key="bohemia"
                                >Bohemia</placeName>, but it is so cold here that we are going to
                            leave this place where we are shivering in our little summer
                            frocks."</hi></p>
                    <p>They returned to take leave of <persName key="warnekros">the
                            Professor</persName> and left for <placeName key="copenhagen"
                            >Copenhagen</placeName>, to get their marriage annulled and put
                            <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’s papers in order. She obtained
                        from the <persName key="king">King of <placeName key="denmark"
                                >Denmark</placeName></persName> a change of her family name to Elbe,
                        after <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>’s river, witness to her
                        renaissance. <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> spent a long visit with
                        her family, trembling when she went out, afraid of being recognized,
                        dreading the moment when her metamorphosis was made known, making her the
                        prey of journalists who would make her a national phenomenon. She didn’t
                        want to touch a palette, nor anything that could remind her of <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>. She spent her days sewing, looking in the
                        mirror, embroidering, doing her nails. She was modest to a fault, whereas
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> loved to recount salacious jokes,
                        she blushed at the drop of a hat and in contrast to her first incarnation
                            (<persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> was a confirmed atheist), she
                        became edifyingly pious, with an intense mysticism. Her second brother,
                            <persName key="brotherSing">Holger</persName>, and her <persName
                            key="sisterInLaw">sister-in-law</persName>, with whom <persName
                            key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> got along very well, were touchingly good
                        to <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> and welcomed her wholeheartedly.
                        Worn out from the mental tension of these last months and knowing that
                            <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> was in <pb n="228"/> good hands, <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> gave in to <persName key="gottliebMrs">her
                            mother</persName>’s insistence that she wanted to take her to rest in
                            <placeName key="italy">Italy</placeName>, and left with her for
                            <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>. They stayed at a family-run
                        pension owned by <persName>a Danish woman</persName> that they knew. It took
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> all she had to distract
                        herself and go out with Italian friends, for, since the annulment of her
                        marriage, <persName key="gottliebMrs">Madame Gottlieb</persName>, believing
                        that she had reverted to a time when <persName key="wegenerG">her
                            daughter</persName> was an adolescent, gave her no freedom and watched
                        over her like a dragon. <persName key="gottliebMrs">The old
                        woman</persName>, wanting to know <placeName key="pompeii"
                            >Pompeii</placeName>, decided to visit with <persName key="wegenerG">her
                            daughter</persName> for a week. Under the constant supervision of
                            <persName key="gottliebMrs">her mother</persName>, <persName
                            key="wegenerG">the young woman</persName> looked for a way to free
                        herself, to be able, finally, to relax. The morning of the return, <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>, disconcerted, walked around in the old
                        part of <placeName key="naples">Naples</placeName>, when she noticed
                            <placeName>a small church</placeName> that drew her to it mysteriously.
                        She entered and approached the altar of the Virgin, she prayed her to come
                        to her aid, to protect her and guide her life towards a loyal and good
                        person who would love her sincerely and with whom she could share the rest
                        of her existence. She left comforted, and that evening, in the train
                        bringing them back to <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>, she resolved
                        to let <persName key="gottliebMrs">her mother</persName> return to
                            <placeName key="denmark">Denmark</placeName> alone and to prolong her
                        stay in <placeName key="italy">Italy</placeName>. At the pension, a pile of
                        mail waited for her. As she moved towards <placeName>the hotel
                            salon</placeName> to go through it, a masculine figure got up to greet
                        her. She recognized an aviation officer who had been introduced to her
                        before her <pb n="229"/> trip to <placeName key="naples">Naples</placeName>. "Allow me to
                        offer you my respects, madame, and tell you how happy I am about your
                        return. I was afraid that you had left <placeName key="rome"
                            >Rome</placeName> definitively and this house had lost its charm during
                        your absence." <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> responded with a
                        few words and accepted a cigarette. After this first conversation <persName
                            key="portaF">Captain Porta</persName> waited each evening for the young
                        woman’s return, and their liking for each other grew more and more. The day
                        of <persName key="gottliebMrs">Madame Gottlieb</persName>’s departure,
                            <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> was surprised to find
                            <persName key="portaF">the officer</persName> waiting for her at the
                        station exit. "I wanted to be sure that you would still be here for me," he
                        said with emotion. Won over by the passion of <persName key="portaF">this
                            handsome and likeable boy</persName>, she agreed to listen to him. They
                        discovered that they got along famously, had the same tastes, and when
                            <persName key="portaF">Fernando Porta</persName> asked her to become his
                        wife, she accepted with a full heart after having told him of her past and
                        of the adventure, so unbelievable, that had cast a shadow over her. "You are
                        now doubly dear to me," he answered, "and admiration filled with respect is
                        mingled with my tenderness; <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> will be our
                        child. I understand that you do not wish to abandon her. She will always
                        have a room in our home, a place in our household."</p>
                    <p>When <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> told us of her engagement, I
                        felt great joy. She was finally receiving the recompense she so deserved,
                        the happiness that I had always wished for her. During a short trip to
                            <placeName key="rome">Rome</placeName>, <persName key="allatiniE">my
                            husband</persName> had the opportunity to meet
                            "<persName key="portaF">Nando</persName>" and found him <pb n="230"/> most charming. He belonged to
                        one of the best Livornese families and had just been appointed vice-consul
                        to <placeName key="marrakech">Marrakech</placeName>. He went there, at the
                        beginning of February, to arrange their settling, while <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> returned to <placeName key="copenhagen"
                            >Copenhagen</placeName>, to manage her affairs, organize her painting
                        exhibition and spend a few weeks with <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>.
                        She also wanted, during this visit, to convert to Catholicism, to share the
                        faith of <persName key="portaF">her future husband</persName>. Above all,
                        she wanted to show her gratitude to the Virgin who had granted her wish.</p>
                    <p>Upon her arrival, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> was greatly
                        touched by the exuberant joy with which <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>
                        welcomed her and received her recent bliss. The time passed fast and
                        delightfully, while <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> built
                        thousands of plans for the future, to which <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> listened with a melancholic rapture: at the beginning
                        of April, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> would rejoin <persName
                            key="portaF">her fiancé</persName> in <placeName key="marrakech"
                            >Marrakech</placeName>, where they would soon be married. The first few
                        days of June <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> would leave for <placeName
                            key="paris">Paris</placeName>; she would spend two weeks with us, before
                        leaving for <placeName key="morocco">Morocco</placeName> where the happy
                        couple would be waiting for her. The time passed quickly and soon came the
                        moment when a group of friends accompanied <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName> to the station. She was radiant in spite of a shadow
                        of regret at the thought of leaving poor <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> behind her. But it was only a shadow, in effect, for
                        wasn’t she supposed to rejoin her, and don’t two months pass quickly,
                        especially when one is happy. The two women embraced one more time: "Until
                        we meet again, little <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>, until we meet
                        again, <pb n="231"/> in <placeName key="marrakech">Marrakech</placeName>!" "See you soon,
                        dear <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>, as always!"</p>
                    <p>The whistle blows, the train moves off, handkerchiefs are waving; for a long
                        time <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> follows with her eyes the
                        slender figure of <persName key="lili">her beloved girl</persName> and, at
                        the very moment when the train makes a curve and disappears from sight, she
                        experiences a sudden and harrowing dread, a tightening of her heart, as if
                        she were seeing <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> for the last
                        time!...</p>
                    <p>April, May, June... I began to prepare for the arrival of <persName
                            key="lili">Lily</persName>. I broke the news of the death of her friend
                            <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName> to <persName key="allatiniJ">my
                            daughter</persName>, who loved him so tenderly. I dried her tears and
                        tried to calm her announcing that <persName key="lili"><persName
                                key="wegenerE">Einar</persName>’s sister, Lily</persName>, was
                        coming to visit us for several days and that she so resembled her poor
                        brother that she would surely replace him in her affection. Then I wrote to
                            <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> to be dressed in mourning upon her
                        arrival.</p>
                    <p>Having thus definitively buried poor <persName key="wegenerE">Bé</persName>,
                        I prepared <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’s room. To flatter her
                        vanity, I had embroidered sheets put on the bed, put a large mirror on the
                        wall, and I spread small luxuries around: candies, collars, perfumes,
                        ribbons, sure to please her.</p>
                    <p>The day before she was to arrive, we were totally stunned and disappointed to
                        receive the following letter from our friend: <hi rend="italics">"My very
                            dear <persName key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName>, I left from <placeName
                                key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName> for <placeName key="paris"
                                >Paris</placeName> Wednesday morning. That evening I telephoned
                                <persName key="warnekros">my Idol</persName> in <placeName
                                key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>, from <placeName key="berlin"
                                >Berlin</placeName>. <pb n="232"/> Then I came Thursday evening to <placeName
                                key="womensClinic">the Frauenklinik</placeName>. An hour later he
                            decided to operate on me again. I am so exhausted by the preparatory
                            treatment that I am undergoing, that I can hardly write. Maybe surprise
                            and a little fear have something to do with it — since I know that it is
                            very serious this time. When I say that I’m afraid, it is rather for
                            him, who is superbly courageous and will stop at nothing to make me
                            happy! Please forgive me if I don’t come to <placeName key="paris"
                                >Paris</placeName> right away, but when I’m in his presence I forget
                            everything else. In <placeName key="denmark">Denmark</placeName> I had
                            become a less timid person and for a few instants I had been able to
                            speak freely; but that was short-lived and all that’s left of me is a
                            humble little thing before <persName key="warnekros">this great adored
                                maître</persName>. I have already gone to bed and although he hasn’t
                            told me, I know that the operation will be tomorrow morning and that it
                            will be very complicated. Even death seems sweet to me here where my
                            heart lives forever, but I understand that death would be a betrayal of
                            him. Therefore, there is a legitimate little delay in my arrival in
                                <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>, dear friend, but when I do
                            come I will be marriageable and who knows if one fine day I won’t also
                            have children?"</hi></p>
                    <p><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> received a similar letter and not
                        only did she feel a violent disappointment, but in reading it she also felt
                        a justified furor. Hadn’t she recommended <pb n="233"/> to <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName>, during her time in <placeName key="copenhagen"
                            >Copenhagen</placeName>, to take at least a year’s rest before having
                        another surgery? She made her swear it, fearing the magnetic attraction that
                            <persName key="warnekros">the Professor</persName> cast over
                            <persName>his patient</persName> would persuade her to desire the
                        surgery sooner, in order to be following once again in his adored wake. With
                        that, it was impossible to do anything, even send a telegram, since
                        according to the date, <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> should be on the
                        operating table at the moment that <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>
                        was reading the letter. Taken by a veritable despair, by rage, confronted
                        with a fait accompli, she opened the door to the room she had prepared for
                            <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> with such tenderness. Upon going
                        into it, in spite of the torrid heat that prevailed in <placeName
                            key="marrakech">Marrakech</placeName> in that season, a glacial chill
                        penetrated her and it seemed that the room had been plunged into a greenish
                        light; under the mosquito net, she felt the presence of a dead person. She
                        recoiled, felt a shiver and a few moments later it was with difficulty that
                            <persName key="portaF">her husband</persName> was able to calm her
                        fears.</p>
                    <p>In <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>, the surgery, like all or
                        almost all operations, was successful, but poor <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> suffered like a condemned person and was unable to get
                        her strength back. <persName key="warnekros">Professor W</persName>. had to
                        admit to himself that his patient’s organism would not be able to fight
                        against this last ordeal, and feeling himself impotent to save her, his
                        visits became less and less frequent. <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’s
                        passionate adoration for <persName key="warnekros">her surgeon</persName>
                        had become her unique reason to live; and so, deprived of his presence, she
                        no longer forced herself <pb n="234"/> to react and stopped fighting to recover her
                        health. She was tormented by the thought that she had been to him only
                        something to experiment on. The time had come for vacations and <persName
                            key="warnekros">the Professor</persName> left <placeName
                            key="womensClinic">the clinic</placeName> to take the rest indispensable
                        to his profession. It was also a relief to no longer feel his heart tighten
                        when entering <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>’s room; he realized that
                        in spite of all that she had endured and that he himself had tried, the poor
                        creature was doomed. His departure finally caused <persName key="lili">the
                            unhappy girl</persName> to give into despair and to aggravate the
                        bitterness that she had served as a guinea pig for this person whom she
                        loved more than her life so much that she let herself die.</p>
                    <p>We learned all of this afterwards, for <persName>the little nurse</persName>
                        who had taken care of <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> until the end,
                        recounted her agony to <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> when she
                        went to <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName> a year later. In the
                        midst of atrocious physical and mental suffering, <persName key="lili">the
                            heroic girl</persName> thought of only one thing: that <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> knew nothing of this and wasn’t troubled
                        in her happiness. As for herself, at the price of much effort, she hid her
                        true condition from her, writing letters full of joy and hope for a rapid
                        recovery. <persName key="doctorF">Doctor F.</persName>, assistant to
                            <persName key="warnekros">the <hi rend="italics">maître</hi></persName>,
                        a man full of heart and pity, had done all that he could to soften the last
                        weeks of <persName>the poor little patient</persName>, coming to see her
                        often, sending <persName>his wife</persName>, who brightened her room with
                        flowers and brought their little monkey to distract her. In the last <pb n="235"/> days of
                        August, feeling that her agony was soon to end, <persName key="lili"
                            >Lily</persName> asked for a notary to do her will. She left the little
                        that she had to <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName>. She asked
                            <persName>the little nurse</persName> to fix her up after her death,
                        coiffed and made up as <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> liked to
                        do, and to remember her thus.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italics">"When I die let one put, / Before nailing my coffin, / A
                            bit of rouge on my cheek, / A bit of black around my eyes."</hi></p>
                    <p>From the "<hi rend="italics">Coquetterie Posthume</hi>" [Posthumous Vanity]
                        of <persName key="gautierTheo">Théophile Gautier</persName>.</p>
                    <p>She even recommended that they put pink polish on her nails.</p>
                    <p>At the beginning of September she wrote with difficulty to <persName
                            key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName> that she was much better and would have
                        the joy to be able, after a little while, to join <persName key="portaF"
                            >Nando</persName> and her, in <placeName key="marrakech"
                            >Marrakech</placeName>. To me, she wrote:</p>
                    <p>"I am beginning to get up and will soon be able to take a few steps in the
                        garden. I think happily about the not so far off day when I will be able to
                        leave for <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> and about the happy
                        moments that I will spend with all of you so dear to me; to the moment when
                        I can embrace you and express my gratitude for having known, thanks to your
                        intervention, my true life, my life as a woman. May you be blessed for that,
                        my dear <persName key="allatiniH">Hélène</persName>."</p> <pb n="236"/>
                    <p>In spite of having been formally forbidden to inform anyone whatsoever,
                            <persName>the little nurse</persName> had secretly written the whole
                        truth to <persName key="wegenerHo">Holger
                        Wegener</persName><!-- first time I'm seeing Holger Wegener with the tag. we also have "brotherSing" for him, but which should we use here? AM 12.2.19 -->,
                        the brother whom <persName key="lili">Lily</persName> loved so very much.
                        The end was now too close to inform <persName key="wegenerG"
                            >Gerda</persName>; the decline being so rapid. It had been a great and
                        final joy for the dying one. She felt at peace surrounded by true affection
                        and died gently, her hand in his, her thoughts far away across the sea
                        towards that land of <placeName key="africa">Africa</placeName> that she
                        would never know...</p>
                    <p>Under a slab of white stone, inscribed</p>
                    <p><persName key="lili">LILY ELBE</persName></p>
                    <p><date>12 septembre 1931</date></p>
                    <p>repose the remains of little <persName key="lili">Lily</persName>, but her
                        soul, pure and beautiful, contemplates with bliss the happiness of she who
                        was the most dear to her. That is her reward for having so suffered and so
                        loved.</p>
                    <p>If, as such a close witness to this story, I was determined to write an exact
                        account, it is in order to annihilate all that has been published about this
                        painful affair. With malicious intent, or as a farcical spectacle, one has
                        tried to debase two of the best people, whose <pb n="237"/> honorable souls and
                        high-mindedness could serve as an example to a great many human beings,
                        especially those who have so unjustly slandered them.</p>
                    <p>I believe in so doing to make myself worthy of a memory that is so profoundly
                        dear to me and of a friendship that I place among the most beautiful that I
                        possess.</p>
                    <!-- do we need this here since the translator is credited in the TEI header? AM 12.2.19 -->
                    <!-- removed the translator reference so the par. numbers line up across the French and English translation DB 4.14.20 -->
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
