<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="MIWschema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter to <persName key="knudsenP">Poul Knudsen</persName>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="lili">Lili Ilse Elvenes</persName>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation completed on <date when="2017-11-06">6 November 2017</date></resp>
                    <persName ref="kj">Kristin Jacobsen</persName>
                    <persName ref="mb">Maiken Boysen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding updated on <date when="2018-11-05">05 November 2018</date></resp>
                    <persName ref="tnm">Tyler Monaghan</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <!-- tnm 10/19/2018: translator's note on lines 52/91 is between Ervin (first name) and Magnus (last name of same character) resulting in a <note> fully wrapped inside the <persName> tag. Shall we move/amend the note, leave as is, or something else? also unsure how to handle [sic] @ line 43 and the translator's insertion [] @ line 51. -->
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="original">
                <div type="opener">
                    <p>Lindevangen 8-10</p>
                    <p>22-I-31</p>
                    <!-- tnm: can/should I add place=pageTopRightCorner to these <p> elements? Or are these only for <add> elements?-->
                </div> <!-- end "opener" div -->
                <div type="body">
                    <p style="salutation">Kære store <persName key="knudsenP">Paul</persName>,<note type="translator">Sometimes Lili writes Poul and sometimes Paul, but the correct form of the name is Poul</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Tusind Tak for Dit Brev.</p>
                    <p>Jeg skal med Sorg rette mig efter Dit Ønske og forandre Heltens Navn.</p>
                    <p>Han kommer saa til at hedde Hjalmar Hvide. Du skal ikke forbavses over, at jeg skriver pænt og korrekt om en Ven – jeg hører jo ikke rigtig med i Lumskebugten her hjemme.</p>
                    <!-- tnm 10/9: I don't think there's a <p> break after Hvide in the image, but the translators have one in the Danish (but not translated, English) version -->
                    <p>Hvor jeg glæder mig til at høre om <persName key="vibeke">Vibeke</persName>s Triumpher [sic] I Julen!<note type="translator">The word could also be Guben</note>
                    </p>
                    <!-- tnm 10/9: how to handle the "sic" above? -->
                    <p>Den vidunderlige i <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName> hedder:</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName key="warnekros">Prof. Dr. <hi rend="underline">Kurt Warnekros</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </p>
                    <p>Det staar endogsaa skrevet med dobbelt W. i mit Hjærte – ja, er endogsaa deri graveret!</p>
                    <p>Det glæder mig meget at Herr <persName key="magnusE">Ervin Magnus</persName>
                        <note type="translator">The name should be Erwin Magnus.</note> tror paa Bogen. Men jeg maa bede Dig forklare ham følgende:
                    </p>
                    <!-- tnm 10/9: use <choice> for Erwin in line above? -->
                    <p>Naar jeg ikke har skrevet Bogen som en Levnedsskildring, er det for at faa frem, at det drejer sig om to Personer <hi rend="underline">
                        <persName key="sparreAn">Andreas</persName> og <persName key="lili">Lili</persName>
                    </hi>, <hi rend="underline">der sjæleligt ikke hører sammen</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Det fremgaar nok mest af sidste Del, at der [er] en <hi rend="underline">Dualitet</hi> – eller var.</p>
                    <!-- tnm 10/9: how to handle the translator's insertion in line above? -->
                    <p>Det er først <persName key="sparreAn">Andreas</persName>, der fortæller sine Erindringer til <persName key="knudsenP">Poul</persName>, medens <persName key="sparreAn">Andreas</persName> havde overtaget, hvorpaa <persName key="lili">Lili</persName> fortæller Erindringer til <persName key="knudsenP">Poul</persName> fra den Tid, hvor hun begyndte at arbejde sig frem
                        <pb />og fik Hovedparten af Aktiverne i deres Fællesbo – og til sidst Eneindehaver.</p>
                    <p>Det fremgaar tydeligt af sidste Del, at det endogsaa er en absolut Livsbetingelse for Lili, at hun aandeligt intet har at skaffe med Andreas – og det <hi rend="underline">store Mirakel er, at hun føler sig nyskabt – ren og jomfruelig – og absolut ikke sjæleligt et Mandfolk, der er bleven<note type="translator">In modern Danish, the word would be blevet</note> til et Pigebarn</hi>!!!</p>
                    <p>Anden Del viser ogsaa, hvorledes <persName key="kreutz">Werner von Kreutz</persName> altid har holdt de to ude fra hinanden.</p>
                    <p>Det er Hovedpointet i Bogen, at der var to Sjæle i et Legeme – og at en genial Kirurg redder Pigebarnet ud af <hi rend="underline">fælles</hi> Skibbrud.<note type="translator">Literally, fælles skibbrud means common shipwreck.</note>
                    </p>
                    <!-- tag "the girl" and "a brilliant surgeon" above? It's clear who's being referred to -->
                    <p>Saa er jeg tilmed bange for, at den anden Form skulde tynge Bogen, og jeg ønsker netop at faa frem, at jeg er koket, sorgløs, overfladisk og pjanket – og det har været mig om at faa frem, at hvad der er af kunstnerisk, af Livsvisdom og alvorlig mandig Viden, kommer fra <persName key="sparreAn">Andreas</persName>, der var Kunstner og et honnet Mandfolk, medens min Indsats er en vis letbenet og tøset Filosofi! (Du ser, det er i Virkeligheden en Nedskrivning af Aktiverne) Bed Her <persName key="magnusE">Ervin<note type="translator">The name should be Erwin.</note> Magnus</persName> at ville høre med Sympathi paa dette mit Forsvar for Bogens Form.</p>
                </div> <!-- end body(original) div -->
                <div type="closer">
                    <p style="valediction">Din stakkeles lille Veninde, <hi rend="underline">
                        <persName key="lili">Lili</persName> Elvenes
                    </hi> Mille baisers à <persName key="vibeke">Vibeke</persName>
                        <hi rend="underline">
                            <persName key="lili">Lili</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <!-- tnm 10/9: should probably do additional markup on the line above, seems to be two signatures and a small PS? -->
                </div> <!-- end closer(original) div -->
            </div> <!-- end "original" div -->
            <div type="translation">
                <div type="opener">
                    <p>Lindevangen 8-10</p>
                    <p>22-I-31</p>
                </div> <!-- end "opener" div -->
                <div type="body">
                    <p style="salutation">Dear big Paul,<note type="translator">Sometimes Lili writes Poul and sometimes Paul, but the correct form of the name is Poul</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Thousand thanks for your letter.</p>
                    <p>It is with regret that I will comply with your wish and change the name of the hero.</p>
                    <p>He will then be called Hjalmar Hvide. You should not be surprised, that I am writing nicely and correctly about a friend – I do not quite belong to the in crowd at home.</p>
                    <p>How happy I am to hear about <persName key="vibeke">Vibeke</persName>’s triumph in Julen!<note type="translator">The word could also be Guben</note>
                    </p> <!-- idk what Guben means, it looks like Julen could be a place (needs tag?) or Christmas, which wouldn't seem to make sense here -->
                    <p>The wonderful person in <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName> is called:</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName key="warnekros">Prof. Dr. <hi rend="underline">Kurt Warnekros</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </p>
                    <p>It is even written with W. in my heart – yes, it is even there engraved!</p>
                    <p>I am very pleased that <persName key="magnusE">Mr. Ervin Magnus</persName>
                        <note type="translator">The name should be Erwin Magnus.</note> believes in the book. But I must ask you to explain to him the following:
                    </p>
                    <!-- tnm 10/9: use <choice> for Erwin in line above? -->
                    <p>Since I have not written the book as a biography, it is important to emphasize that it is about two people <hi rend="underline">
                        <persName key="sparreAn">Andreas</persName> and <persName key="lili">Lili</persName>
                    </hi>, <hi rend="underline">, who do not belong together mentally</hi>.</p>
                    <p>It might appear, especially from the last part, that there [is] a <hi rend="underline">duality</hi> – or was.</p>
                    <!-- tnm 10/9: how to handle the translator's insertion in line above? -->
                    <!-- tnm 10/9: translators removed underline from English version.. I have reinserted it -->
                    <p>It is first <persName key="sparreAn">Andreas</persName>, who tells his memories to <persName key="knudsenP">Poul</persName>, while <persName key="sparreAn">Andreas</persName> was dominant, whereafter <persName key="lili">Lili</persName> tells memories to <persName key="knudsenP">Poul</persName> from the time where she began to work upward
                        <pb />and got the majority of the assets in their common estate – and eventually became sole owner.</p>
                    <p>It appears clearly from the last part that it is even an absolute foundation of life for Lili, that spiritually she has nothing to do with Andreas – and <hi rend="underline">the big miracle is that she feels newly created – clean and virginal – and absolutely not mentally a man, who has become a girl</hi>!!!</p>
                    <p>The second part also shows how <persName key="kreutz">Werner von Kreutz</persName> has always held the two separate from one another.</p>
                    <p>That is the main point in the book, that there were two souls in one body – and that a brilliant surgeon saves the girl from a <hi rend="underline">mutual</hi> disaster.<note type="translator">Literally, fælles skibbrud means common shipwreck.</note>
                    </p>
                    <!-- tag "the girl" and "a brilliant surgeon" above? It's clear who's being referred to -->
                    <p>So I am even afraid that the other form should weigh down the book and I really wish to show that I am coquettish, carefree, superficial, and giddy – and it has been important to me to show that what is of artistic, wisdom and seriously manly knowledge, comes from <persName key="sparreAn">Andreas</persName>, who was an artist and a respectable man, while my contribution is a certain shallow and girlish philosophy! (You see, it is in reality a writing down of the assets) Ask Mr. <persName key="magnusE">Ervin<note type="translator">The name should be Erwin.</note> Magnus</persName> to listen with sympathy to this my defense of the form of the book.</p>
                </div> <!-- end body(original) div -->
                <div type="closer">
                    <p style="valediction">Your poor little friend <hi rend="underline">
                        <persName key="lili">Lili Elvenes</persName>
                    </hi> A thousand kisses to <persName key="vibeke">Vibeke</persName>
                        <hi rend="underline">
                            <persName key="lili">Lili</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <!-- should probably do additional markup on the line above, seems to be two signatures and a small PS? -->
                </div> <!-- end closer(original) div -->
            </div> <!-- end translation div -->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>